<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<quotes>
    <quote>
        <n>0</n>
        <div style="height:auto; padding-top:110px; padding-left:80px;padding-right:80px;">
        <p class="nav-title nav-style" style="font-size:30px;line-height:1.8;">
              The Avesta of today does not merely consist of the remnants of the Sassanian canon: its nucleus, the liturgical books (the Yasna, the Yashts, and the prayers), goes back to an independent collection with the canon.</p>
        <p class="nav-title nav-style" style="font-size:26px;padding-right:100px;">- Samuel Nyberg</p>
        <p class="nav-title nav-style" style="font-size:19px;text-align:right;">( "Sasanid Mazdaism according to Moslem Sources", <i>JCOI</i>, 39 (1958), 1-63, p. 23 )</p>
        </div>
    </quote>
    <quote>
        <n>1</n>
        <div style="height:auto; padding-top:110px; padding-left:80px;padding-right:80px;">
        <p class="nav-title nav-style" style="font-size:22px;line-height:1.8;">
              As a matter of fact, Zoroastrian priestly rituals constitute an interrelated network that is constructed according to varied degrees of complexity: the Visperad, Vendidad, and Nerangdin are ever more complex ritual elaboration of the Yasna. (...) To a certain degree, the Yasna is a structured arrangement, or compilation, of several units that, in different contexts and with certain modifications, are also performed as independent rituals. </p>
        <p class="nav-title nav-style" style="font-size:26px;padding-right:100px;">- Michael Staussberg</p>
        <p class="nav-title nav-style" style="font-size:19px;text-align:right;">( "Contextualizing the Contexts. On the study of Zoroastrian rituals", pp. 24-25 )</p>
        </div>
    </quote>    
    <quote>
        <n>2</n>
        <div style="height:auto; padding-top:110px; padding-left:80px;padding-right:80px;">
        <p class="nav-title nav-style" style="font-size:21px;line-height:1.8;">
            La collectanée du Yasna est une entreprise ancienne, qui appartient pleinement à l’histoire de la composition en avestique. Et c’est aussi, pour cette époque, le seul corpus textuel engagé dans le processus de fixation. Le Yasna, avec ses ancêtres et ses variantes, a existé bien avant l’idée d’Avesta, qui ne se réalise que dans la collection de l’Avesta sassanide, virtuelle pour nous, et dont on peut douter à satiété.
</p>
        <p class="nav-title nav-style" style="font-size:26px;padding-right:100px;">- Jean Kellens</p>
        <p class="nav-title nav-style" style="font-size:19px;text-align:right;">( "Contre l’idée platonicienne d’Avesta ou les Considérations revisitées", pp. 58 )</p>
        </div>
    </quote>    
    <quote>
        <n>3</n>
        <div style="height:auto; padding-top:110px; padding-left:80px;padding-right:80px;">
        <p class="nav-title nav-style" style="font-size:26px;line-height:1.8;">
            It is today becoming increasingly clear that the editions give a distorted image of the individual texts of the Avesta. The ritual texts, for instance, all accompany rituals and reflect ritual activities. The standard editions minimally take this fact into account.
</p>
        <p class="nav-title nav-style" style="font-size:26px;padding-right:100px;">- P.O. Skjaervo</p>
        <p class="nav-title nav-style" style="font-size:19px;text-align:right;">( "The Zoroastrian Oral Tradition as Reflected in the Texts", pp. 5 )</p>
        </div>
    </quote>
    <quote>
        <n>4</n>
        <div style="height:auto; padding-top:110px; padding-left:80px;padding-right:80px;">
        <p class="nav-title nav-style" style="font-size:18px;line-height:1.8;">
            En essayant de se représenter concrètement comment l’Avesta put être mis par écrit, nous avons perdu la simplicité qui caractérisait le schéma du Sasanidischer Archetypus : plus d’archétype unique, interférences des lignées les unes avec les autres au lieu d’un στέμμα aux arborescences clairement distinctes, subarchétypes peut-être fictifs. En particulier il semble qu’il y ait contradiction entre la démonstration philologique d’un goulet d’étranglement de la tradition, une corruptèle d’un seul manuscrit ayant entraîné tous les autres dans sa chute comme s’ils étaient copiés sur lui, et la démonstration historique qu’il n’a jamais existé de manuscrit unique de tout l’Avesta, ni une lignée unique remontant à un seul manuscrit adamique.
</p>
        <p class="nav-title nav-style" style="font-size:26px;padding-right:100px;">- X. Tremblay</p>
        <p class="nav-title nav-style" style="font-size:14px;text-align:right;">( "Ibant obscuri uaria sub nocte : Les textes avestiques et leurs recensions des Sassanides au XIIIe s. aden particulier d’après l’alphabet avestique", p. 130 )</p>
        </div>
    </quote>       
    
    <quote>
        <n>5</n>
        <div style="height:auto; padding-top:110px; padding-left:80px;padding-right:80px;">
        <p class="nav-title nav-style" style="font-size:26px;line-height:1.8;">
             The circumstance demonstrates that, apart from the official Canon, the liturgy was composed by a sort of earlier ritual assemblage of various sources (in Older and Later Avestan) following the different moments of the worship.
</p>
        <p class="nav-title nav-style" style="font-size:26px;padding-right:100px;">- A. Panaino</p>
        <p class="nav-title nav-style" style="font-size:19px;text-align:right;">( "The Age of the Avestan Canon and the Origins of the Ritual Written Texts", p. 86 )</p>
        </div>
    </quote>        
    <quote>
        <n>6</n>
        <div style="height:auto; padding-top:110px; padding-left:80px;padding-right:80px;">
        <p class="nav-title nav-style" style="font-size:30px;line-height:1.8;">
            Muß festgehalten werden, daß alles, was wir vom Avestischen wissen oder wissen können, eben auf diesen Handschriften beruht.
</p>
        <p class="nav-title nav-style" style="font-size:26px;padding-right:100px;">- Karl Hoffmann &amp; Johanna Narten</p>
        <p class="nav-title nav-style" style="font-size:19px;text-align:right;">( "Der Sasanidische Archetypus", p. 20 )</p>
        </div>
    </quote>
    <quote>
        <n>7</n>
        <div style="height:auto; padding-top:110px; padding-left:80px;padding-right:80px;">
        <p class="nav-title nav-style" style="font-size:26px;line-height:1.8;">
             We must not forget that phonetics were more urgently needed than grammar. A sacred text may be effective for ritual purposes without being fully understood. But it is usually all-important to preserve intact the correct pronunciation, and great care is often taken to ensure this.</p>
        <p class="nav-title nav-style" style="font-size:26px;padding-right:100px;">- Georg Morgenstierne</p>
        <p class="nav-title nav-style" style="font-size:19px;text-align:right;">( "Ortography and Sound-system of the Aveasta", p. 35 )</p>
        </div>
    </quote>    
    <quote>
        <n>8</n>
        <div style="height:auto; padding-top:110px; padding-left:80px;padding-right:80px;">
        <p class="nav-title nav-style" style="font-size:18px;line-height:1.8;">
            … la principale difficulté … consiste en ce que le Yasna et le Vispéred sont des textes liturgiques, c'est-à-dire des textes récités dans l'accomplissement d'un certain cérémonial. Il est clair que tant que ce cérémonial est inconnu, les textes, qui en sont le reflet ou le commentaire, ou si l'on aime mieux, qui en sont l'âme, ne se suffiront pas à eux-mêmes. La chose importante dans le sacrifice, ce ne sont point les paroles, mais les actes qui accompagnent ces paroles, les actes qui sont l'objet même du sacrifice et son accomplissement et auxquels ces paroles font allusion. […] La condition essentielle pour traduire des textes liturgiques, c'est de connaître la liturgie à laquelle ils ont rapport.
</p>
        <p class="nav-title nav-style" style="font-size:26px;padding-right:100px;">- James Darmesteter</p>
        <p class="nav-title nav-style" style="font-size:14px;text-align:right;">( "Le Zend-Avesta", p. 1. ii-iii )</p>
        </div>
    </quote>       
</quotes>