<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text xml:id="ParagnaLL12.4.3" status="created">  <!-- created, approved, updated--> <header>
        <creators>
            <creator>Porro</creator>
            <creator>Cantera</creator>
        </creators>
        <created/>
    </header>
    <div type="Stanza" sameAs="" n="3" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.4.3">
                
    </div>
    <Apparatus>
        <Critical/>
        <Commentary/>
    </Apparatus>
    <Parallels/>
    <Ritual>
        <Nerangs id="ritualNerangs">
            <ab>ParagnaLL12.4.3 (Ms. K7):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                pas čahār <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō</em> ḫᵛāndan <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō</em> avval ḫᵛāndan tā <em>š́iiaoθananąm</em> yekbār hum va urvarān kuftan <em>aŋhə̄uš</em> yekbār 
                kuftan <em>mazdā̊</em> yekbār kuftan <em>xšaθrəmca ahurāi ā yim darəɤubiiō</em> vāstārəm ḫᵛāndan čahār angušt daste az hāvan ǧodā kardan pas <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō</em> 
                dovvom be <em>š́iiaoθananąm</em> do bār kuftan <em>aŋhə̄uš</em> do bār kuftan <em>mazdā̊</em> do bār kuftan <em>xšaθrəmcā</em> tā sar ḫāndan <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō</em>
                seivom be <em>š́iiaoθnanąm</em> se bār kuftan be <em>aŋhə̄uš</em> se bār kuftan va se bār kuftan <em>xšaθrəmcā</em> tā sar ḫᵛāndan <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō</em> čahārom 
                tā vāstārəm  kuftan va hāvan šekāftan</ab>  
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "Then he should recite four <em>Yaθā ahū vairiiō</em>. He should recite the first <em>Yaθā ahū vairiiō</em> until <em>š́iiaoθananąm</em>, when he should pound (the <em>hum</em> and 
                <em>urvarān</em>) once; at <em>aŋhə̄uš</em> he should pound them once; at <em>mazdā̊</em> he should pound them once; at <em>xšaθrəmca</em> he should pound them 
                once. He should recite <em>ahurāi ā yim darəγubiiō vāstārəm</em> and lift the pestle four fingers from the <em>hāvan</em>. During the second <em>Yaθā ahū vairiiō</em>,
                he should pound them at <em>š́iiaoθananąm</em> twice; at <em>aŋhə̄uš</em> he should pound them twice; at <em>mazdā̊</em> he should pound them twice; at <em>xšaθrəmca</em> 
                he should pound them twice. He should recite it until the end. During the third <em>Yaθā ahū vairiiō</em>, he should pound them at <em>š́iiaoθananąm</em> thrice; at <em>aŋhə̄uš</em>
                he should pound them thrice; at <em>mazdā̊</em> he should pound them thrice; at <em>xšaθrəmca</em> he should pound them thrice. He should recite it until the end. During the 
                fourth <em>Yaθā ahū vairiiō</em> until <em>vāstārəm</em> he should pount (them) and hit the <em>hāvan</em>."</ab>
        </Nerangs>
    </Ritual>
    <translation>
        <include type="CAB" corresp="CABTrParagnaLL12.4.3"/>
    </translation>
</text>