<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text xml:id="ParagnaLL6.2.1" status="created">  <!-- created, approved, updated--> <header>
        <creators>
            <creator>Porro</creator>
            <creator>Cantera</creator>
        </creators>
        <created/>
    </header>
    <div type="Stanza" sameAs="" n="1" xml:id="ParagnaLL6.2.1">
                
    </div>
    <Apparatus>
        <Critical/>
        <Commentary/>
    </Apparatus>
    <Parallels/>
    <Ritual>
        <Nerangs id="ritualNerangs">
            <ab>ParagnaLL6.2.1 (Phl) Var. a (WīD 95.1b-2a):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                pas pad sē ašemwohū sē tāg ī mōy pad *kāhspan bē brīnišn ud pad ašamwohū ī čahārom abāz pādyāb abāg dast kunišn ud andar †warsdān bē nihišn pas wāz bē hilišn haft ǰām 
                xwurd ud taštag ud hāwan ud hamāg sāzišn pādyāb kunišn ud zōhr abar gīrišn ud barsom ud aibyāhan ud urwarām ud ǰum kardan pas srešk jām ī pēšēn andar ǰām pasēn handāzišn
                pas srešk ī čand ham-ēwēn andar čahār ǰām ka pēš ast bē rēzišn pārag ī zōhr čahrišwadag pad ān ǰām nigāh dārišn ud sē srešk ī warr ī ātaxš ī warahrām andar ān abganišn ud ān 
                ǰām pad abzār *kuwāhspan pādyāb ud hērbad-ēw didīgar ka-š nāwar dāšt estēd abar ān ō ātaxš nihēd pas harw sē tāk ī wars abāg *halk ī zarrēn ayāb asēmēn band estēd andar 
                ān ǰām abganēd ud haftād bār abar ōšmurišn ud az ātaxš ul gīrēd ud pad dast zōt bē abespārēnd</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "Then, he has to cut three hair strains at three <em>aṣ̌əm vohū</em>s. At the fourth <em>aṣ̌əm vohū</em>, he has to wasch them with his hands and put them on the <em>warsdān</em>.  
                Afterwards, he has to leave the <em>wāz</em>, to wash seven small goblets, the bowls, the <em>hāwan</em> and all implements. He has to takle the <em>zōhr</em> and prepare 
                the <em>barsom</em>, the <em>aibyāhan</em>, the <em>urwarām</em> and the <em>ǰiwām</em>. 
                Afterwards, he has to pour a driblet (of water) from the former goblet into the latter one. Then, he has to pour as many driblets into four goblets as it was before. He should check 
                that the portion of <em>zōhr</em> in that goblet is a fourth. He has to throw into it tree pinches of ashes from teh <em>ātaxš ī Warahrām</em>. He cleans this goblet with a *** 
                and another <em>hērbad</em> who has the <em>nāwar</em>, puts it in the fire. Aftwerwards each one of the three hair strains are tied to a gold or silver ring and throw it into
                the this goblet. He has to count 70 times and then removes it from the fire and they handle it out to the <em>zōt</em> with the hand."</ab>
            
            <ab>ParagnaLL6.2.1 (Phl) Var. b (Ms. M53):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                sē <em>aṣ̌əm vohū</em> az sar ō ī bun šustan pad ēk aṣ̌əm vohū az bun ō ī sar šustan ud abar xalk kardan ud andar dēg nihādan tā guš abar āwarēd čiyōn be guš āyēd panǰāh ud
                ēk bar šmurdan ud az ātaxš abar griftan barsom az dēg abar āwurdan</ab>  
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "(He should recite) three <em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū</em>s, wash (the <em>vars</em>) from the tip to the top. At one (additional) <em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū</em>, from the top to the tip. He 
                should then braid it in the ring and put in the vessel until it boils. When it starts boiling, he should count fifty-one and (then) remove (the vessel) from the fire. He should remove
                the <em>barsom</em> from the vessel."</ab>
            
            <ab>ParagnaLL6.2.1 Var. a (Mss. K7, RJ):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                <em>aṣ̌əm vōhū</em> čahār goftan va har <em>aṣ̌əm vōhū</em> az bon u sar šostan va pas se bār ḫalqe begardānand pas yek ḫalqe-ye zarrin b-āb pādyāvi bešuyand va ān 
                vars ḫalqe-karde dar gardan-e ān andazand va ān ḫalqe-ye zarrin rā be-sar-e barsom-čin konand va yek sokare porr az āb-e pādyāb konand va yek-pāre-ye var-e ātaš varhrām 
                dar ānǧā konand yaʾni xākestar-e ātaš be-sabab-e ān  nahānd čenānke ḥorm-e ātaš bālā na-yāyad va ān āb be-ǧuš āyad va panǧāh-o yek bār ān vars b-āb-e ǧušān foru barand  
                va bar āvarand zud āb-e sard b-ānǧā foru rizand</ab> 
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "He should recite four <em>Aṣ̌əm vohū</em>. During each <em>Aṣ̌əm vohū</em>, he should wash (the vars) from tip to the end and braid it three times. Then they wash a golden
                ring with <em>padyav</em>-water and put in its neck the braided vars. They place this golden ring next to the <em>barsom-čin</em> and fill a vessel with <em>pādyāvi</em>-water. 
                They introduce a small quantity of embers from an <em>ātaš varhrām</em> in it -- that is, fire ashes- with the purpose that the heat of the fire does not go up, but the water comes 
                to boil. They immerse the <em>vars</em> in the boiling water and take it out fifty one times. Immediately they pour there cold water."</ab> 
            
            <ab>ParagnaLL6.2.1 Var. b (Ms. K36):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                va se <em>aṣ̌əm vōhū</em> aǧ sar u bon šostan va fe yek ašem vohi aǧ bon u sar šostan va avar ḥalqe kardan andar dig nahādan tā ǧuš avar āvarid čin be-ǧuš āyad panǧāh va 
                yek-bār avar šemordan va az ātaš avar gereftan barsom-čin az āb avar āvardan va dudigar hamčun ān bid ke šuyid dast va vars fe pādyāv kardan va vāǧ-e urmazd gereftan va se 
                <em>aṣ̌əm vōhū</em> aǧ sar u bun šostan va fe yek <em>aṣ̌əm vōhū</em> aǧ bon u sar šostan va ḫalqe kardan va hezār va yek-bār fe pādyāv kardan</ab>  
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "(He should recite) three <em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū</em>s, wash (the <em>vars</em>) from the tip to the top. At one (additional) <em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū</em>, from the top to the tip. He 
                should then braid it in the ring and put in the vessel until it boils. When it starts boiling, he should count fifty-one and (then) remove (the vessel) from the fire. He should take the
                <em>barsom-čin</em> the water and repeat the action. When he has washed (the <em>vars</em> and the <em>barsom-čin</em>), he should wash his hands and the <em>vars</em>
                with <em>pādyāv</em> and take the <em>vāǧ</em> for <em>Urmazd</em>. With three <em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū</em>s, he should wash (the <em>vars</em>) from the tip to the 
                top and at one <em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū</em> from the top to the tip and braid it in the ring and purify it thousand-one times."</ab>
            
            <ab>ParagnaLL6.2.1 Var. c (Ms. RKS):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                se <em>aṣ̌əm vōhū</em> aǧ sar tā bā u bon šostan avar. <em>hił tiłā halγa</em> kardan tā dig be-ǧus āyad pas vars ke dārad be-dast be āv-e ǧus panǧāh va yek-bār avar šomārdan
                vars be-dur bordan vars pe ǧāy-e ḫod nahādan</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "While reciting three <em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū</em>s, he should wash (the <em>vars</em>) from the tip to the top and braid it into the ring until the vessel starts boiling. Then he should 
                (bring) the <em>vars</em> he is holding in his hand to the boiling water and count fifty-one. He should take it away (from the boiling water) and put the vars at its proper place."</ab>
            
            <ab>ParagnaLL6.2.1 Var. d </ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                sə. <em>aṣ̌əm vōhī</em> aj. sar. tā. bi. aōa. bun. šuštən. pə. ẏak. <em>aṣ̌əm vōhī</em> dīgar. aj. bun. tā. aōi. sar. šuštən. aōar. har. tirā. bāiiat̰. harka. kərdən. tā. dəg. bi. jōš. āiiətṯ. 
                pas. vars. ki. dārat̰. bi. dast. pi. āva. jōš. piṇjāhu. ẏak. bāk. avar. šəmārtən. pas. dastu. vars. bi. dīr. burdən. vars. pi. jāi. xud. nihādən</ab> 
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "While reciting three <em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū</em>s, he should wash (the <em>vars</em>) from the tip to the top and while reciting one <em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū</em>, again from the top
                to the tip. He must braid each hair into the ring until the vessel starts boiling. Then he should (bring) the <em>vars</em> he is holding in his hand to the boiling water and count 
                fifty-one. Then, he should take it away (from the boiling water) and put the <em>vars</em> at its proper place."</ab>
        </Nerangs>
    </Ritual>
    <translation>
        <include type="CAB" corresp="CABTrParagnaLL6.2.1"/>
    </translation>
</text>