<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text xml:id="ParagnaLL12.1.1" status="created">  <!-- created, approved, updated--> <header>
        <creators>
            <creator>Porro</creator>
            <creator>Cantera</creator>
        </creators>
        <created/>
    </header>
    <div type="Stanza" sameAs="" n="1" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.1.1">
                
    </div>
    <Apparatus>
        <Critical/>
        <Commentary/>
    </Apparatus>
    <Parallels/>
    <Ritual>
        <Nerangs id="ritualNerangs">
            <ab>ParagnaLL12.1.1 Var. a (Mss. K7, RJ):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                pas hum pyāle va hum urvarān barad va ān yek sokure-ye ḫāli nahand ān kasi ke ātaš miforuzad yek šāḫ-e esm va buy nahand va varsdān piš āwarad sar-aš begirad vars rā andar 
                hum pyāle andāzad ān kasi ke hum pyāle be-dast dārad va hāvan daste u čab dast-e māhruy ǧā-i ke hum urwarān nahāde ast naheš pas angušt-e čab-e ḫod moḥkam var ruy-e ān 
                vars va ḫalqe nahad čenānke vars rā binad pas <em>xšnaoθra ahurahe mazdā̊ ašəm vōhū</em> se <em>frauuarāne</em> gāh ānče bid <em>zaraθuštrahe spitamahe aṣ̌aonō 
                    frauuaṣ̌əē xšnaoθra y. v. x.  f.  yaϑā ahū vairiiō zaotā</em> tā <em>mraotū</em></ab> 
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "Then, he brings the <em>hum-pyāle</em>, the <em>hum</em> and the <em>urvarān</em> and puts an empty cup. The one who kindles the fire, puts a piece of <em>esm</em> 
                and <em>buy</em>, brings the <em>varasdān</em> nearby, removes its lid and puts the <em>vars</em> in the <em>hum-pyāle</em>. The one who has the <em>hum-pyāle</em>
                has to place the <em>hāvan</em> and the pestle on the left side of <em>māhruy</em> where he has put the <em>hum</em> and the <em>urvarān</em>. Therefore, he should
                put firmly his left (hand's) finger on the <em>vars</em> and the ring so that he sees the <em>vars</em>. Then (he should recite) <em>xšnaoϑra ahurahe mazdā̊</em> and three 
                <em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū</em>s and <em>frauuarāne</em> with the corresponding <em>gāh</em> (and the <em>šnūman</em>) <em>zaraϑuštarahe spitāmahe aṣ̌aonō frauuaṣ̌ə̄ xšnaoϑra
                    ẏ. v. x. f. </em> and <em>ẏaϑā ahū vairiiō zaotā</em> until <em>mraotū</em>."</ab>
            
            <ab>ParagnaLL12.1.1 Var. b (Ms. K36):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                nirang farāhum gereftan fe nām-e dādār-e urmazd ke farāhum girid esm va buy yek tāk az kuste-ye rāst be nahešn va hum va urvarām fe čandaš be peydāyinešn va hum fe kuste
                se gereh va fe yašte post va yek gereh va urvarām andar hami nihešn tā avāǧ u be-har hum āyad fe pādyāv ke az āne zur avā šuyad šāyad ke yek dudigar fe in kār ul šuyad šāyad
                <em>aṣ̌əm vohī</em> se goftan <em>frauuarāne zaraθuštrahe spitamahe aṣ̌aonō frauuaṣ̌əē xšnaoθra yasnāi. v. x.  f.  yaϑā ahī vairiiō zaotā</em> tā ǧā-ye gofan</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "Instructions for taking te <em>farāhum</em>. In the name of the creator <em>Urmazd</em>. The one takes the <em>farāhim</em>, he has to put a piece of <em>esm</em> 
                and <em>bu</em> to the right and show the <em>hum</em> and <em>urvarām</em>. He should put in the same (saucer) three pieces (of <em>hum</em>) and and piece 
                <em>urvarām</em> so that he can access again any (piece of) <em>hum</em> and can wash again with the with the <em>pādyāv</em> from the <em>zur</em> so that he 
                can wash them again to this purpose. He should recite three <em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū</em>s and the <em>frauuarāne</em> (with the <em>šnūman</em>) <em>zaraθuštrahe spitamahe
                    aṣ̌aonō frauuaṣ̌əē xšnaoθra yasnāi v. x. f.</em>"</ab> 
        </Nerangs>
    </Ritual>
    <translation>
        <include type="CAB" corresp="CABTrParagnaLL12.1.1"/>
    </translation>
</text>