<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text xml:id="ParagnaLL10.2.1" status="created">  <!-- created, approved, updated--> <header>
        <creators>
            <creator>Porro</creator>
            <creator>Cantera</creator>
        </creators>
        <created/>
    </header>
    <div type="Stanza" sameAs="" n="1" xml:id="ParagnaLL10.2.1">
                
    </div>
    <Apparatus>
        <Critical/>
        <Commentary/>
    </Apparatus>
    <Parallels/>
    <Ritual>
        <Nerangs id="ritualNerangs">
            <ab>ParagnaLL10.2.1 Var. a (Mss. K7, RJ):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                pas yek-yek barsom sar čidan va šemordan pas b-āb-e pādyāb šostan be-čahār <em>aṣ̌em vohū</em> se <em>aṣ̌em vohū</em> az bon u sar šuyad va yek <em>aṣ̌əm vōhū</em> 
                az sar u bon šuyad va barsom be pāy-e māhruy nahādan</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "Then, he has to cut the end of the <em>barsom</em>, one to one, and count (the twigs) and wash them with <em>pādyāb</em>. (He has to recite) four <em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū</em>s.
                During the three first <em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū</em>, he washes them from the bottom to the top and during one <em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū</em> from the top to the bottom. He has to put the 
                <em>barsom</em> at the bottom of the <em>māhruy</em>."</ab>
            
            <ab>ParagnaLL10.2.1 Var. b (Mss. K36, 31, 19):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                <em>aṣ̌əm vohū</em> se be guyešn va se bār az bon tā sar-e barsom be-šoyešn yeki digar be-guyešn va yekbār az sar tā bon be-šuyešn čin avāyad kardan ke har bār-i be har ǧā-ye 
                pādyāv avar resid ke fa se-bār besyār berasīd šāyad</ab> 
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "He has to recite three <em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū</em>s and to wash (the twigs) three times from the tip to the top of the <em>barsom</em> and one time from the top to the tip as it must
                been done so that each single time he reaches that every parts is clean when it reaches entirely for three times, then it is allowed."</ab> 
        </Nerangs>

        <Quotations id="ritualQuotations">
            <ab>N28.16 (Mss. K7, RJ):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                <em>aṣ̌əm vohū</em> čahār bē gōwišn u-š harw sē bār az bun ō sar šōyišn u-š ēk-ē did bē gōwišn u-š ēk bār az sar ō bun šōyišn u-š ēdōn kunišn kū harw gyāg *pas bē ēk pas harw 
                tāg pēš* pādyāb abar bē rasēd ast kē ēdōn gōwēd ya ka harw čahār bār rasēd ā šāyēd ast kē ēdōn gōwēd ay hād andar ōy sē *bār šōyēd ā šāyēd.</ab> 
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "Then one should take the <em>bāj</em> and recite <em>aṣ̌əm vohū</em> four times. The first three times one should wash (the <em>barsom</em>) from bottom to top, and 
                recite another (a.v.) and (then) wash it from top to bottom, and one should do this in such a way that (they wash) all places and then one (more). The <em>pādyāb</em> reaches 
                each twig before and after. There is one who says: When (the <em>pādyāb</em>) reaches them every four times, then it is allowed. There is one who says that when he washes (them) in it 
                three times, it is allowed."</ab>   
        </Quotations>
    </Ritual>
    <translation>
        <include type="CAB" corresp="CABTrParagnaLL10.2.1"/>
    </translation>
</text>