<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text xml:id="ParagnaLL7.3.1" status="created">  <!-- created, approved, updated--> <header>
        <creators>
            <creator>Porro</creator>
            <creator>Cantera</creator>
        </creators>
        <created/>
    </header>
    <div type="Stanza" sameAs="" n="1" xml:id="ParagnaLL7.3.1">
                
    </div>
    <Apparatus>
        <Critical/>
        <Commentary/>
    </Apparatus>
    <Parallels/>
    <Ritual>
        <Nerangs id="ritualNerangs">
            <ab>ParagnaLL7.3.1 (Phl.) (WīD95.3a)</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                pas wars andar harw dō dast griftag wāz hilišn <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō</em> dō <em>yasnəmca</em> tā ān <em>āfrīnāmi ahurahe mazdå raēuuatō xᵛarənaŋhatō</em> andar wāz 
                ham-ēdōn hixtēnd ud wars pādyāb abāz andarrōn ī †warsdān nihišn pas hamāg sāzišn abāz az sar bē šōyišn ud āb az wastarg pādyābīh bē †pālāyišn pas hamāg ābzār ud urwēs 
                abāz sē bār pādyāb kardag ātaxš abrōzēnānd ud †sāzišn hamāg xūb bē nihišn pas wars pazīdag bē āwarēd</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "Afterwards, once he has taken the <em>wars</em> with both hands, he has to leave the <em>wāz</em>, (reciting) two <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō</em> and <em>yasnəmca</em>
                up to <em>āfrīnāmi ahurahe mazdå raēuuatō xᵛarənaŋhatō</em>. During the <em>wāz</em>, they draw water and wash again the <em>wars</em>. He should put it in the innner 
                of the <em>warsdān</em>. Afterwards, he has to wash all the implement from the top and filter the water though clean cloth. Then, after having clean all tools and the <em>urwēs</em> 
                again three times, they shall kindle the fire and to dispose correctly all implements. Then, he brings the boiled <em>wars</em>."</ab>
            
            <ab>ParagnaLL7.3.1 (Ms. K7):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                va <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō</em> do <em>yasnəmca</em> tā <em>ahurahe mazdā̊ raēuuatō xvarənaŋhatō</em> sar-aš moḥkam be-nahand va dar yazešngāh moḥkam be-nahand 
                pas yek <em>aṣ̌əm vohū ahmāi raēsca</em> OD <em>hazaŋhrəm</em> OD <em>jasa.mē</em> tamām ḫᵛāndan</ab> 
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "(He should recite) two <em>Yaθā Ahū Vairiiō</em>s and <em>yasnəmca</em> until (the <em>šnūman</em>) <em>ahurahe mazdā̊ raēuuatō xvarənaŋhatō</em>. They fix its 
                end and they deposite it on the <em>yazešngāh</em>. Then he should recite one <em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū ahmāi raēšca</em> until <em>hazaŋhrəm</em> and <em>jasa.me</em> complete."</ab>
        </Nerangs>
    </Ritual>
    <translation>
        <include type="CAB" corresp="CABTrParagnaLL7.3.1"/>
    </translation>
</text>