<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text xml:id="ParagnaLL8.2.1" status="created">  <!-- created, approved, updated--> <header>
        <creators>
            <creator>Porro</creator>
            <creator>Cantera</creator>
        </creators>
        <created/>
    </header>
    <div type="Stanza" sameAs="" n="1" xml:id="ParagnaLL8.2.1">
                
    </div>
    <Apparatus>
        <Critical/>
        <Commentary/>
    </Apparatus>
    <Parallels/>
    <Ritual>
        <Nerangs id="ritualNerangs">
            <ab>ParagnaLL8.2.1. Var. a (Phl.) (Ms. K43):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                <em>frā.tē staōmaide ahurāne ahurahe vaŋhīš yasnąsca vahmąsca hubəraitīšca ušta.bəraitīšca vaṇta.bəraitīšca yazatanąm</em> abar āb <em>ϑβā</em> andar wardēnišn <em>aṣ̌aōnąm</em> 
                pādyāb andar hilišn <em>kuxšnaēša</em> purr bē kunišn <em>us.bī.barāmi</em> az āb ul dārišn <em>raϑβasca bərəzatō</em> andar rāh-ē <em>gāϑā̊sca srāuuaiiōit̰</em> ān gyāg bē nihēd</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "(He should recite) above the water: <em>frā.tē staōmaide ahurāne ahurahe vaŋhīš yasnąsca vahmąsca hubəraitīšca ušta.bəraitīšca vaṇta.bəraitīšca yazatanąm</em>. At <em>ϑβā</em>
                he should turn the cups. At <em>aṣ̌aōnąm</em> he should fill them with a little consecrated water. At <em>kuxšnaēša</em> he should fill them completely. At <em>us.bī.barāmi</em>
                he should lift them out of the water. (He recites) <em>raϑβasca bərəzatō</em> on the way and <em>gāϑā̊sca srāuuaiiōit̰</em> there (where) he put them down."</ab>
            
            <ab>ParagnaLL8.2.1. Var. b (Phl.) (WīD95.4):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                pas <em>frā.tē staomaide</em> tā <em>yazatanąm θβā</em> harw dō ǰām andar wardišn <em>ašaonąm</em> pādyāb andak-ēw andar kunišn <em>kuxšnūša</em> purr bē 
                kunišn <em>usbī.barāmi</em> az āb ul dārišn <em>raθβasca bərəzatō</em> andar rāh-ēw <em>gāθā̊sca srāuuaiiōit̰</em> ān gyāg kē abar hāwan bē nihēd kē dō-mardīh kār 
                framāyēnd ā-šān ēk az did wāz gīrišn <em>raθβasca bərəzatō</em> *ōh gōwišn kē bē barēd tā az sē gām ī āb bē šawišn hamē ka a-pādyāb bē bawēd u-š <em>frā.tə̄ staomide</em> 
                abāz gōwišn ka az sē gām ī āb bē šawišn ā-š wāz abāz gīrišn</ab> 
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "Afterwards, (he should recite <em>frā.tē staomaide</em> up to <em>yazatanąm θβā</em> and he should turn the cups. At <em>ašaonąm</em> he has to pour a driblet of 
                <em>pādyāb</em>. At <em>kuxšnūša</em> he should fill them completely. At <em>usbī.barāmi</em> he should lift them out of the water. (He should recite) <em>raθβasca bərəzatō</em>
                on the way and <em>gāθā̊sca srāuuaiiōit̰</em> there, where he would put them on the <em>hāwan</em>. If they order that it is a job for two persons, then they should take the
                <em>wāz</em> one from the other and recite <em>raθβasca bərəzatō</em>. The one who brings them, until he goes three steps away from water, if something becomes impure,
                he has to recite again <em>frā.tə̄ staomide</em>. When he has gone three steps way from the water, he has to take again the <em>wāz</em>."</ab>
            
            <ab>ParagnaLL8.2.1. Var. a (Pers.) (Mss. K7, RJ):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                <em>frā.tē staōmaiδe ahurāne ahurahe vaŋhīš yasnąsca vahmąsca hubərətīsca uštā.bərətīsca vaṇta.bərətīsca yazatanąm ϑβā aṣ̌aōnąm kuxšnīša</em> āb andar sokure-ye do tā 
                porr kardan <em>us.bībarāma</em> se bār sokure andar bālā va šib āvardan pas <em>raϑβasca bərəzatō gāϑā̊sca srāuuaiiōit̰</em> sokure andar ruy-e sang-e urwis nahādan</ab> 
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "<em>frā.tē staōmaiδe ahurāne ahurahe vaŋhīš yasnąsca vahmąsca hubərətīsca uštā.bərətīsca vaṇta.bərətīsca yazatanąm ϑβā aṣ̌aōnąm kuxšnīša</em>. He should fill the two cups
                with water. At <em>us.bībarāma</em> he should move the cups up and down three times and then at <em>raϑβasca bərəzatō gāϑā̊sca srāuuaiiōit̰</em> he should put them on the
                surface of the stone <em>urwis</em>."</ab> 
            
            <ab>ParagnaLL8.2.1. Var. b (Pers.) (Ms. 89):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                <em>frā.tē staōmaiδe ahurāne ahurahe vaŋhuš yasnąsca vahmąsca hubərətīsca uštā.bərətīsca vaṇta.bərətīsca yazatanąm</em> avar āb <em>ϑβā</em> āb ke dar bon-e zurdān 
                bāšad riḫtan <em>aṣ̌aōnąm</em> pādyāv andar dārešn <em>kuxňīša</em> zurdān porr-e āb kardan <em>usbī.barāmi</em> aǧ āb ul dārešn <em>raϑβaēca bərəzatō</em> andar 
                rāhi <em>gāϑā̊sca srāuuaiiōit̰</em> ānǧā-i nahešn</ab> 
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "<em>frā.tē staōmaiδe ahurāne ahurahe vaŋhuš yasnąsca vahmąsca hubərətīsca uštā.bərətīsca vaṇta.bərətīsca yazatanąm</em> -over the water- . At <em>ϑβā</em> he should
                pour the water that might be in the bottom of the <em>zurdān</em>. At <em>aṣ̌aōnąm</em>, he should hold it in <em>pādyāv</em>. At <em>kuxšnīša</em>, he should fill the
                <em>zurdān</em> with water. At <em>usbī.barāmi</em>, he should take (the <em>zurdān</em>) out of the water. (He should recite) <em>raϑβaēca bərəzatō</em> on the way
                and at <em>gāϑā̊sca srāuuaiiōit̰</em> he should put it there (on the <em>urwisgāh</em>)."</ab>
            
            <ab>ParagnaLL8.2.1. Var. c (Pers.) (Ms. RKS):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                <em>frātē staomaede ahurāne ahurahe vaŋhə̄uš ẏas ną̇sca vahmą̇sca hubərətīmca uštabərətīmca vaṇtanə rətīmca ẏazataną̇m ϑβā</em> avar āv vardešn <em>aṣ̌aoną̇m</em> pādyāv andaki 
                andar konešn <em>kuxšnīṣ̌a</em> por bekonešn <em>usbī barāmī</em> az āv dārešn <em>raϑβasca bərəzatō</em> andar rāh <em>gāϑā̊sca srāuuaiiōit̰</em> pa ǧāy nahešn</ab> 
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "<em>frātē staomaede ahurāne ahurahe vaŋhə̄uš ẏas ną̇sca vahmą̇sca hubərətīmca uštabərətīmca vaṇtanə rətīmca ẏazataną̇m</em>. At ϑβā., he should turn it towars the water.
                At <em>aṣ̌aoną̇m</em>, he should pour inside a driblet of <em>pādyāv</em>. At <em>kuxňīša</em>, he should fill it. At <em>usbi barāmi</em>, he has to take it out of the
                water (and recite) <em>raϑβasca bərəzatō</em> in the way. At <em>gāϑā̊sca srāuuaiiōit̰</em>, he has to place it (on the <em>urvis</em>)."</ab>
        </Nerangs>
        
        <Quotations id="ritualQuotations">
            <ab>N30.11 (Ms. K43):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                <em>frātə̄ staōmaide ahurāne ahurahe vaŋhə̄uš yasnąsca vahmąsca hubərətīšca ušta.bərətīšca vaṇta.bərətīšca yazatanąm</em> abar āb <em>ϑβā</em> andar wardēnnišn 
                <em>aṣ̌aōnąm</em> pādyāb andak-ē andar kunišn <em>kuxšnūša</em> purr bē kunišn <em>usbībarāmi</em> az āb ul dārišn <em>raϑβasca bərəzatō</em> andar rāh-ē 
                <em>gāϑā̊sca srāuuaiiōit̰</em> ān gyāg kē bē nihēd </ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "(He should recite) above the water: <em>frātə̄ staōmaide ahurāne ahurahe vaŋhə̄uš yasnąsca vahmąsca hubərətīšca ušta.bərətīšca vaṇta.bərətīšca yazatanąm</em>. At <em>ϑβā</em>
                he should turn the cups face down. At <em>aṣ̌aōnąm</em> he should fill them with a little consecrated water. At <em>kuxšnūša</em> he should fill them completely. At <em>usbībarāmi</em>
                he should lift them fully out of the water. (He recites) <em>raϑβasca bərəzatō</em> on the way and <em>gāϑā̊sca srāuuaiiōit̰</em> at the place where he put them down."</ab> 
        </Quotations>
    </Ritual>
    <translation>
        <include type="CAB" corresp="CABTrParagnaLL8.2.1"/>
    </translation>
</text>