<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text xml:id="ParagnaLL5.3.1" status="created">  <!-- created, approved, updated--> <header>
        <creators>
            <creator>Porro</creator>
            <creator>Cantera</creator>
        </creators>
        <created/>
    </header>
    <div type="Stanza" sameAs="" n="1" xml:id="ParagnaLL5.3.1">
                
    </div>
    <Apparatus>
        <Critical/>
        <Commentary/>
    </Apparatus>
    <Parallels/>
    <Ritual>
        <Nerangs id="ritualNerangs">
            <ab>ParagnaLL5.3.1 Var. a (Mss. K7, RJ):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                digar dast-e avar gāv nahāde yā gusfand va <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō</em> goftan va <em>yasnəmca</em> tā sar <em>āfrīnāmi gə̄uš tašne gə̄uš urune tauua gə̄uš huδā̊ŋhō urune</em>
                se tā har kodām be-vāǧ gerefte bāšand ān vāǧ beguyad pas andar yazešgāh bordan moḥkam nahādan pas durtar āyad yek <em>aṣ̌əm vohū</em> goftan <em>ahmāi raēsca</em> 
                tās sar <em>hazaŋhrəm</em> se bār tā sar <em>jasa.mē</em> tā sar <em>aṣ̌əm vohū</em> yek goftan</ab> 
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "Further, he has to recite two <em>Yaθā ahū vairiiō</em> with the hand put on the cow or the sheep and then <em>yasnəmca</em> until the end <em>āfrīnāmi</em> (with the
                <em>šnūman</em>) <em>gə̄uš tašne gə̄uš urune tauua gə̄uš huδā̊ŋhō urune</em>, one of the three ones -- they should say the <em>vāǧ</em> that they have taken (at the beginning). 
                Then, he should bring it to the <em>yazešngāh</em> and place it. Then, he should go further and say one <em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū</em> and <em>ahmāi raēsca</em> until the end and
                three times <em>hazaŋhrəm</em> until the end. He should recite one <em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū</em>."</ab>
            
            <ab>ParagnaLL5.3.1 Var. b (Mss. K36, 31):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō</em> do goftan <em>yasnəmca v. aō. z. āf. gə̄uš tašne gə̄uš urune</em> tā sar ǧāmdān moḥkam kardan be ǧāy nahādan va vāǧ tamām goftan</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "He should recite two <em>Yaθā ahū vairiiō</em> and <em>yasnəmca v. aō. z. āf. gə̄uš tašne gə̄uš urune</em> until the end. He should put the <em>ǧāmdān</em>, put it at its
                place and complete the <em>vāǧ</em>."</ab>
        </Nerangs>
    </Ritual>
    <translation>
        <include type="CAB" corresp="CABTrParagnaLL5.3.1"/>
    </translation>
</text>