<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text xml:id="ParagnaLL6.1.1" status="created">  <!-- created, approved, updated--> <header>
        <creators>
            <creator>Porro</creator>
            <creator>Cantera</creator>
        </creators>
        <created/>
    </header>
    <div type="Stanza" sameAs="" n="1" xml:id="ParagnaLL6.1.1">
                
    </div>
    <Apparatus>
        <Critical/>
        <Commentary/>
    </Apparatus>
    <Parallels/>
    <Ritual>
        <Nerangs id="ritualNerangs">
            <ab>ParagnaLL6.1.1 Var a (Phl) (WīD 95.1a)</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                pad *nērang ī wars puxtan nazdist dumb ī gāw ī nar kē arus mōy abāg hamāg handām tā pāy ud sumb ud manaoθra ud čašm ud srū hamāg spēd bawēd āwarišn ud hamāg hannām ud
                dumb pāk kunišn ud dō mard ī yōždahrgar kē yašt *nōg nāwar kard estēd pēš ān gāw āyēd ud pad <em>xšnaoθra ahurahe mazdā̊ aṣ̌əm vohū</em> sē bār dumb ī gāw pādyāb čiyōn
                urwarām bē kunišn ud wāz ī ōhrmazd xwadāy kū šnūman ī ōhrmazd xwadāy tā maraotū *gōwišn</ab>  
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "According to the instruction for boiling the wars, first, they should bring the tail of a male bull that has white hair in all his limbs except feet, hoofs, neck, eyes and horns. He has 
                to wash all limbs and the tail and two <em>yōždahrgar</em> who have perforemd a <em>Yašt Nōg-nāwar</em>, should go to this bull and at <em>xšnaoθra ahurahe mazdā̊</em> 
                and three <em>aṣ̌əm vohū</em>, he has to purify three times the bull's tail in the same as they have to do with the <em>urwarām</em> and he has to say the <em>wāz ī ōhrmazd</em> 
                that includes the <em>šnūman ī ōhrmazd</em> up to <em>maraōtu</em>."</ab>
            
            <ab>ParagnaLL6.1.1 Var. b (Phl) (Ms. M53):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                nērang wars puxtan nadist dēg-e pad pādyāb kard ud zōhr-ē abar griftan ud sē srešk war ī ātaxš warhrām andar afgandan ud wāz bē guftan wāz ōhrmazd griftan dast ud war pad 
                pādyād bē kardan</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "Instruction for boiling the <em>vars</em>. He should wash the vessel and take the <em>zur</em>. He should throw in it three pinches of ashes from the <em>ātaš varharām</em>
                and say the <em>vāǧ</em> and take the <em>wāǧ</em> for Urmazd and wash the hands and the <em>vars</em> with <em>pādyāb</em>."</ab>
            
            <ab>ParagnaLL6.1.1 Var. c (Ms. RKS (Unvala 2.31 ff.) . It is likely that the original was a Pāzand version identical or similar to the one of ms. F13. The text is better there. Cf. ParagnaLL5.1.1-3 Var. d):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                nirang-e vars poḫtan naḫost yek āv pādyāv āvāyad andāḫtan pas ṣabāḥ dast be-pādyāv kardan dig be-pādyāv kardan u pādyāb be-zur avar gereftan be-dig se †serešk vari ātaš 
                āvāyad kardan andak-i be-dig kardan vāǧ hurmazd gereftan dast vars be-pādyāv be-kardan</ab>  
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "Instruction for boiling the <em>vars</em>. First, one should collect <em>pādyāv</em>-water. Then, at the morningdawn, he should wash his hands with <em>pādyāv</em>, 
                wash a vessel with <em>pādyāv</em> and pour the <em>pādyāv</em> into the <em>zur</em>. He should put three pinches of ashes from the fire into the vessel and add 
                (a further) pinch to the vessel. He should take the <em>vāǧ</em> for Hurmazd and wash the hands and the <em>vars</em>."</ab>
            
            <ab>ParagnaLL6.1.1 Var. d (Ms. F13):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                nirang-e vars poḫtan nīrəng. vars. puxδən. nuxust. ẏak. šaba. bi. āvi. pādiiāv. āvāiiat̰. ṇdāxtən. pas. sabāh. dast. bi. pādiiāv. kirdən. dīg. bi. pādiiāv. kirdən. āvi. pādiiāv. bi.zōr. auur. 
                girəftən. bi. dəg. si. sərəšg. varə. ātaš. āvāiiaṯ. kirdən. ṇdakə. bi. dīg. kirdən. vāj. hōrməzd. gərəftən. dast. varas. bi. pādiiāv. bi. kirdən.</ab>  
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "Instruction for boiling the <em>vars</em>. First, one should collect <em>pādyāv</em>-water one night. Then, at the morningdawn, he should wash his hands with <em>pādyāv</em>,
                wash a vessel with <em>pādyāv</em> and pour the <em>pādyāv</em> into the <em>zur</em>. He should put three pinches of ashes from the fire into the vessel and add (a further) 
                pinch to the vessel. He should take the <em>vāǧ</em> for Hurmazd and wash the hands and the <em>vars</em>."</ab> 
        </Nerangs>
    </Ritual>
    <translation>
        <include type="CAB" corresp="CABTrParagnaLL6.1.1"/>
    </translation>
</text>