<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text xml:id="ParagnaLL1.2.1" status="created">  <!-- created, approved, updated--> <header>
        <creators>
            <creator>Porro</creator>
            <creator>Cantera</creator>
        </creators>
        <created/>
    </header>
    <div type="Stanza" sameAs="" n="1" xml:id="ParagnaLL1.2.1">
                
    </div>
    <Apparatus>
        <Critical/>
        <Commentary/>
    </Apparatus>
    <Parallels/>
    <Ritual>
        <Nerangs id="ritualNerangs">
            <ab>ParagnaLL1.2.1. (Pahl.) (Ms. K43):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                u-š pad <em>nǝmō uruuaire</em> wēšag pad ēwkardagīh nigērišn ēn kū wēšag ō wēšag čand pādixšāy ast kē gōwēd ēw +daxšmēst, ast kē ēdōn gōwēd ay bē ka az harw bun-ē 
                tāg-+ē wēned  ā nē šāyēd, ast kē ēdōn gōwēd ay ka wāng āšnawēd ā šāyēd </ab> 
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "At <em>nəmō uruuaire</em>, he has to look to the thicket "as a whole". That means that "how much distance is allowed between each thicket. There is one who says: 
                "A <em>daxšmēst</em>". There is one who says: "Except when he sees (at least) a branch from each trunk, it is not permissible." There is one who says: "When he can hear the 
                voice (from one thicket to another), then it is permissible."</ab>
            
            <ab>ParagnaLL1.2.1 (NP) (Mss. K7, RJ, RSK, K36, 31, 89, 19):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                <em>nəmō uruuaire vaŋhi mazdaδāte aṣ̌aōni</em> urvar va dār va deraḫt tamām be-negarand</ab>  
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "<em>nəmō uruuaire vaŋhi mazdaδāte aṣ̌aōni</em>. They examine thoroughly the plant, the wood and the three."</ab>
        </Nerangs>
        <Quotations id="ritualQuotations">
            <ab>N53.41</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                u-š <em>nəmō uruuaire</em> ān gyāg gōwišn kū barsom cīnēd</ab>  
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "He has to recite <em>nəmō uruuaire</em> at the moment when he cuts the <em>barsom</em>."</ab>
            
            <ab>N79.10</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                ēn kū az wēšag tā ō wēšag cand *pādixšāy ast kē gōwēd ay *daxšmēst gōwēd ast kē ēdōn gōwēd ay be ka az harw *bun-ē tāg-ē wēnēd tā nē šāyēd ast kē ēdōn gōwēd ay ka 
                wāng ašnawēd ā šāyēd</ab>  
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "As to the (question) of how much distance it is permissible from thicket to thicket, there is one who says: "A <em>daxšmēst</em>." There is one who says thus: "Unless he sees
                a twig from each tree, it is not proper."There is one who says thus: "If he can hear a call, then it is permissible."</ab>
        </Quotations>
    </Ritual>
    <translation>
        <include type="CAB" corresp="CABTrParagnaLL1.2.1"/>
    </translation>
</text>