<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text xml:id="ParagnaLL8.1.1" status="created">  <!-- created, approved, updated--> <header>
        <creators>
            <creator>Porro</creator>
            <creator>Cantera</creator>
        </creators>
        <created/>
    </header>
    <div type="Stanza" sameAs="" n="1" xml:id="ParagnaLL8.1.1">
                
    </div>
    <Apparatus>
        <Critical/>
        <Commentary/>
    </Apparatus>
    <Parallels/>
    <Ritual>
        <Nerangs id="ritualNerangs">
            <ab>ParagnaLL8.1.1 Var. a (Phl.) (Mss. K7, RJ):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                hassārīh ī āb šawišn u-š abastāg pad *war ī āb gōwišn ašemvohū 3 frawarānē čē gāh dārēd <em>aiβiiō vaŋhībiiō vīspanąmca apąm mazdaδātanąm bərəzatō ahurahe nafəδrō apąm
                    apasca mazdaδātaiiå tauua ahurāni ahurahe xšnaōϑra</em> u-š wāz frāz gīrišnīh</ab>  
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "He should move in the direction of the water and recite these Avestan texts near the water: <em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū</em> three times; then the <em>Frauuarāne</em> that contains 
                the section of the day (with the dedicatory) <em>aiβiiō vaŋhubiiō vīspanąmca apąm mazdaδātanąm bərəzatō ahurahe nafəδrō apąm apasca mazdaδātaiiā̊ tauua ahurane ahurahe xšnaōϑra</em>. 
                He should take the <em>wāz</em>."</ab>
            
            <ab>ParagnaLL8.1.1 Var. b (Phl.) (WīD95.3):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                čiyōn ka-š zōhr bē *zōhēnēd ēn abestāg drust bē gōwišn <em>aṣ̌əm vōhū</em> sē <em>frauuarāne</em> čē gāh dārēd <em>aiβiiō vaŋuhēbiiō vīspanąmca apąm mazdaδātanąm 
                    bərəzatō ahurahe nafəδrō apąm apasca mazdaδātaiiå tauua ahurāne ahurahe xšnaoθra</em> tā sar u-š wāz gīrišnīh</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "When he takes (?) the <em>zōhr</em>, he should recite correctly the following <em>abastāg</em>: three <em>aṣ̌əm vōhū</em> and the <em>frauuarāne</em> that includes 
                the <em>gāh</em> (with the <em>šnūman</em>) <em>aiβiiō vaŋuhēbiiō vīspanąmca apąm mazdaδātanąm bərəzatō ahurahe nafəδrō apąm apasca mazdaδātaiiå tauua ahurāne 
                    ahurahe xšnaoθra</em> until the end. He has to take the <em>wāz</em>." </ab>
            
            <ab>ParagnaLL8.1.1 Var. a (Pers.) (Mss. K7; om. RJ):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                pas nirang farāhim avar gereftan pas zud va rās̱vi dar yazešngāh šodan va ātaš dar ādošk bar afruḫtan va ān kasi ke zud bāšad fanān bastan va rās̱vi dar pas-e sang-e urvis šodan 
                va āb rā pādyāvi kardan va pādyāvi ān ast ke dar barsom čidan gufte budim ke se bār az ān mašrabe-ye bozorg dar mašrabe-ye ḫord rizand va az mašrabe-ye ḫord dar mašrabe-ye 
                bozorg rizand va āb rā nik eḥtiāṭ konand ke pāk bāšad va pas ruy-e sang-e urvis rā sokori se tā va ǧāmdān va him pyāle va māhruy va hāvan va daste va ān āb-e pāk šostan va har 
                yek se bār pas zur bar gereftan ān ast ke sokori-ye farāhimdān va sokori-ye zurdān har do be-dast-e čab bar-dārand va āb-e pāk be-šostan va har yek se bār pādyāb karde be-dast-e 
                rāst bar-dārand va az ruy-e sang-e urwis bālā dārand <em>xšnaōϑra ahurahe mazdā̊ aṣ̌əm vohū</em> se goftan <em>frauuarāne</em> gāh-e hāvan <em>aiβiiō vaŋhibiiō vīspanąmca
                    apąm mazdaδātanąm bərəzatō ahurahe nafəδrō apąm apasca mazdaδātaiiå xšnaōϑra y. v. x. f. yaϑā ahū vairiiō zaōtā</em> OD <em>mraōtū</em>.</ab> 
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "Then the <em>nirang</em> for getting the <em>fraāhim</em>. Afterwards, the <em>zud</em> and the <em>rās̱vi</em> should go to the <em>yazešngāh</em> and kindle 
                the fire on the fire altar. The one who will be the <em>zud</em> should bind the <em>padām</em> and the <em>rās̱vi</em> should go behind the stone of the <em>urvis</em> 
                and has to purify the water. The purification happens as we have written in the section of the <em>barsom čidan</em> so that one pours the water three times from the bigger vessel 
                into the smaller one and from the smaller into the bigger one. They have to take care that the water becomes pure. Then, concerning the stone of the <em>urvis</em>, he should 
                wash the three cups, the <em>ǧāmdān</em>, the <em>him-pyāle</em>, the <em>māhruy</em>, the <em>hāvan</em>, the pestle with pure water, each one three times. Then
                one should take the <em>zur</em>, that is, one should hold both the cup <em>farāhimdān</em> and the cup <em>zurdān</em> in the left hand and wash them with pure water. 
                When each one has been purifies three times, one holds them with the right hand and raise them from the stone of the urvis. He should recite <em>xšnaōϑra ahurahe mazdā̊</em> 
                and three <em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū</em>s  and the <em>frauuarāne</em> with the <em>gāh</em> of <em>hāvan</em> and (the <em>šnūman</em>) <em>aiβiiō vaŋhibiiō vīspanąmca
                    apąm mazdaδātanąm bərəzatō ahurahe nafəδrō apąm apasca mazdaδātaiiå xšnaōϑra y. v. x. f. yaϑā ahū vairiiō zaōtā</em> until <em>mraōtū</em>."</ab>
            
            <ab>ParagnaLL8.1.1 Var. b (Pers.) (missing in 39):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                nirang-e zur gereftan āb pādyāv kardan va sekure-ye zurdān pādyāv kardan va sar-e †sekāle-ye āb bar dast-e rāst va zurdān bar dast-e čab gereftan <em>xšnaōϑra ahurahe mazdā̊ aṣ̌əm vohū</em> 
                se goftan <em>frauuarāne</em> gāh āne bid goftan <em>aiβiiō vaŋhibiiō vīspanąmca apąm mazdaδātanąm bərəzatō ahurahe nafəδrō apąm apasca mazdaδātaiiā̊ tauua ahurāne
                    ahurahe xšnaōϑra yas. v. x. f.  yaϑā ahū vairiiō zaōtā</em> tā sar</ab> 
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "The instruction for taking the <em>zur</em>. He should purify the water and clean the <em>zurdān</em>-cup. He should take the cup of the water in the right hand and the 
                <em>zurdān</em> in the left. He should recite <em>xšnaōϑra ahurahe mazdā̊</em> and three <em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū</em>s  and the <em>frauuarāne</em> with the corresponding
                <em>gāh</em> and (the <em>šnūman</em>) <em>aiβiiō vaŋhibiiō vīspanąmca apąm mazdaδātanąm bərəzatō ahurahe nafəδrō apąm apasca mazdaδātaiiå tauua ahurāne ahurahe
                    xšnaōϑra yas. v. x. f.  yaϑā ahū vairiiō zaōtā</em> until the end."</ab> 
            
            <ab>ParagnaLL8.1.1 Var. c (Pers.) (Ms. RKS (Unv. 465 17ff.)):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                ke ǧuddivdād gāh-e oziran †zur bāyad gereftan <em>aivīō vaŋhēbiiō vīspaną̇mca apą̇m mazdaδātaną̇m bərəzatō ahurahe nafəδrōapą̇m apasca mazdaδātaiiā̊ tauua ahurāne ahurahe
                    xšnaoϑra ẏ. v. x. f. ẏaϑā ahū vairiiō zaōtā</em> tā sar</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "When they perform a <em>Ǧudivdād</em>, they must take the <em>zur</em> at the <em>gāh oziran</em> (and recite corresponding the <em>Frauuarāne</em> with the 
                dedication) <em>aiβiiō vaŋhibiiō vīspanąmca apąm mazdaδātanąm bərəzatō ahurahe nafəδrō apąm apasca mazdaδātaiiå tauua ahurāne ahurahe xšnaōϑra y. v. x. f.</em> (and 
                then) <em>ẏaϑā ahū vairiiō zaōtā</em> until the end."</ab>
        </Nerangs>
        <Quotations id="ritualQuotations">
            <ab>N30.10-11 (Ms. 43):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                ka zōhr stānēd ā-š pad war ī āb šawišn u-š abastāg pad hassārīh ī āb gōwēd <em>ašəm vohū</em> 3 frawarānē čē gāh dārēd <em>aiβiiō vaŋhubiiō vīspanąmca apąm mazdaδātanąm
                    bərəzatō ahurahe nafəδrō apąm apasca mazdaδātaiiā̊ tauua ahurane ahurahe xšnaōϑra yasnāica</em> tā <em>frasastaiiaēca</em> u-š wāž frāz gīrišnīh</ab> 
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "When he takes the <em>zōhr</em>, he should move in the direction of the water and recite these Avestan texts near the water: <em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū</em> three times; then the 
                <em>Frauuarāne</em> withe corresponding <em>gāh</em> (and with the <em>šnūman</em>) <em>aiβiiō vaŋhubiiō vīspanąmca apąm mazdaδātanąm bərəzatō ahurahe nafəδrō 
                    apąm apasca mazdaδātaiiā̊ tauua ahurane ahurahe xšnaōϑra yasnāica</em> until <em>frasastaiiaēca</em>. And he should take the <em>wāz</em>."</ab> 
        </Quotations>
    </Ritual>
    <translation>
        <include type="CAB" corresp="CABTrParagnaLL8.1.1"/>
    </translation>
</text>