<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text xml:id="ParagnaLL12.5.3" status="created">  <!-- created, approved, updated--> <header>
        <creators>
            <creator>Porro</creator>
            <creator>Cantera</creator>
        </creators>
        <created/>
    </header>
    <div type="Stanza" sameAs="" n="3" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.5.3">
                
    </div>
    <Apparatus>
        <Critical/>
        <Commentary/>
    </Apparatus>
    <Parallels/>
    <Ritual>
        <Nerangs id="ritualNerangs">
            <ab>ParagnaLL12.5.3 (Mss. K7, RJ):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                yek <em>aṣ̌em vohu</em> yek <em>aɱāi raēšca</em> OD <em>hazaŋrəm</em> OD <em>jasa.mē</em> tā sar goftan pas is̱ā ahu vairyu ḫᵛāndan ān kasi ke yašt mikonad pas 
                urvisgāh šodan yašt tā sar tamām ḫᵛāndan har ḫšnīman ke ḫᵛāhad šāyad ellā nu-nāvar visperad-e ruz-e avval dovvom čon yašt tamām šod zud ān farāhim nahāde in avestā ḫāndan 
                <em>rātōiš darəgō.bāzāuš nāšū paitī.viiādā̊ paitī.sə̄ṇdā̊ mātarō jītaiiō yeŋ́hē.hātąm</em> tā sar ḫᵛāndan <em>yeŋ́hē.hātąm</em> tā sar ḫᵛāndan ānkas ke yašt karde bāšad urvarān 
                az no čidan va ǧām az no duḫtan barsom bist o se az no čidan vars rā be-hamān dastur-e ruz-e avval šostan be-ḫalqe kardan va nahādan va digar ruz sāǧešn tamām kardan be-hamān 
                dastur ruz-e avval farāhim gereftan moḥkam nahādan čon yašt tamām šod digar ruz farāhim be-hamān dastur be-āb ravān riḫtan digar 
                ānkas ke yašt karde bāšad digar urvarān no čidan va barsom si o panǧ tā čidan ǧām duḫtan vars rā be-hamān dastur šostan ḫalqe kardan hazār va yekbār be-āb forubordan va āvardan 
                digar ruz be-hamām dastur-e ruz-e avval hamān sāǧešn ḫub nahādan farāhim va stāyeš ḫᵛāndan farāhim moḥkam nahādan agar gahanbār bāšad bāšad visperad be-ḫšnumaine gahanbār 
                kardan agar gahanbār na-bāšad visperad be-ḫšnumane-e ruz kardan va yā ašuvān čon yašt tamām kardan zur dar āb riḫtan ān farāhim rā moḥkam nahādan har bār ke yašti konand ān 
                farāhim gerd kardan qatre-ye dar farāhim-dān bar sar-e hāvan nahādan čenānke rasm ast farāhim barāy-e ān-ast yazešn bā-in farāhim va rastat (?) va ǧāme-ye pāk va sāǧešn-e pāk va 
                maqām-e pāk va del-e pāk va ḫᵛāndan-e avestā-ye dorost farmude-ye dastur ānče az yazdān va amāšasfandān va ānče az yazdān be-ḫᵛāhad be-resad in-ast neyrang farāhim gereftan.</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "Then he should recite one <em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū</em>, one <em>aɱāi raēšca</em> until <em>jasa.mē</em> until the end. Then he shoud recite one <em>Yaθā Ahū vairiiō</em>.
                The one who will perform the <em>yašt</em> should go to the <em>urvisgāh</em> and recite the <em>yašt</em> until the end. He might use whatever <em>šnūman</em> he
                likes except the one for <em>nu-nāvar</em> or the <em>visperad</em> of the first day. Secondly, when he has completed the <em>yašt</em>, the <em>zōt</em> should recite
                following <em>avestā</em> after having put the (remaining) <em>farāhim</em>: <em>rātōiš darəgō.bāzāuš nāšū paitī.viiādā̊ paitī.sə̄ṇdā̊ mātarō jītaiiō</em>. He should then recite
                a <em>Yeŋ́hē.hātąm</em> until the end. 
                The one who will have performed the <em>yašt</em>, he should  cut anew the <em>vars</em>, milk anew the <em>ǧām</em>, cut again the twenty-three twigs of the barsom.
                He should wash the <em>vars</em> according to the instructions for the first day, twist it in the ring, put it in its place. Next day he should complete the preparatives according to
                the instruction for the first day. He should take the <em>farāhim</em>, deposite it and when the <em>yašt</em> has been completed, he should pour the <em>farāhim</em> next 
                day into a waterstream following the same instructions as for the first day. 
                The one who will have performed the <em>yašt</em>, he shoud cut again anew the <em>urvarān</em>, cut the thirty-five twigs of the <em>barsom</em>, milk the <em>ǧām</em>, 
                wash the <em>vars</em> according to the same instructions and twist it in the ring. He should immerse and take it out the water thousand and one times. Next day, he should dispose 
                correctly all <em>sāǧešn</em> according to the same instructions of the first day. He should recite the <em>farāhim</em> and the <em>setāyeš</em>, put the <em>farāhim</em>
                at its place. Each time that they perform a <em>yašt</em>, they should get (new) <em>farāhim</em>, (pour) a drop into the <em>farāhim-dān</em> and put it on the <em>hāvan</em> 
                as it is the custom. The <em>farāhim</em> is to that purpose. The <em>yazešn</em> (should be performed) with this <em>farāhim</em>, with pure clothes, pure <em>sāǧešn</em>, 
                at a pure place, with a pure heart and with a correct recitation of the <em>avestā</em> according to the instructions. Might he obtain whatever he requires from the gods and the 
                <em>Amašāsfandān</em>, whatever he requires from the gods. This is the instruction for getting the <em>farāhim</em>."</ab>
        </Nerangs>
    </Ritual>
    <translation>
        <include type="CAB" corresp="CABTrParagnaLL12.5.3"/>
    </translation>
</text>