<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text xml:id="ParagnaLL12.4.1" status="created">  <!-- created, approved, updated--> <header>
        <creators>
            <creator>Porro</creator>
            <creator>Cantera</creator>
        </creators>
        <created/>
    </header>
    <div type="Stanza" sameAs="" n="1" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.4.1">
                
    </div>
    <Apparatus>
        <Critical/>
        <Commentary/>
    </Apparatus>
    <Parallels/>
    <Ritual>
        <Nerangs id="ritualNerangs">
            <ab>ParagnaLL12.4.1 (Ms. 100):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                <em>aētaṯ dim vīspanąm</em> daste-ye hāvan az ruy-e sang-e urvis be-dast gereftan <em>mazištəm dazdiiāi ahūmca ratūmca yim ahurəm mazdąm</em> čašm va ruy andar 
                vāḫtar afšānidan <em>snaϑāi aŋhrahe mainiiə̄uš druuatō</em> yaʾni zanešn b-ahreman druvand <em>snaθāi aešmahe xruuī.draōš</em> čašm va ruy andar avāḫtar afšānidan 
                yaʾni zaneš be-hišm ḫore-ye vepadraḫš (***?) div dādam <em>snaθāi mazaniianąm daēuuanąm</em> čašm va ruy andar avāḫtar afšānidan yaʾni zaneš be māzanigān divān dādam 
                <em>snaθāi vīspanąm daēuuanąm</em> čašm va ruy andar avāḫtar afšānidan yaʾni zanešn bā hamān divān dādam <em>varənīnąmca druuatąm</em> daste az ruy-e sang-urvis
                bar dāštan se bār bar se sān hāvan zadan yekbār az ānsu ke xoršid bar-āyad yeki az ānsuy-e nimruz yeki az ānsuy ke xoršid foru šavad pas daste bar dast negāh dāštan </ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "(He should recite) <em>aētaṯ dim vīspanąm</em>, take in the hand the pestle of the <em>hāvan</em> from the <em>urvis</em>-stone (and continue with) <em>mazištəm 
                    dazdiiāi ahūmca ratūmca yim ahurəm mazdąm</em>. He should turn his glance and face towards the East (and recite) <em>snaϑāi aŋhrahe mainiiə̄uš druuatō</em> that means, 
                the striking of the <em>druvand Ahreman</em>. At <em>snaθāi aešmahe xruuī.draōš</em> he should turn his glance and face to the North that means, I stroke the <em>div Hišm</em> 
                with bloody mace. At <em>snaθāi mazaniianąm daēuuanąm</em> he should (again) turn his glance and face to the North that means, I stroke the <em>divs māzanigān</em>. 
                At <em>snaθāi vīspanąm daēuuanąm</em> he should turn his glance and face to the North that means, I stroke all <em>divs</em>. At <em>varənīnąmca druuatąm</em> he 
                should take the pestle from the <em>urvis</em>-stone and hit the <em>hāvan</em> three times and at three sides: once at the side in which the sun goes up, once from the south
                side and once at the side in which the sun goes down. Then he should keep the pestle in his hand."</ab>
        </Nerangs>
    </Ritual>
    <translation>
        <include type="CAB" corresp="CABTrParagnaLL12.4.1"/>
    </translation>
</text>