<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text xml:id="ParagnaLL1.3.10" status="created">
    <!-- created, approved, updated-->
    <header>
        <creators>

            <creator>Cantera</creator>
            <creator>Porro</creator>
        </creators>
        <created/>
    </header>
    <div type="Stanza" sameAs="" n="10" xml:id="ParagnaLL1.3.10"> </div>
    <Apparatus>
        <Critical/>
        <Commentary>According to Ǧāsā's Revāyat, when the tree from which the <em>aivyanghan</em>
            is cut stays far from the thicket from which the <em>barsom</em> is cut, then at this
            moment the whole wāz of the barsom has to be repeated, that is, the Neyrang-e barsom
            cidan (Par1.3.10 agar aivyanghan ǧā-ye digar bud vāǧ-e barsom guftan). At its end, after
            Par1.3.10, the priest recites again xšnaōθra ahurahe mazdā̊ with three Aṣ̌əm Vohūs and
            then cuts the <em>aivyanaghan</em> (see NerPar1.3.10 in Ritual) </Commentary>
    </Apparatus>
    <Parallels/>
    <Ritual>
        <Nerangs id="ritualNerangs">
            <ab>ParagnaLL1.3.10 Var. a (Mss. K7, RJ):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                <em>aṣ̌əm vōhū</em> yek ḫᵛāndan agar aivyanghan ǧā-ye digar bud vāǧ-e barsom guftan
                va barsomdān dur nahādan va pas ahmāi. raesca tā sar va hazaŋhrəm tā sar va jasamē
                tā sar xāndan pas digar bār <em>xšnaoθra ahurahe mazdā̊ aṣ̌əm vōhū</em> se ḫᵛāndan
                barsom va barsomdām va āb bar dāštan va nazdik-e aivyanghan šodan va aivyanghan az
                har deraḫt-e sabz šāyad ellā nār va gaz našāyad va digar dast b-āb pādyāvi šostan
                barsom az barsomdān bedar kardan va dar dast gereftan pas be-kārd-e barsom-čin
                aivyanghan čidan ba hǐč čiz našāyad ḫᵛāndan va ān <em>ašem vohu</em> ke šomā neveste
                budid niz navāyad ḫᵛāndan va barsom be-dast našāyad čidan barsom šab našāyad čidan
                va ān <em>xšaθrahe vairiiehe</em> ke šoma nevešte budid niz nabāyad ḫᵛāndan ke
                barsom bandand se tā yā panǧ tā yā hafta tā barsom va aivyanghan dar dast gereftan
                čenān konand ke dast-e čab az barsom ǧodā nabāšad </ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent"> "If the <em>aivyanghan</em> was at a different place, he should
                recite again the <em>vāǧ</em> for the <em>barsom</em> and to put the
                    <em>barsomdān</em> far away. Then, he should recite <em>ahmāi raesca</em> till
                the end and <em>jasa.me</em> till the end. Then he should recite again <em>xšnaoθra
                    ahurahe mazdā̊</em> and three <em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū</em>. He should raise the
                    <em>barsom</em>, the <em>barsomdān</em> and the water and go near the
                    <em>aivyanghan</em>. The <em>aivyanghan</em> can be from any frutal tree, but
                pomegranate and tamarisk are not allowed. He should wash again the hand with
                    <em>pādyāb</em> and remove the <em>barsom</em> from the <em>barsomdān</em> and
                take it in the hand and then cut the <em>aivyanghan</em> with the knife called
                    <em>barsom-čin</em>. It is not allowed to recite anything else. It is not
                allowed to recite the <em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū</em> that you have written. It is also not
                allowed to cut the <em>barsom</em> with the hand. It is not allowed to cut it during
                the night. It is also not allowed to recite the <em>xšaθrahe vairiiehe</em> that you
                have written.The ones who tie the barsom, they should take three, five, seven
                branches of the barsom and the aivyanghan in the right hand and make so that the
                left hand does not release the barsom."</ab>
        </Nerangs>
    </Ritual>
    <translation>
        <include type="CAB" corresp="CABTrParagnaLL1.3.10"/>
    </translation>
</text>