<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text xml:id="ParagnaLL1.2.2" status="created">  <!-- created, approved, updated--> <header>
        <creators>
            <creator>Porro</creator>
            <creator>Cantera</creator>
        </creators>
        <created/>
    </header>
    <div type="Stanza" sameAs="" n="2" xml:id="ParagnaLL1.2.2">
                
    </div>
    <Apparatus>
        <Critical/>
        <Commentary/>
    </Apparatus>
    <Parallels/>
    <Ritual>
        <Nerangs id="ritualNerangs">
            <ab>ParagnaLL1.2.2. (Pahl.) (Ms. K43):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                u-š <em>aṣ̌əm</em> frāz gīrišn u-š pad vohū kārd abar nihēd u-š pad vahištəm bē brīnišn tā sē tāg pad abestāg bē čīnēd hamē ka ēw tāg apādyāb bē bawēd ā-š wāz abāz gīrišn 
                ka-š sē tāg pad abestāg čīnēd ka harw sē apādyāb bē bawēd ā-š wāz abāz nē gīrišn kar sar hušk...</ab>  
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "He has to grab (the branch) it at <em>aṣ̌əm</em>, to put the knife at <em>vohū</em>, to cut it at <em>vahištəm</em> (and to repeat the process thus) until he cuts three pieces
                while reciting the <em>abestāg.</em> Every time that a branch is polluted, he has to take again the <em>wāz</em>. When all three become polluted, then he has not to take again 
                the <em>wāz</em>. When the tip is dry..."</ab>
            
            <ab>ParagnaLL1.2.2. (NP) Var. a (Mss. K7, RJ):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                va pe <em>aṣ̌əm</em> sar-e šāḫ-e barsom boridan va meqdār-e ēk dāne-ye ǧou va dar afgandan pas vohū barsom-čin bar miyān-e barsom nihādan pas <em>vahištəm</em> tak-i 
                barsom boridan pas <em>astī uštā astī uštā aɱāi</em> tā sar ḫvāndan se šāḫ-e barsom b-in dastur āvāyad čidan pas har čand ke ḫᵛāhand činand hame-rā yek-yek bar āvāyad boridan 
                meqdār-e yek dāne-ye ǧou vaqt šomordan mi-vāyad ke ǧoft ǧoft šomārand dar āḫar yeki ke ṭāq bāšad agar ǧoft bāšad yeki digar čidan pas aivyanghan be-hamin vāǧ bečinand ke 
                aivanghan vāǧ gīrišn nadārad pas be-hamān šāḫ-e barsom āyand ke vāǧ gerefte bāšand vāǧ be-guyand</ab> 
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "At <em>aṣ̌əm</em> he should cut the end of the <em>barsom</em>-twig in the size of a corn of barley and detach it. Then (at) <em>vohū</em> he should put the <em>barsom-čin</em> 
                on the middle of the <em>barsom</em>. Then at <em>vahištəm</em> he should cut one twig of the <em>barsom</em> and then recite <em>astī uštā astī uštā aɱāi</em> upto 
                the end. He should cut in this way (at least) three twigs of the <em>barsom</em>. Then he should cut twig by twig as many twigs as they want to cut. He should cut the end of all
                branches, one to one, in the size of one corn of barley. When they count, they should count by pairs. Eventually, it must remain a single piece. If they are pairs, then another one 
                should be cut. Afterwards, they cut the <em>aivyanghan</em> with even the same <em>vāǧ</em>. If there is not <em>vāǧ-gīrešn</em> for the <em>aivanghan</em>, then they
                go to exactly the branch of the <em>barsom</em> at which they has taken the <em>vāǧ</em> and say the <em>vāǧ</em>."</ab>
            
            <ab>ParagnaLL1.2.2 (NP) Var. b (Mss. K36, 31, 89, 19):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                va se <em>aṣ̌em</em> avāyad ḫᵛānd ašem ke miguyad sar-e barsom avāyad dāšt vohi miyān-e barsom kārd mizanad va <em>vahištem</em> bon-e barsom be činad tā se tāk-e 
                barsom čide šavad baʿd az ān har šāḫi be barsom bāšad be čidan va ʿaivyānghan be činad va baʿd az ān bāyad va vāǧ be-guyad va ān šāḫi ke barsom se tāk čide-and be-girand</ab> 
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "He must recite three <em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū</em>s. When he recites <em>aṣ̌em</em>, he must hold the the tip of the <em>barsom</em>. At <em>vohū</em>, they put the knife on
                the mid of the <em>barsom</em>. At <em>vahištəm</em>, he cuts the tip of <em>barsom</em> until he has cut three twigs of the <em>barsom</em>. Afterwards, he should cut 
                as many braches as needed for the <em>barsom</em>. He cuts the <em>aivyanghan</em>. Afterwards, he must recite the <em>vāǧ</em> and they take the branch from which three
                <em>barsom</em>-twigs have been cut."</ab>
            
            <ab>ParagnaLL1.2.2 (NP) Var. c (Ms. RKS):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                pa <em>aṣ̌em</em> yek ǧou sar-e barsom boridan pa <em>vōhū</em> barsom-cin bar miyān-e barsom nahādan va pa <em>vahištəm</em> tak-i barsam boridan pas 
                <em>astī uštā astī uštā aɱāi hiiat̰ aṣ̌āi vahištāi aṣ̌əm</em> ĪĪĪ <em>aṣ̌əm vōhū</em> goftan va se tā barsam cidan va pas harcand barsam ḫᵛāhand cidan va šomāre kardan cenānke
                ṭāq bāšad va agar ǧoft bāšad yeki digar cidan va †pas hamān šāḫ ke avval vāǧ gerefte bāšad gereftan</ab>  
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "At <em>aṣ̌em</em> he must cut (the size of) a barley corn at the end of the <em>barsom</em>. At <em>vōhū</em>, he should put the <em>barsom</em>-cin on the middle
                of the <em>barsom</em>. At <em>vahištəm</em>, he should cut one twig of the <em>barsom</em>. Then he should recite <em>astī uštā astī uštā aɱāi</em> and three 
                <em>aṣ̌əm vohū</em> and cut three pieces of the <em>barsom</em>. Then, he should cut as many <em>barsom</em>-branches as they want, and count then so that they are 
                an even number. If they are odd, he must cut an aditional one. Then he should take the same branch that he took with the first <em>vāǧ</em>."</ab>
        </Nerangs>
        <Quotations id="ritualQuotations">
            <ab>N79.11</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                u-š pad <em>aṣ̌əm</em> frāz gīrišn u-š pad <em>vohū</em> kārd abar nihišn u-š pad <em>vahištəm</em> bē brīnišn tā sē tāg pad abestāg bē čīnēd hamē ka ēw tāg apādyāb 
                bē bawēd ā-š wāz abāz gīrišn ka-š sē tāg pad abestāg čīnēd ka harw sē apādyāb bē bawēd ā-š wāz abāz nē gīrišn</ab> 
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "He has to grab (the branch) at <em>aṣ̌əm</em>, to put the knife at <em>vohū</em>, to cut it at <em>vahištəm</em> (and to repeat the process thus) until he cuts three pieces
                while reciting the <em>abestāg</em>. Every time that a branch is polluted, he has to take again the <em>wāz</em>. When all three become polluted, then he has not to take again
                the <em>wāz</em>."</ab>
        </Quotations>
    </Ritual>
    <translation>
        <include type="CAB" corresp="CABTrParagnaLL1.2.2"/>
    </translation>
</text>