<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text xml:id="VrS0.1" status="created">
    <!-- created, approved, updated-->
    <header>
        <creators>
            <creator>Porro</creator>
            <creator>Cantera</creator>
        </creators>
        <created>1 June 2019</created>
        <approved/>
        <updated/>
    </header>
    <div type="Stanza" sameAs="" xml:id="VrS0.1">
        <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/nerang/visperad_nerang" xpointer="VrS0.1NerangTransc.a"/>
        <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/blocks/prayers/AV" xpointer="AV"/>
    </div>
    <Speaker>
        <SpeakerInfo>
            <div>zōt: vid. Y0.1.</div>
        </SpeakerInfo>
        <Commentary/>
    </Speaker>
    <Apparatus>
        <Critical/>
        <RecitationInstruction>
            <ab>ʾywk' gwptn'] 2007, 2070, 2101, 2109; III gwptn' 2010; om. 2038, 2065, 2230.</ab>
        </RecitationInstruction>
        <Commentary/>
    </Apparatus>
    <Parallels/>
    <Ritual>
        <Nerangs id="ritualNerangs">
            <ab>VrS0.1 Var. a (mss. 2007, 2010, 2040, 2070, 2101, 2103, 2104a, 2106, 2109):</ab> 
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                barsom sih ud se tāg ud frāgām dō tāg barsom bastan parāhōm kardan sāzišn hamāg xūb frāz nihādan ud ān kas kē zōtīh kāmēd kardan <em>aṣ̌əm vohū</em> ēk guftan ud dast
                pad pādyāb kunišn</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "The <em>barsom</em> (consists of) 33 twigs and the <em>frāgām</em> are two. He should tie the <em>barsom</em>, prepare the <em>parāhōm</em> and dispose all the 
                implements carefully. The one who wishes to perform in the office of <em>zōt</em> should recite one <em>aṣ̌əm vohū</em> and has to wash his hands with <em>pādyāb</em>."</ab>
            <ab>VrS0.1 Var. b (ms. 2065):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                barsom sih ud sē tāg ud frāgām dō tāg barsom bastan parāhōm kardan sāzišn hamāg xūb frāz nihādan ud parāhōm kardan rāy pad har hōmāst-ē pad kamistīh hōm sē tāg urwarām
                pārag-ē ǰām andak-ē frāz nihišn ud ōy kē zōtīh kāmēd kardan dast pad pādyāb bē kunišn </ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "The <em>barsom</em> (consists of) 33 twigs and the <em>frāgām</em> are two. He should tie the <em>barsom</em>, prepare the <em>parāhōm</em> and dispose all the 
                implements carefully. For the preparation of the <em>parāhōm</em>, he has to dispose for each <em>hōmāst</em> at least three twigs of <em>hōm</em>, one branch of 
                <em>urwarām</em> and a drop of <em>ǰām</em>. The one who wishes to perform in the office of <em>zōt</em> has to wash his hands with <em>pādyāb</em>."</ab>
        </Nerangs>
        <ModernPractice id="ritualModernPractice">
            <ab>
                <ab><bibl>Redard and Daruwalla, 2021</bibl>, pp. 193: </ab>
                <ab class="ab_indent">"... the priest who is about to become the chief priest, comes into that <em>pāvī</em> which is outside of the <em>pāvī</em> of the table
                    of the ritual precinct; (after) reciting one <em>Aṣ̌ǝm Vohū</em>, he comes into the <em>pāvī</em> of the (ritual) table (and) stands near the water container containing the pure
                    implements;"</ab>
            </ab>
        </ModernPractice>
    </Ritual>
    <translation>
        <include type="CAB" corresp="CABTrVrS0.1"/>
    </translation>
</text>