<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text xml:id="VrS0.10" status="created">
   <!-- created, approved, updated-->
   <header>
      <creators>
         <creator>Porro</creator>
         <creator>Cantera</creator>
      </creators>
      <created>1 June 2019</created>
   </header>
   <div type="Stanza" sameAs="" xml:id="VrS0.10">
      <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/blocks/Frauuarane_BP" xpointer="Frauuarane_BP4"/>
   </div>
   <Speaker>
      <SpeakerInfo>
         <div>zōt ud rāspīg: vid. Y0.10.</div>
      </SpeakerInfo>
      <Commentary/>
   </Speaker>
   <Apparatus>
      <Critical/>
      <Commentary>
         <ab><em>raϑβō. ... raϑβō.</em> (<em>šnūman</em>)] vid. Nērang; abbv. 2220.</ab>
         <ab><em>maiδiiōizarəmaiiehe. ... frasastaiiaēca.</em>] zō. ghm.bār. ardī.bhə̄št. mhānā. huitu. <em>maiδiiō.zarəmaiiehe. raϑβō. x. v. x. f.</em> phariia. zō. gahm. bār. tīr. mhānā. huitu. <em>maiδiiō.šəmahe. raϑβō. x. y. v. x. f.</em>
            phariia. zō. g ahm. bār. šharə̄. var. mhānā. huitu. <em>maiδiiō. (del. man.) paitiš.hahiiehe. raϑβō. x. y. v. x. f.</em> phariia. zō. gahm. bār. maihar. mhānā. huitu. <em>aiiāϑrəmahe. raϑβō. x. y. v. x. f.</em> 
            phariia.zō. gahm. bār. di. mhānā. huitu. <em>maiδiiā.riiehe. raϑβō. x. y. v. x. f.</em> phariia. zō. gahm. bār. gāϑānā. huiti. <em>hamaspaϑmaēδaiiehe. raϑβō. x. y. v. x. f.</em> 2230</ab>
      </Commentary>
   </Apparatus>
   <Parallels/>
   <Ritual>
      <Nerangs id="ritualNerangs">
         <ab>VrS0.10 šnūman Var. a (mss. 2007, 2010):</ab>
         <ab class="indent">
            agar xšnūman ī gāhānbār bēd . : <em>raϑβō bərəzatō yō aṣ̌ahe raϑβąm aiiaranąmca asniianąmca māhiianąmca yāiriianąmca sarəδanąmca raϑβąm vīspe mazištanąm yōi həṇti aṣ̌ahe
            ratauuō hāuuanūm paiti ratūm maiδiiōizarəmiie raϑβō</em> ayāb ān gāh kē bawēd guftan <em>xšnaōϑra yasnāica vahmāica xšnōϑrāica frasastaiiaēca</em> agar xšnūman srōš 
            bēd  . : <em>sraōšahe aṣ̌iiehe taxmahe tanumąrahe darši.draōš ahūiriiehe xšnaōϑra</em> . : tā sar ud agar xšnūman ardā fraward bēd <em>ahurahe mazdā̊ raēuuatō xᵛarənaŋhatō
               aməṣ̌anąm spəṇtanąm aṣ̌aōnąm frauuašinąm uγranąm aiβiϑūranąm paōiriiō.t̰kaēšanąm frauuaṣ̌inąm nabānazdištanąm frauuaṣ̌inąm xšnaōϑra yasnāica</em> OD <em>frasastaiiaēca</em> </ab>
         <ab class="indent">
            "If it is the <em>šnūman</em> of the <em>gāhānbār</em>. : <em>raϑβō bərəzatō yō aṣ̌ahe raϑβąm aiiaranąmca asniianąmca māhiianąmca yāiriianąmca sarəδanąmca raϑβąm vīspe
             mazištanąm yōi həṇti aṣ̌ahe ratauuō hāuuanūm paiti ratūm maiδiiōizarəmiie raϑβō</em> (or he should say the corresponding gāh) <em>xšnaōϑra yasnāica vahmāica xšnōϑrāica 
             frasastaiiaēca</em> If it is the <em>šnūman</em> for Srōš : <em>sraōšahe aṣ̌iiehe taxmahe tanumąrahe darši.draōš ahūiriiehe xšnaōϑra</em> up to the end. If it is the <em>šnūman</em> 
            for Ardā Fraward : <em>ahurahe mazdā̊ raēuuatō xᵛarənaŋhatō aməṣ̌anąm spəṇtanąm aṣ̌aōnąm frauuašinąm uγranąm aiβiϑūranąm paōiriiō.t̰kaēšanąm frauuaṣ̌inąm nabānazdištanąm 
            frauuaṣ̌inąm xšnaōϑra yasnāica</em> up to <em>frasastaiiaēca</em>."</ab>
         <ab>VrS0.10 šnūman Var. b (mss. 2030, 2070, 2101):</ab>
         <ab class="indent">
            agar yazišn gāhānbār bēd <em>raϑβō bərəzatō yō aṣ̌ahe raϑβąm aiiaranąmca</em> tā <em>sarəδanąmca raϑβąm vīspe mazištanąm yōi həṇti
            aṣ̌ahe ratauuō hāuuanīm paiti ratīm maiδiiōi.zarəmiiehe raϑβō</em> ayāb ān gāh bēd abāyēd guftan <em>xšnaōϑra yasnāica v. x. f.</em> agar xšnūman ī did bēd abāyēd guftan</ab>
         <ab class="indent">
            "If it is the <em>yazišn</em> of <em>gāhānbār</em>, he has to recite <em>raϑβō bərəzatō yō aṣ̌ahe raϑβąm aiiaranąmca</em> until <em>sarəδanąmca raϑβąm vīspe mazištanąm yōi həṇti
             aṣ̌ahe ratauuō hāuuanīm paiti ratīm maiδiiōi.zarəmiiehe raϑβō</em> or the corresponding <em>gāh</em> <em>xšnaōϑra yasnāica v. x. f.</em> It the dedicatory is another one, then
             he has to say (the corresponding one)."</ab>
         
         <ab>VrS0.10 šnūman Var. c (ms. 2065):</ab>
         <ab class="indent">
            šnūman ān ī bawēd wizārišnīh ud ka šnūman ī gāhānbār <em>raϑβą̇m aiiaraną̇mca asniianą̇mca māhiianą̇mca yāiriianą̇mca sarəδaną̇m y. v. x. f. raϑβō barəzatō ẏōi
            ašahe raϑβą̇m aiiaraną̇mca asniianą̇mca māhiianą̇mca yāiriianą̇mca sarəδaną̇mca vīspe mazištaną̇m ẏōi həṇti aṣ̌ahe ratuuō hāuuanīm paiti ratūm maiδiiōizarəmiiahe raϑβō xšnaoϑra ẏasnāica</em> 
            OD ka gāhą̇mbār <em>maiδiiōšmahe raϑβō</em> har gāhą̇mbār. ki. bāšat̰. ą̇n.bāiiat̰. guftan. cū. ẏašt auuayət̰. xą̇ndən. tā <em>v. x. f.</em> ayāb ān gāh kē bēd</ab>
         <ab class="indent">
            "Perfomance of the corresponding <em>šnūman</em>. If it is the <em>šnūman ī gāhānbār</em> <em>raϑβą̇m aiiaraną̇mca asniianą̇mca māhiianą̇mca yāiriianą̇mca sarəδaną̇m y. v. x. f. raϑβō barəzatō ẏōi
            ašahe raϑβą̇m aiiaraną̇mca asniianą̇mca māhiianą̇mca yāiriianą̇mca sarəδaną̇mca vīspe mazištaną̇m ẏōi həṇti aṣ̌ahe ratuuō hāuuanīm paiti ratūm maiδiiōizarəmiiahe raϑβō. xšnaoϑra. ẏasnāica.</em> 
            when it is then <em>gāhānbār</em> <em>maiδiiōšmahe raϑβō</em>. 
            He has to say here the corresponding <em>gāhānbār</em> until <em>v. x. f.</em> depending the <em>yašt</em> he must perform."</ab>
      </Nerangs>
      <Quotations id="ritualQuotations">         
         <ab>Revāyat of Kāmdin Šapur (MU1, p. 447), on the Visperad ī Gahānbār:</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">(Pers.) bevāǧ gereftan con <em>raϑβą̇m</em> tamām ḫᵛānand pas <em>raϑβō bərəzatō ẏō aṣ̌ahe raϑβą̇m 
               aiiaraną̇mca asniianą̇mca māhīaną̇mca ẏāriianą̇mca sarəδaną̇mca raϑβą̇m vīspa mazištaną̇m ẏōi həṇti aṣ̌ahe 
               ratauuō hāuuanīm paitiratūm maidiiōi.zaramiie raϑβō xšnaoϑra ẏasnāica</em> ke gahanbār midyošahm bāšad 
               <em>maidiiō.ṣ̌amahe raϑβō</em> har gahanbār ke bāšad ān bāyad goftan con yašt āvāyad ḫᵛāndan tā  <em>hiiat̰ vasnā fraṣ̌nō</em> (VrS0.12).</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">"At the taking of the <em>wāz</em>, after they recite completely <em>raϑβą̇m</em> then (they should recite) <em>raϑβō bərəzatō 
               ẏō aṣ̌ahe raϑβą̇m aiiaraną̇mca asniianą̇mca māhīaną̇mca ẏāriianą̇mca sarəδaną̇mca raϑβą̇m vīspa mazištaną̇m ẏōi həṇti 
               aṣ̌ahe ratauuō hāuuanīm paitiratūm maidiiōi.zaramiie raϑβō xšnaoϑra ẏasnāica.</em> If it is during the <em>gahānbār ī
                  maiδiiōišəma</em>, (he should recite) <em>maidiiō.ṣ̌amahe raϑβō</em>. At each <em>gahānbār</em> that should be,
               they should recite as it has to be recited in the Yasna until <Av>hiiat̰ vasnā fraṣ̌nō</Av> (VrS0.12)."</ab>
         
         <ab>On the Panji, Yašt-ī Gahānbār, Yašt-ī Gāϑābiiō:</ab>
         <ab><ab>Revāyat of Kama Bohra (MU1, p. 453):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent"><em>frauuarāne mazdaiiasnō zaraϑuštarəš vīdaēuuō ahura.t̰kaēšō hāuuanə̄ē aṣ̌ahe raϑβe ẏ. v. x. f. 
               sāuuaŋhə̄ē vīsīāica aṣ̌aone aṣ̌ahe raϑβe ẏ. v. x. f. raϑβąm aiiar.nąmca</em> (Pahl.) OD. <em>sarəδaną̇mca ẏ. v. x. f. raϑβō 
                  bərəzatō ẏō aṣ̌ahe raϑβą̇m aiiaraną̇mca</em> (Pahl.) OD. (Pers.) tā <em>sarəδaną̇mca raϑβą̇m vīspe mazištaną̇m ẏō həṇti 
                     aṣ̌ahe ratauuō hāuuanīm paiti ratūm hamaspaϑamaēdiiehe raϑβō xšnaoϑra. ẏ. v. x. f.</em> (Pahl.) zwt (Pers.) zud <em>ẏaϑā 
                        ahū vairiiō zaotā frāmē marūtē</em> (Pers) rāspi <em>ẏaϑā ahū vairiiō ẏō zaotā frāmē marūtē</em> (Pahl.) zwt (Pers.) zud 
               <em>aϑā ratuš</em> kardan</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent"><em>frauuarāne mazdaiiasnō zaraϑuštarəš vīdaēuuō ahura.t̰kaēšō hāuuanə̄ē aṣ̌ahe raϑβe ẏ. v. x. f. 
               sāuuaŋhə̄ē vīsīāica aṣ̌aone aṣ̌ahe raϑβe ẏ. v. x. f. raϑβąm aiiar.nąmca</em> until <em>sarəδaną̇mca ẏ. v. x. f. raϑβō 
                  bərəzatō ẏō aṣ̌ahe raϑβą̇m aiiaraną̇mca</em> until <em>sarəδaną̇mca raϑβą̇m vīspe mazištaną̇m ẏō həṇti 
                     aṣ̌ahe ratauuō hāuuanīm paiti ratūm hamaspaϑamaēdiiehe raϑβō xšnaoϑra. ẏ. v. x. f.</em>. (Then) the <em>zōt</em>
               <em>ẏaϑā ahū vairiiō zaotā frāmē marūtē</em>, the <em>rāspi</em> <em>ẏaϑā ahū vairiiō ẏō zaotā frāmē marūtē</em>
               and the <em>zōt</em> has to perform the <em>aϑā ratuš</em>.</ab> </ab> --&gt;
         
      </Quotations>
   </Ritual>
   <translation>
      <include type="CAB" corresp="CABTrVrS0.10"/>
   </translation>
</text>