<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text xml:id="VrS15.1" status="created">
   <!-- created, approved, updated-->
   <header>
      <creators>
         <creator>Porro</creator>
         <creator>Cantera</creator>
      </creators>
      <created>1 June 2019</created>
   </header>
   <div type="Stanza" sameAs="" xml:id="VrS15.1">
      <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/nerang/visperad_nerang" xpointer="VrS15.1NerangTransc.a"/>
      <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/static/Visperad_Static" xpointer="VrS6.1"/>
   </div>
   <Speaker>
      <SpeakerInfo>
         <div>
            <ab class="ab_indent">zōt ud rāspīg <em>sastica</em>, zōt <em>vaṇtāca</em>... vid. Nērangs; Anklesaria, Geldner.</ab>
         </div>
      </SpeakerInfo>
   </Speaker>
   <Apparatus>
      <Critical/>
      <Commentary/>
      <RecitationInstruction>
         <ab>VrS15.1a <em>sastica vaṇtāca rafnaŋhāca</em>...] <em>vaṇtāca rafnaŋhāca viϑušaēibiiasca zaoϑrābiiō</em> OD <em>yeŋ́hē mē</em> (VrS15.2) 2065, 2070.</ab>
      </RecitationInstruction>
   </Apparatus>
   <Parallels>
      <Parallels>
         <ab><em>aršuxδaēibiiasca vāγžibiiō</em> = Y16.1, Y16.2; ~ Y9.25 <em>vacąm ərəžuxδanąm [...] ərəǔxδəm [...] vācim</em>; ~ Y7.30 <em>aršuxδəm vācim</em>;  ~ Y60.5 <em>aršuxδō vāxš</em>; ~ Y71.10 <em>vacō aršuxδa</em>; ~ Y27.8 <em>aršuxδanąmcā vacąm</em>; ~ VrS31.13 <em>aršuxδanąmca vacaŋhąm</em> (!), etc.</ab>
         <ab><em>bərəja vaŋhə̄uš aṣ̌ahe bərəja daēnaiiā̊ vaŋhuiiā̊ māzdaiiasnōiš</em> quotes Y35.1 <em>bərəjā vaŋhə̄uš aṣ̌ahe bərəjā daēnaiiā̊ vaŋhuiiā̊ māzdaiiasnōiš</em> = VrS65.15.</ab>
         <ab> <em>daēnaiiā̊ vaŋhuiiā̊ māzdaiiasnōiš</em> = Y0.10, Y1.14, Y22.4, Y22.24, Y22.25, Y24.3, Y24.8, Y24.29, Y25.3, Y35.1, Y53.11 (x2), Y66.19, Y66.20, Y70.3, Y72.7, Y72.11, VrS87.11; 
            ~ Y9.26, Yt16.5, Yt16.8, Yt16.11, Yt16.14, Yt16.16, Yt16.18 <em>vaŋᵛhīm daēnąm māzdaiiasnīm</em>
         </ab>
      </Parallels>
   </Parallels>
   <Ritual>
      <Nerangs id="ritualNerangs">
         <ab>VrS15.1 Var. a (mss. 2000, 2065):</ab>
         <ab class="ab_indent">
            zōt ud rāspīg harw dō sastica guftan barsom gušādan ud grih andak-ē šust kardan barsom hōy ud dašn paydāg kardan ud datuš †ēw- tāg ī stabrtar ud rāsttar abar abrāštan ud abar 
            barsomdān bastan <em>vaṇtāca</em>. ...</ab> 
         <ab class="ab_indent">
            "The <em>zōt</em> and the <em>rāspīg</em>, both, should recite <em>sasti</em>. He should loose the <em>barsom</em>, make the knot a bit slack***/ wash a bit the knot, 
            show the left and the right side of the <em>barsom</em>, raise the strongest and straightest twig as <em>datuš</em> and tie it to the <em>barsomdān</em> (and then continue with) 
            <em>vaṇtāca</em>. ..."</ab> 
         
         <ab>VrS15.1 Var. b (mss. 2010, 2030, 2040, 2101, 2106, 2109, 4000, 4010, 4020, 4025, 4040, 4045, 4050, 4161, 4162, 5020):</ab>
         <ab class="ab_indent">
            <em>sastica</em>. zōt ud rāspīg harw dō bē gōwišn barsom az barsomdān ul stānišn bē dō nēm abāz kunišn hašt pad dōgānag-ē az dašn ōšmurdan ēk tāg rāsttar ud stabrtar pad 
            datuš kunišn ud bē abrāzēnišn ud barsom ō ī māhrōy bandišn dast abar barsom nihišn guftan vaṇtāca... <em>daēnaiiā̊ vaŋhuiiā̊ māzdaiiasnōiš</em> skūrag abāz rāst kunišn ǰīv bē baxšišn</ab>
         <ab class="ab_indent">
            "Both, the <em>zōt</em> and the <em>rāspīg</em> have to recite <em>sastica</em>. (The <em>zōt</em>) has to take the <em>barsom</em> from the <em>barsomdān</em> 
            and divide it into two halves. He should count eight pairs from the right side. He should make one twig that is the straightest and the strongest to <em>datuš</em> and he has to raise 
            it and to tie the <em>barsom</em> to the <em>māhrōy</em> and put his hand on the <em>barsom</em>. He should recite <em>vaṇtāca ... daēnaiiā̊ vaŋhuiiā̊ māzdaiiasnōiš</em>.
            He has to turn up again the (inverted) <em>skūrag</em> and distribute <em>ǰīwām</em> (into the <em>skūrag</em>)"</ab>
         
         <ab>VrS15.1 Var. c (ms. 2101):</ab>
         <ab class="ab_indent">
            <em>sastica</em>. zōt ud rāspīg harw dō bē gōwišn barsom abar gīrišn barsom dašn ud hōy paydāg bē kunišn bē dō nēm abāz kunišn hašt pad dōgānag-ē az dašn ōšmurdan ēk tāg 
            rāsttar ud stabrtar pad datuš kunišn ud bē abrāzēnišn ud barsom ō ī māhrōy bandišn dast abar barsom nihišn guftan <em>vaṇtāca ... daēnaiiā̊ vaŋhuiiā̊ māzdaiiasnōiš</em> skūrag 
            abāz rāst kunišn ǰīw abāz baxšišn </ab> 
         <ab class="ab_indent">
            "Both, the <em>zōt</em> and the <em>rāspīg</em> have to recite <em>sastica</em>. (The <em>zōt</em>) has to take the <em>barsom</em>, show the right and left sides and 
            divide it into two halves. He should count eight pairs from the right side. He should make one twig that is the straightest and the strongest to <em>datuš</em> and he has to raise it 
            and to tie the <em>barsom</em> to the <em>māhrōy</em> and put his hand on the <em>barsom</em>. He should recite <em>vaṇtāca ... daēnaiiā̊ vaŋhuiiā̊ māzdaiiasnōiš</em>. 
            He has to turn up again the (inverted) <em>skūrag</em> and distribute <em>ǰīwām</em> (into the <em>skūrag</em>)."</ab>
         
         <ab>VrS15.1 Var. d (ms. 2070):</ab>
         <ab class="ab_indent">
            <em>sastica</em> datuš bē abrāzēnišn <em>vaṇtāca</em></ab>
         <ab class="ab_indent">
            "Between <em>sastica</em> and <em>vaṇtāca</em>, he has to raise the <em>datuš</em>."</ab>
      </Nerangs>
   </Ritual>
   <translation>
      <include type="CAB" corresp="CABTrVrS15.1"/>
   </translation>
</text>