<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text xml:id="VrS29.3" status="created">
   <!-- created, approved, updated-->
   <header>
      <creators>
         <creator>Porro</creator>
         <creator>Cantera</creator>
      </creators>
      <created>1 June 2019</created>
   </header>
   <div type="Stanza" sourceIs="Y25.3" xml:id="VrS29.3">
      <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/static/Visperad_Static" xpointer="VrSY25.3"/>
      <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/nerang/visperad_nerang" xpointer="VrS29.3NerangTransc.a"/>
   </div>
   <Speaker>
      <SpeakerInfo>
         <div>
            <ab class="ab_indent">zōt ud rāspīg: vid. VrS29.1.</ab>
         </div>
      </SpeakerInfo>
   </Speaker>
   <Apparatus>
      <Critical/>
      <Commentary/>
   </Apparatus>
   <Parallels/>
   <Ritual>
      <Nerangs id="ritualNerangs">
         <ab>VrS29.3 Var. a (mss. 2007, 2010, 2104, 2109):</ab>
         <ab class="ab_indent">
            ... <em>vīspaca vohu mazdaδāta aṣ̌a.ciθra yazamaide</em> hōm ud urwarām andar hāwan abganišn xšnūman az ān ī bēd wizārdan (VrS29.4) agar xšnūman ahlawān padiš bēd guftan tā  
            <em>staōmi zbaiiemi ...</em> (VrS30.13) <em>yeŋ́hē.hātąm tā̊sca yazamaide</em> ka ēzišn gāhānbār (VrS29.3) <em>mazdaδāta aṣ̌a.ciθra yazamaide</em>  (VrS29.4) <em>ratauuō vīspe mazišta yazamaide aiiara asńiia māhiia yāiriia
               sarəδa yazamaide hāuuanīm aṣ̌auuanəm aṣ̌ahe raϑβəm yazamaide maiδiiōizarəmaēm aṣ̌auuanəm aṣ̌ahe ratūm yazamaide</em> ayāb ān gāh bēd</ab>  
         <ab class="ab_indent">
            "At ... <em>vīspaca vohu mazdaδāta aṣ̌a.ciθra yazamaide</em>, he has to throw <em>hōm</em> and <em>urwarām</em> into the <em>hāwan</em>. They should utter the 
            corresponding <em>šnūman</em> (VrS29.4). If the <em>šnūman</em> contains the one for the <em>ahlawān</em>, they should recite until <em>staōmi zbaiiemi ...</em> (VrS30.13) <em>yeŋ́hē.hātąm tā̊sca 
               yazamaide</em>. When it is a liturgy for Gāhānbār, (they should recite) (VrS29.3) <em>mazdaδāta aṣ̌a.ciθra yazamaide</em>  (VrS29.4) <em>ratauuō vīspe mazišta yazamaide aiiara asńiia māhiia yāiriia
            sarəδa yazamaide hāuuanīm aṣ̌auuanəm aṣ̌ahe raϑβəm yazamaide maiδiiōizarəmaēm aṣ̌auuanəm aṣ̌ahe ratūm yazamaide</em> or the corresponding <em>gāh</em>."</ab>
         
         <ab>VrS29.3 Var. b (mss. 2030, 2101, 2106):</ab>
         <ab class="ab_indent">
            ... <em>vīspaca vohu mazdaδāta aṣ̌a.ciθra yazamaide</em> xšnūman az ān ī bēd wizārdan (VrS29.4) ka pad xšnūman <em>aṣ̌āunąm</em> padiš bēd <em>staōmi zbaiiemi</em> (VrS30.13) <em>yeŋ́hē.hātąm</em> 
            ka ēzišn gāhānbār bēd (VrS29.3) <em>mazdaδāta aṣ̌a.ciθra yazamaide</em> (VrS29.4) <em>ratauuō vīspe mazišta yazamaide aiiara asńiia māhiia yāiriia sarəδa yazamaide hāuuanīm aṣ̌auuanəm aṣ̌ahe raϑβəm
            yazamaide maiδiiōizarəmaēm aṣ̌auuanəm aṣ̌ahe ratūm yazamaide</em> ayāb ān gāh bēd.</ab>
         <ab class="ab_indent">
            "At ... <em>vīspaca vohu mazdaδāta aṣ̌a.ciθra yazamaide</em>, they should utter the corresponding <em>šnūman</em> (VrS29.4). When it contains the one for the <em>aṣ̌āunąm</em>, 
            (they should recite) <em>staōmi zbaiiemi</em> (VrS30.13) <em>yeŋ́hē.hātąm</em> When it is a liturgy for the Gāhānbār, (they should recite) (VrS29.3) <em>mazdaδāta aṣ̌a.ciθra yazamaide</em> (VrS29.4) <em>ratauuō vīspe mazišta 
            yazamaide aiiara asńiia māhiia yāiriia sarəδa yazamaide hāuuanīm aṣ̌auuanəm aṣ̌ahe raϑβəm yazamaide maiδiiōizarəmaēm aṣ̌auuanəm aṣ̌ahe ratūm yazamaide</em> or the corresponding <em>gāh</em>."</ab>
         
         <ab>VrS29.3 Var. c (ms. 2040):</ab>
         <ab class="ab_indent">
            ... <em>vīspaca vohu mazdaδāta aṣ̌a.ciθra yazamaide</em> ka gāhānbār bēd (VrS29.4) <em>ratauuō vīspe mazišta yazamaide aiiara asńiia māhiia yāiriia sarəδa yazamaide hāuuanīm aṣ̌auuanəm
               aṣ̌ahe raϑβəm yazamaide maiδiiōizarəmaēm aṣ̌auuanəm aṣ̌ahe ratūm yazamaide</em> ... (VrS30.11) <em>haδa.zaōϑrəm haδa.aiβiiā̊ŋhanəm</em> tā ō (VrS29.3) hōm ud urwarām andar hāwan nihādan <em>aṣ̌a.ciθra
               yazamaide</em> (VrS29.4) <em>ahurəm mazdąm raēuuaṇtəm xᵛarənaŋᵛhaṇtəm yazamaide aməṣ̌ā spəṇtā huxšaϑrā huδā̊ŋhō yazamaide aṣ̌āunąm vaŋᵛhīš sūrā̊ spə̄ntā̊ frauuaṣ̌aiiō staōmi zbaiiemi</em> …</ab> 
         <ab class="ab_indent">
            "At ... <em>vīspaca vohu mazdaδāta aṣ̌a.ciθra yazamaide</em>, when it is a Gāhānbār, (they should recite) (VrS29.4) <em>ratauuō vīspe mazišta yazamaide aiiara asńiia māhiia yāiriia sarəδa
               yazamaide hāuuanīm aṣ̌auuanəm aṣ̌ahe raϑβəm yazamaide maiδiiōizarəmaēm  aṣ̌auuanəm aṣ̌ahe ratūm yazamaide</em> ... (VrS30.11) <em>haδa.zaōϑrəm haδa.aiβiiā̊ŋhanəm</em> until (the end). (VrS29.3)
            He should put <em>hōm</em> and <em>urwarām</em> in the <em>hāwan</em> (and then) <em>aṣ̌a.ciθra yazamaide</em> (VrS29.4) <em>ahurəm mazdąm raēuuaṇtəm xᵛarənaŋᵛhaṇtəm 
            yazamaide aməṣ̌ā spəṇtā huxšaϑrā huδā̊ŋhō yazamaide aṣ̌āunąm vaŋᵛhīš sūrā̊ spə̄ntā̊ frauuaṣ̌aiiō staōmi zbaiiemi</em> ..."</ab>
      </Nerangs>
   </Ritual>
   <translation>
      <include type="CAB" corresp="CABTrVrS29.3"/>
   </translation>
</text>