<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text xml:id="VrS25.31" status="create            d">
   <!-- created, approved, updated-->
   <header>
      <creators>
         <creator>Porro</creator>
         <creator>Cantera</creator>
      </creators>
      <created>1 June 2019</created>
   </header>
   <div type="Stanza" sourceIs="Y22.24" xml:id="VrS25.31">
      <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/static/Visperad_Static" xpointer="VrSY22.21"/>
      <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/static/Visperad_Static" xpointer="VrSY22.22a" on_line="in1lineblock"/>
      <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/blocks/ShnumanGen" xpointer="ShnumanGen42" on_line="in1line"/>
      <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/static/Visperad_Static" xpointer="VrSY22.22b" on_line="in1line"/>
   </div>
   <Speaker>
      <SpeakerInfo>
         <div>
            <ab class="ab_indent">zōt ud rāspīg: vid. Y22.21.</ab>
         </div>
      </SpeakerInfo>
   </Speaker>
   <Apparatus>
      <Critical/>
      <Commentary/>
      <RecitationInstruction>
         <ab>VrS25.31a <em>imąmcā uruuarąm</em> ...]  šnwmn' wcʾlšnyh bwndk gwptn 2000.</ab>
         <ab>VrS25.31d <em>xšnūmaine</em> ...] HT yšt' gʾsʾnbʾl YHWWNyt' <em>xšnūmaine raϑβō bərəzatō yō</em> OD OL Y ... <em>maiδiiōizarəmaiiehe raϑβō aōxtō.nāmanō yazatahe ā. y.</em>  (err. add. <em>ā. y.</em>) ʾywp ẔK gʾs MNW YHWWNyt' gwptn' 2010;
            HT ycšn' gʾsʾnbʾl YHWWNyt' <em>xšnūmaine raϑβō bərəzatō ... maiδiiōizarəmaiiehe raϑβō</em> ʾywp ẔK gʾs YHWWNyt' <em>aōxtō.nāmanō yazatahe</em> 2030, 2106, 2109;
            MN <em>iməm haōməm</em> (VrS25.29a) ... HT ycšn' gʾssʾnbʾl <em>xšnīmaine raϑβō bərəzatō ... maiδiiōizarəmiiehe raϑβō aōxtō.nāmanō yazatahe</em> II bʾl gwptn' 
            HT' plwlʾn' YHWWNyt <em>xšnīmaine ahurahe... nabānazdištanąm frauuaṣ̌anąm aōxtō.nāmanō yazatahe</em> II bʾl <em>ā. y. auuaŋhā̊</em> (VrS25.33) 2040;
            HT ycšn' gʾsʾnbʾl YHWWNyt' <em>xšnūmaine raϑβō bərəzatō ... maiδiiōizarəmaiiehe raϑβō</em> ʾywp ẔK gʾs YHWWNyt' <em>aōxtō.nāmanō yazatahe</em> II bʾl gwptn' 2070;
            <em>xšnīmaine</em> ẔK Y YHWWNyt gwptn' HT ʾycšn' gʾsʾnbʾl YHWWNyt <em>xšnīmaine raϑβō ... maiδiiōizarəmiiehe raϑβō</em> ʾywp ẔK gʾs YHWWNyt <em>aōxtō.nāmanō yazatahe</em> II bʾl gwptn' 2101.</ab>
      </RecitationInstruction>
   </Apparatus>
   <Parallels/>
   <Ritual>
      <Nerangs id="ritualNerangs">
         <ab>VrS25.31 Var. a (mss. 2005, 2010, 2030, 2040, 2101, 2104, 2106, 2109):</ab>
         <ab class="ab_indent">
            ... <em>aṣ̌a.ciθra āiiese</em> agar yašt gāhānbār bēd <em>xšnūmaine raθβō bərəzatō … yōi həṇti aṣ̌ahe ratauuō hāuuanīm paiti ratūm maiδiiōizarəmiiehe raθβō</em> ayāb ān 
            gāh bēd <em>aōxtō.nāmanō yazatahe</em> (VrS25.32) dudīgar bār az <em>iməm haōməm aṣ̌aiia uzdātəm āiiese</em> tā gyāg dō bār guftan sāzišn hāmag xūb bē nigerišn ud bōy ō ī  ātaxš 
            dahišn agar xšnūman dudīgar bēd ka xšnūman ī ahlawān padiš bēd <em>āiiese yešti auuaŋ́hā̊ frauuaṣ̌aiiō</em>. …</ab> 
         <ab class="ab_indent">
            "... <em>aṣ̌a.ciθra āiiese</em> If it is the service of the <em>Gāhānbār: xšnūmaine raθβō bərəzatō … yōi həṇti aṣ̌ahe ratauuō hāuuanīm paiti ratūm maiδiiōizarəmiiehe raθβō</em> 
            (or the corresponding <em>gāh</em>) <em>aōxtō.nāmanō yazatahe</em> (VrS25.32) A second time: they should say twice from <em>iməm haōməm aṣ̌aiia uzdātəm āiiese</em> until this 
            passage. He has to gaze carefully at all implements and to give <em>bōy</em> to the fire. If the <em>šnūman</em> is another one, when the <em>šnūman</em> is one that contains 
            <em>ahlawān</em>, (they have to recite:) <em>āiiese yešti auuaŋ́hā̊ frauuaṣ̌aiiō</em> …"</ab>
         
         <ab>VrS25.31 Var. b (ms. 2000):</ab>
         <ab class="ab_indent">
            <em>iməm haoməm</em> čīyōn pad yašt bēd tā šnūman wizārišnīh bowandag guftan agar šnūman ardā ī frawahr bēd <em>auuaŋ́hā̊ frauuaṣ̌aiiō</em> tā <em>vaŋhuš</em></ab>
         <ab class="ab_indent">
            "They should recite <em>iməm haoməm</em> complete as it is in the <em>yašt</em> until the performance of the <em>šnūman</em>. If it is the <em>šnūman</em> of Ardā Frawahr, 
            (they have to recite:) <em>auuaŋ́hā̊ frauuaṣ̌aiiō</em> OD <em>vaŋhuš</em>."</ab>
      </Nerangs>
      <Quotations id="ritualQuotations">
         <Quotations id="ritualQuotations">
            <ab><ab>Revāyat of Kamdīn Šapur (MU1, p. 448) on the Visperad ī Gāhānbār:</ab>
               <ab class="ab_indent"><em>əməm haoməm aṣ̌aiia uzdātəm āiie.</em> (VrS25.29) (Pahl) LD  <em>vīspaca vōhū mazdaδātahe aṣ̌aciϑra āiie. xšnūmaine raϑβō bərəzatō ẏō aṣ̌ahe raϑβąm aiiaraną̇mca</em> (Pahl.) LWD <em>yō həṇti aṣ̌ahe ratuuō hāuuanīm paiti 
                  ratūm maiδiiō.zaramaiiahe raϑβō aoxtō.nāmanō ẏazatahe iməm haoməm</em> (Pahl.) LWD <em>aoxtō.nāmanō ẏazatahe āiie. arəzahebiiō sauuahebiiō</em> (VrS25.36) (Per.) gāhanbār ke bāšad ān ḫešnuman bāyad goftan
                  (Paz.) u.<em>fradaδafšubiiō</em>.</ab>
               <ab class="ab_indent"><em>əməm haoməm aṣ̌aiia uzdātəm āiie.</em> (VrS25.29) until  <em>vīspaca vōhū mazdaδātahe aṣ̌aciϑra āiie. xšnūmaine raϑβō bərəzatō ẏō aṣ̌ahe raϑβąm aiiaraną̇mca</em> until <em>yō həṇti aṣ̌ahe ratuuō hāuuanīm paiti 
                  ratūm maiδiiō.zaramaiiahe raϑβō aoxtō.nāmanō ẏazatahe iməm haoməm</em> until <em>aoxtō.nāmanō ẏazatahe āiie. arəzahebiiō sauuahebiiō</em> (VrS25.36) (Per.) 
                  In case it is the Gāhānbār, this <em>šnūman</em> should be recited and<em>fradaδafšubiiō</em>.</ab>
            </ab>
         </Quotations>
         <ab><ab>In case of Visperad-ī Gāhānbār, from Revayat of Kāma Bohra (MU1, p. 454):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent"><em>aməm haoməm aṣ̌aiia uzadātəm āiie.</em> (Pahl.) OD (Per.) tā <em>aṣ̌aciϑra xšnūmaine raϑβō bərəzatō ẏō aṣ̌ahe raϑβą̇m aiiaraną̇mca asniianą̇mca māhiianą̇mca ẏāiriianą̇mca sarəδaną̇mca raϑβą̇m 
               vīspe mazištaną̇m ẏōi həṇti aṣ̌ahe ratuuō hāuuanīm paiti ratūm hamaspaϑmaēδiiahe raϑβō aoxtō.nāmanō ẏazatahe (VrS25.32) iməm haoməm aṣ̌aiia uzdātəm āiie.</em> (Per.) tā sar .</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent"><em>aməm haoməm aṣ̌aiia uzadātəm āiie.</em> until <em>aṣ̌aciϑra xšnūmaine raϑβō bərəzatō ẏō aṣ̌ahe raϑβą̇m aiiaraną̇mca asniianą̇mca māhiianą̇mca ẏāiriianą̇mca sarəδaną̇mca raϑβą̇m 
               vīspe mazištaną̇m ẏōi həṇti aṣ̌ahe ratuuō hāuuanīm paiti ratūm hamaspaϑmaēδiiahe raϑβō aoxtō.nāmanō ẏazatahe (VrS25.32) iməm haoməm aṣ̌aiia uzdātəm āiie.</em> to the end  <em>māhiianą̇mca yāiriianą̇mca sarəδaną̇mca raϑβą̇m
                  vīspamazištaną̇m ẏō həṇti aṣ̌ahe ratuuō hāuuanīm paiti ratūm hamaspaϑmidiiahe raϑβō aoxtō.nāmanō ẏazatahe</em>.</ab></ab>
         
      </Quotations>
   </Ritual>
   <translation>
      <include type="CAB" corresp="CABTrVrS25.31"/>
   </translation>
</text>