<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text xml:id="VrS31.3" status="created">
   <!-- created, approved, updated-->
   <header>
      <creators>
         <creator>Porro</creator>
         <creator>Cantera</creator>
      </creators>
      <created>1 June 2019</created>
   </header>
   <div type="Stanza" sameAs="" xml:id="VrS31.3">
      <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/nerang/visperad_nerang" xpointer="VrS31.3NerangTransc.a"/>
      <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/blocks/prayers/YAV" xpointer="YAV"/>
      <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/blocks/prayers/YAV" xpointer="YAV"/>
      <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/blocks/prayers/YAV" xpointer="YAV"/>
      <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/blocks/prayers/YAV" xpointer="YAV"/>
   </div>
   <Apparatus>
      <Critical/>
      <Commentary/>
   </Apparatus>
   <Parallels/>
   <Ritual>
      <Nerangs id="ritualNerangs">
         <ab>VrS31.3 (ms. 2000):</ab>
         <ab class="ab_indent">
            <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō</em> čahār pad ēk ī fradom pad <em>xš́iiaōθananąm</em> hōm ēk bār hunīdan ud pad aŋhəuš ēk bār hunīdan ud pad <em>mazdāi</em> ēk bār hunīdan 
            ud pad dudīgar <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō</em> pad <em>xš́iiaōθananąm</em> dō bār hunīdan pad <em>aŋhəuš</em> dō bār hunīdan pad mazdāi dō bār hunīdan pad sidīgar 
            <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō</em> pad <em>xš́iiaōθananąm</em> sē bār hunīdan pad aŋhəuš sē bār hunīdan pad <em>mazdāi</em> sē bār hunīdan ud abarhāwan gōš bālā abar dāštan 
            ud pad ēk ī čahārom was hāwan frōd kōftan ud škāftan</ab> 
         <ab class="ab_indent">
            "(They should recite) the <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō</em> four times. During the first one, he should pound the <em>hōm</em> once at <em>xš́iiaōθananąm</em>, pound it once at 
            <em>aŋhəuš</em> and pound it once at <em>mazdāi</em>. During the second <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō</em>, he should pound the hōm twice at <em>xš́iiaōθananąm</em>, pound 
            it twice at <em>aŋhəuš</em> and pound it twice at <em>mazdāi</em>. During the third <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō</em>, he should pound the <em>hōm</em> three times at  
            <em>xš́iiaōθananąm</em>, pound it three times at <em>aŋhəuš</em> and pound it three times at <em>mazdāi</em> and hold up the <em>abarhāwan</em> to the height of the
            ears. During the fourth one, he has to strike and hit continuously the <em>hāwan</em>."</ab>
      </Nerangs>
   </Ritual>
   <translation>
      <include type="CAB" corresp="CABTrVrS31.3"/>
   </translation>
</text>