<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text xml:id="VrS87.1" status="created">
   <!-- created, approved, updated-->
   <header>
      <creators>
         <creator>Porro</creator>
         <creator>Cantera</creator>
      </creators>
      <created>1 June 2019</created>
   </header>
   <div type="Stanza" sameAs="" xml:id="VrS87.1">
      <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/blocks/prayers/AV" xpointer="AV"/>
      <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/blocks/prayers/AV" xpointer="AV"/>
      <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/blocks/prayers/AV" xpointer="AV"/>
   </div>
   <Apparatus>
      <Critical/>
      <Commentary/>
   </Apparatus>
   <Parallels/>
   <Ritual>
      <Nerangs id="ritualNerangs">
         <ab>VrS87.1 (mss. 2005, 2007, 2010, 2030, 2101, 2102, 2104, 2106, 2109):</ab>
         <ab class="ab_indent">
            ka panǰag weh bēd yazišn ardā fraward ǰud az gāhānbār ud srōš tā abārīg <em>yā̊ vīsāδa</em> ō gōwišn ka gāhānbār ud srōš bēd nē gōwišn agar ardā farward padiš ka <em>yaōždātą</em>
            guft pas zōt ud rāspīg <em>aṣ̌əm vohū</em> sē guftan I <em>frauuarāne</em> ud <em>hāuuanə̄e</em> ud <em>sāuuaŋhə̄e</em> ud <em>raθβąm</em> tā gyāg <em>ahurahe
               mazdā̊ raeuuatō xᵛarənaŋᵛhatō aməšanąm spəṇtanąm aṣ̌āunąm frauuašinąm</em> tā <em>nabānazdištanąm frauuašanąm xšnaoϑra</em> tā sar guftan ka panǰag ī
            gāhānīg bēd gāθābiiō tā sar guftan zōt <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō yō ātrauuaxšō</em> rāspīg <em>aθā ratuš</em> kardan hamrāspīg <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō yō zaōtā</em> zōt <em>
               aϑā ratuš</em> kardan zōt ud rāspīg <em>ahurəm mazdąm raēuuaṇtəm xᵛarənaŋᵛhaṇtəm yazamaide aməṣ̌ā spəṇtā huxšaϑrā huδā̊ŋhō yazamaide frauuaṣ̌aiiō yazamaide yā̊ vīsāδa
                  āuuaiieiṇti hamaspaϑmaēdaēm paiti ratūm</em> tā. <em>nəmaŋha</em> ka panǰag ī gāhānīg bēd <em>gāθā spəṇtā</em> tā sar gōwišn barsom abar barsomdān nihišn skūrag
            ī zōhr abar gīrišn zōhr bē nigerišn <em>aṣ̌əm vohū</em> sē guftan</ab>  
         <ab class="ab_indent">
            "When it is (a performance during) the Five Good Days, a service for Ardā Fraward except for Gāhānbār or Srōš, he has to recite the text until the additional <em>yā̊ vīsāδa</em>.
            When it is a ceremony for Gāhānbār or for Srōš, then he has not to recite this text. If the <em>frauuaṣ̌is</em> are mentioned (in the <em>šnūman</em>), then, when he has said 
            <em>yaōždātą</em>, then the <em>zōt</em> and the <em>rāspīg</em> recite three <em>aṣ̌əm vohū</em>, then the <em>frauuarāne</em>. and the section <em>hāuuanə̄e</em> 
            and the section <em>sāuuaŋhə̄e</em> and the section <em>raθβąm</em>. until (the <em>šnūman</em>) <em>ahurahe mazdā̊ raeuuatō xᵛarənaŋᵛhatō aməšanąm spəṇtanąm aṣ̌āunąm 
               frauuašinąm</em> OD <em>nabānazdištanąm frauuašanąm xšnaoϑra</em> until the end. When they are the Five Days of the Gāθās, they should say <em>gāθābiiō</em> until the 
            end. Then the <em>zōt</em> should say <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō yō ātrauuaxšō</em> and the <em>rāspīg</em> should answer <em>aθā ratuš</em>. The same <em>rāspīg</em>
            should say: <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō yō zaōtā</em>. The zōt should answer: <em>aϑā ratuš</em>. The <em>zōt</em> and the <em>rāspīg</em> should recite togeher: <em>ahurəm 
               mazdąm raēuuaṇtəm xᵛarənaŋᵛhaṇtəm yazamaide aməṣ̌ā spəṇtā huxšaϑrā huδā̊ŋhō yazamaide frauuaṣ̌aiiō yazamaide yā̊ vīsāδa āuuaiieiṇti hamaspaϑmaēdaēm paiti ratūm</em> until 
            <em>nəmaŋha</em>. When they are the Five Days of the Gāθās, they should recite the section <em>gāθā spəṇtā</em>. He has to put the <em>barsom</em> on the <em>barsomdān</em>, 
            take the <em>skūrag</em> for the <em>zōhr</em> and gaze at the <em>zōhr</em>. They should recite three <em>aṣ̌əm vohū</em>."</ab>
      </Nerangs>
   </Ritual>
   <translation>
      <include type="CAB" corresp="CABTrVrS87.1"/>
   </translation>
</text>