<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text xml:id="VytVrS79.0" status="created">
   <!-- created, approved, updated-->
   <header>
      <creators>
         <creator>Porro</creator>
         <creator>Cantera</creator>
      </creators>
      <created>1 June 2019</created>
   </header>
   <div type="Stanza" sameAs="" xml:id="VytVrS79.0">
      <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/blocks/Frauuarane_BP" xpointer="Frauuarane_BP9"/>
   </div>
   <Apparatus>
      <Critical/>
      <Commentary>
         <ab> WazGr8 <em>yaθā. ahū....</em>] In contrast to the Visperad and Vīdēvdād, the Vyt
            manuscripts show the double <em>wāz gīrišnīh</em>. Ms. 5010, 5030, 5105 and the rest of
            manuscripts of this group show a <em>nērang</em> indicating it, see below. Ms. 5020
            gives the text of the double <em>wāz gīrišnīh</em> in extenso. Ms. 5102 have the typical
               <em>wāz gīrišnīh</em> of the Visperad, because it is dereived from a Visperad
            manuscript. (AC)</ab>
      </Commentary>
   </Apparatus>
   <Parallels/>
   <Ritual>
      <Nerangs id="ritualNerangs"> Ms. 5010 (= 5030, 5105) <ab>zōt ud rāspīg wāz gīrišnīh dōgānag
            kardan </ab>
         <ab> The <em>zōt</em> and the <em>rāspīg</em> have to make the double <em>wāz
            gīrišnīh</em></ab>
      </Nerangs>
      <Commentary id="ritualCommentary">
          <ab>In the other ceremonies, the Frauuarāne of the second Drōn Yašt (VrS79.0) is the same as in the first Drōn Yašt. Only the manuscripts
         of the Vīštāsp Yašt (with exception of ms. 5102) show the double <em>wāz gīrišnīh</em>. Two alternative explanations are possible: 1. the mansucripts of the Visperad
         nad the Vīdēvdād have taken the Frauuaraēne of the Srōš Drōn and used it wrongly in the
         second one 2. there is a real ritual difference between the Drōn Yašt and the rest of
         the ceremony and the simple <em>wāz gīrišnīh</em> is correct in the all manuscripots, but the ones
         of the Vīštāsp Yašt. Although there is no certainty, I consider the first hypothesis more
         likely, since the scribes are usually well aware of the difference between the first and
         the second Drōn Yašt and copy them faithfully. Accordingly, the dissimilar <em>wāz gīrišnīh</em>
         in all Vıštāsp Yašt might be a common error harking back to Rōstam Mihrābān’s manuscript
         or his source. (AC)</ab>
      </Commentary>
   </Ritual>
   <translation>
      <include type="CAB" corresp="CABTrVytVrS79.0"/>
   </translation>
</text>