<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div type="ceremony" n="NerWaras">
    <header>
        <creators>
            <creator>Cantera</creator>
        </creators>
        <created>02 March 2020</created>
        <updated/>
    </header>
    <div n="1" type="chapter">
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="NerWaras1.1NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers"> pas varas z-inke az gāv va varazā mičinand dast rā b-āb-e pādyāvi
                pāk bešuyad va ān varas rā be-dast girad se bār b-āb-e pādyāvi bešuyad</ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="NerWaras1.1NerangEnglish.a">Afterwards,
                they cut the <em>varas</em> from a cow or beef. He washes the hand clean with
                <em>pādyāb</em> and takes the <em>varas</em> with the hand and wash it three
                times with <em>pādyāb</em>.</ab1>
        </div>
    </div>
    <div n="2" type="chapter">
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="NerWaras2.1NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">aṣ̌əm vōhū čahār guftan ke se ašem vohū az bon ō sar šostan va pas
                se bār ḥalqe begardānand pas yek ḥalqe-ye zarrin b-āb pādyāvi bešuyand va ān varas
                ḥalqe-karde dar gardan-e ān andazand va ān ḥalqe-ye zarrin rā be-sar-e barsom-čin
                konand va yek sukure porr az āb-e pādyāb konand va yek-pāre-ye var-e ātaš vaharām
                dar ānǧā konand yaʾni xākestar-e ātaš šeib-e-ān nahānd čenānke ḫorm-e ātaš bālā na-yāyad va ān āb be-ǧuš āyad va
                panǧāh-o yek bār ān varas b-āb ǧušān foru barand va bar āvarand zud āb-e sard b-ānǧā
                foru rizand </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="NerWaras2.1NerangEnglish.a">He has to
                recite four Aṣ̌əm Vohū. During the third, he has to wash (the <em>varas</em>) from
                the begin to the end. They braid it three times and wash a golden ring with
                <em>pādyāb</em>. Then they put the braided <em>varas</em> in the the ring neck
                and pit the golden ring next to the <em>barsom-čin</em>. They fill a <em>sukure</em>
                with <em>pādyāb</em> and put some hot ashes of the Ātaš Waharām in it (viz. the
                <em>sukure</em>), that is, they put ashes of the fire at its bottom so that the
                smoke of the fire does not go up and the water reaches the boiling point. The bring
                the <em>varas</em> fifty one times to the boiling water and take it out. Immediatly,
                the pour cold water on it. </ab1>
        </div>
    </div>
    <div n="3" type="chapter">
        <div n="2" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="NerWaras3.2NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers"> digar ān varas az ḥalqe bāz konand se bār b-āb-e pādyāvi bešuyand </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="NerWaras3.2NerangEnglish.a">Then they
                lose again the <em>varas</em> from the ring and wash it three times with
                <em>pādyāb</em>.</ab1>
        </div>
    </div>
    <div n="5" type="chapter">
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="NerWaras5.1NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">čahār aṣ̌əm vōhū čon piš neveštam pas digar be-ḥalqe dar-ārand dar
                hamān ḥalqe-ye zarrin andazand va hezār-o-yek bār b-āb-e pādyāvi foru barand va
                bar-āvarand va varasdān nahand</ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="NerWaras5.1NerangEnglish.a">four Aṣ̌əm
                Vohū as I have written before. Then they wind the <em>varas</em> in the ring and put
                it in the same golden ring. They bring it thousand and one times to the water and
                out of it and lay the <em>varas-dān</em>.</ab1>
        </div>
    </div>
    <div n="6" type="chapter">
        <div n="2" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="NerWaras6.2NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers"> sar-aš mohkam be-nahand va dar yazišngāh mohkam be-nahand </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="NerWaras6.2NerangEnglish.a">Then they
                lose again the <em>varas</em> from the ring and wash it three times with
                <em>pādyāb</em>.</ab1>
        </div>
    </div>
</div>