<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text xml:id="VVrS0.1" status="created">
    <!-- created, approved, updated-->
    <header>
        <creators>
            <creator>Porro</creator>
            <creator>Cantera</creator>
        </creators>
        <created>1 June 2019</created>
        <approved/>
        <updated/>
    </header>
    <div type="Stanza" sameAs="" xml:id="VVrS0.1">
        <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/nerang/videvdad_nerang" xpointer="VVrS0.1NerangTransc.a"/>
        <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/blocks/prayers/AV" xpointer="AV"/>
    </div>
    <Speaker>
        <SpeakerInfo>
            <div>zōt: vid. Y0.1.</div>
        </SpeakerInfo>
        <Commentary/>
    </Speaker>
    <Apparatus>
        <Critical/>
        <RecitationInstruction>
            <ab>ʾywk' gwptn'] 4000a, 4010, 4020, 4025; ʾdywk gwptn' 4050.</ab>
        </RecitationInstruction>
        <Commentary>
            <ab>VVrS0.1] om. Indian mss.</ab>
        </Commentary>
    </Apparatus>
    <Parallels/>
    <Ritual>
        <Nerangs id="ritualNerangs">
            <ab>VVrS0.1 (mss. 4000a, 4010, 4020, 4025, 4050, 4063, 4080):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                barsom sih ud sē tāg ud frāgām dō tāg barsom bastan ud parāhōm kardan sāzišn hamāg frāz nihādan ud ān kas kē zōtīh kāmēd kardan <em>aṣ̌əm vohū</em> ēk guftan ud dast 
                pad pādyāb kardan</ab> 
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "The <em>barsom</em> (consists of) 33 twigs and the <em>frāgām</em> are two. He should tie the <em>barsom</em>, prepare the <em>parāhōm</em> and dispose all the
                implements. The one who wishes to perform in the office of <em>zōt</em> should recite one <em>aṣ̌əm vohū</em> and wash his hands with <em>pādyāb</em>."</ab>
        </Nerangs>
        <Quotations id="ritualQuotations">
            <ab>
                <ab>NērangVVrS0.1 (Nērang ī āb) [mss. 4000 4010 4020 4025 4063], cf. WiD, Revāyat of Kāma Bohra (MU1, p. I. 577) and Revāyat of Kāmdin Šapur (var. b) (MU1, p. I. 584), on the Nērang ī Āb ud Padyāb ceremony:</ab>
                <ab class="ab_indent">ōy kē zōtīh kāmēd kardan dast pad pādyāb bē kunišn, ēk-bār
                    gōmēz ud āb bē nigerišn. hamāg gyāgīhā pēš gōmēz ud pas āb nigerišn. hamāg
                    gyāgīhā ān-ī wāzag kē ō pēš nibēsam bē gōwišn bē estišn. gōmēz ud āb bē nigerišn
                    pas abastāg bē rāyēnišn.</ab>
                <ab class="ab_indent">The one who wishes to take the office of the <em>zōt</em>, has to wash
                    his hands with <em>pādyāb</em> and gaze once at the <em>gōmēz</em> and the water. Each time, he
                    has to gaze first at the <em>gōmēz</em> and then at the water. Each time, he has to
                    recite the words that I write in the following. He has to stand and gaze at the <em>gōmēz</em>
                    and the water. Then he has to arrange the abastāg. </ab>
            </ab>

            <ab>
                <ab>Revāyat of Kāmdin Šapur (var. a) (MU1, pp. I. 579-580), on the Nērang ī Āb ud Padyāb ceremony:</ab>
                <ab class="ab_indent">(Pāz.) zōt̰. <em>ẏaϑā. ahū. vairiiō.</em> 5 guftan u. darust.
                    niṣ̌astan. u. dast. ba. ātaš. dāštan. nīrəṇg. bar. gə̄raftan. u. bar. miiąna.
                    aravīs. ādušt. bi. rāsti. tə̄cai. ādušt. nihādan. u. ṣ̌iša. bar. kināriš.
                    nihādan. caną̇n. ki. ba. ẏak. dīgar. ni. zanṇt̰. u. nīrəṇg. guną̇. kirdan. ki.
                    adušt. ki. ṣ̌ōiiṇt̰. āv. baṣ̌īša. narasat̰. u. pas. pāδiiāv. kardan. dast. ba.
                    ātaš. daštan. u. nīrəṇg. u. [†āv] nigarīdan. himājā. aval. nīrəṇg. u. pas. āv.
                    nigirīdan.</ab>
                <ab class="ab_indent">The zōt should recite five <em>yaϑā ahū vairiiō</em> and stay
                    seated erected, he should hold the hand over the fire,  take the
                        <em>nērang</em> and place it in the middle between the <em>urvīs</em>
                    and the <em>ādušt</em>, on the empty right side of the <em>ādušt</em>. The
                    vessel (of water) should be placed at his side, in such a way that they do not
                    touch each other. The <em>nērang</em> should be so that the water with which the
                        <em>ādušt</em> is cleaned, does not reach the vessel of water. Afterwards,
                    the hands should be purified and put over the fire. The <em>nērang</em> and the
                    water should be watched, always first the <em>nērang</em> and then the
                    water.</ab>
            </ab>

            <ab>
                <ab>Revāyat of Behdin Ǧāsā (MU1, p. I. 592), on the Nērang ī Āb ud Padyāb ceremony:</ab>
                <ab class="ab_indent">(Pers.) ānkas yašt ḫᵛāhad kard dar pāy istad va panǧ ahunavar
                    beḫᵛānad ḫešnumani soruš pas moḥkam benšinad con vāz gereft dast-e cap rā pādyāv
                    karde dast-e cap pādyāv šoste dast-e rāst beātaš dārad sar-e gomiz bengarad pas
                    saraš benahand degar dast beātaš barad digar sar-e āb bardārad benegarad saraš
                    benahand hamā sāǧešn benegarešn pas avarḫizad barābar-e ādušt beistad va
                    ašim vohu beguyad hamā sāǧešn ḫub benegarad</ab>
                <ab class="ab_indent">Then he who is to perform the cermony, should stand up and
                    recite five Ahunavars (with) the <em>šnūman</em> of Srōš. Then he should
                    stand firm, as when the <em>wāz</em> is taken. He should purify his left hand,
                    (i.e., wash his left hand with the pure water), hold the right hand over the
                    fire, take up the lid of the vessel of urine and look at the urine. Then the top
                    of it should be covered and he should again hold his hand over the fire and take
                    up the lid of the vessel of water and look at it and cover it again. All the
                    apparatus should be looked at. Then getting up, he should stand just opposite
                    the <em>adūšt</em>, recite one <em>aṣ̌əm vohū</em>, and look well at all the
                    apparatus. </ab>
            </ab>
        </Quotations>
    </Ritual>
    <translation>
        <include type="CAB" corresp="CABTrVVrS0.1"/>
    </translation>
</text>