<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text xml:id="VVrS0.5" status="created">
   <!-- created, approved, updated-->
   <header>
      <creators>
         <creator>Porro</creator>
         <creator>Cantera</creator>
      </creators>
      <created>1 June 2019</created>
      <approved/>
      <updated/>
   </header>
   <div type="Stanza" sameAs="" xml:id="VVrS0.5">
      <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/nerang/videvdad_nerang" xpointer="VVrS0.5NerangTransc.a"/>
      <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/blocks/prayers/YAV" xpointer="YAV"/>
      <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/blocks/prayers/YAV" xpointer="YAV"/>
   </div>
   <Speaker>
      <SpeakerInfo>
         <div>zōt: vid. Y0.5.</div>
      </SpeakerInfo>
      <Commentary/>
   </Speaker>
   <Apparatus>
      <Critical/>
      <Commentary>
         <ab>VVrS0.5] Indian mss. om.</ab>
      </Commentary>
   </Apparatus>
   <Parallels/>
   <Ritual>
      <Nerangs id="ritualNerangs">
         <ab>VVrS0.5 (Nērang ī āb) (mss. 4000a, 4010, 4020, 4025, 4063):</ab>
         <ab class="ab_indent">            
            <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō</em> dō andar rāh ēd bē gōwišn ō ī pas barsom šawēd u-š tarsāgīhā bē ēstišn</ab> 
         <ab class="ab_indent">
            "He has to recite two <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō</em> on the way. He goes past the <em>barsom</em> and has to stand respctfully."</ab>
      </Nerangs>
      <Quotations id="ritualQuotations">
         <ab><ab>NērangVVrS0.5 (Nērang ī āb) [mss. 4000 4010 4020 4025 4063], cf. WiD, Revāyat of Kāma Bohra (MU1, p. I. 577) and Revāyat of Kāmdin Šapur (var. b) (MU1, p. I. 584), on the Nērang ī Āb ud Padyāb ceremony:</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">"(Pahl.) yadāhuwēryō dō andar rāh ēd bē gōbišn ō ī pas barsom šawet u-š tarsagāhīh bē estišn ud sidīgar bār sāzišn gōmēz āb xūb bē nigerišn"</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">"He (the <em>zōt</em>) has to recite two <em>yaϑā ahī vairiiō</em> on his way. He has to go towards the <em>barsom</em> and place his feet on it reverentially."</ab></ab>
         
         <ab><ab>Revāyat of Behdin Ǧāsā (MU1, p. I. 592-93), cf. Revāyat of Kāmdin Šapur (var. a) (MU1, pp. I. 580-81), on the Nērang ī Āb ud Padyāb ceremony:</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">"(Pers.) cenānke dar yašt sāḫtan <em>ẏaϑā ahū vairiiō.</em> do <em>ẏasnəmcā.</em> tā sar <em>ahurahe mazdā̊ raē.</em> (Pahl.) OD pas dur āmadan 
               (AvPersTr.) ašim vohu (Pers.) ānkas ke yašt ḫᵛāhand kardan (AvPersTr) is̱ā ahu vairiyo andar rāh goftan va be <em>š́iiaoϑə̄naną̇m.</em> bālāy-e (†pāy-ī) rāst andar zudgāh nahādan bar yazešn gāh nešastan 
               va beyazdān va amšāsfandān setāyeš bordan ve beyāri miṭalbidan va ānkas ke rās̱vi ast zud dast ḫošk kardan va soruš darun nahādan va panǧ (AvPersTr.) is̱ā ahu vairiyo ḫᵛāndan 
               va esm va buy se tā nahādan dast ḫošk kardan ānkas ke yazešn ḫᵛāhad kardan dast beāb pādyāvi šostan hamā sāǧešn bekardan va rās̱vi moḥkam nešastan dast be ātas bordan 
               hamā ǧā ke vāǧ ke piš neveštam va begoftan beistādan pas negaridan pas vāǧ-e digar begoftan"</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">"The person who has prepared de ritual (performed the Paragna), (at the) two <em>yaϑā ahū vairiiō</em> (should recite) <em>yasnəmcā</em> until the endo of <em>ahurahe mazdā̊ raē.</em> until (the end).
               Afterwards he should go away (reciting) <em>aṣ̌əm vohū</em>. The one who wants to perform the ceremony has to recite two <em>yaϑā ahū vairiiō</em> on his way and at <em>š́iiaōϑənanąm</em> put his right foot on the 
               <em>zōtgāh</em> and sit reverentially. He should praise the Yazdan and the Aməṣ̌a Spəṇta and call them to his assistance. That person who is the <em>rāspīg</em> should soon make his hands dry, put the Srōš Drōn and utter 
               five <em>yaϑā ahū vairiiō</em> and arrange thre <em>esm</em> and <em>boy</em> and make his hands dry. The person who is to perform the Yasna should wash his hands with the <em>padyāb</em>, 
               and look at all the apparatus. The <em>rāspīg</em> should sit straight, carry his hands to the fire. At all places, the words I indicate below should be uttered and they should stay and look and then recite the remaining words."
            </ab></ab>
      </Quotations>
     
      <Commentary id="ritualCommentary">
         <ab class="ab_indent">For a description of the actions of the <em>rāspīg</em>, see Y0.5.</ab>
      </Commentary>
   </Ritual>
   <translation>
      <include type="CAB" corresp="CABTrVVrS0.5"/>
   </translation>
</text>