<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text xml:id="VVrS0.4" status="created">  <!-- created, approved, updated--> <header>
        <creators>
            <creator>Porro</creator>
            <creator>Cantera</creator>
        </creators>
    <created>1 June 2019</created>
    <approved/>
    <updated/>
    </header>
    <div type="Stanza" sameAs="" xml:id="VVrS0.4">
         <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/nerang/videvdad_nerang" xpointer="VVrS0.4NerangTransc.a"/>
         <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/blocks/prayers/AV" xpointer="AV1"/>
         <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/blocks/prayers/AV" xpointer="AV"/>
         <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/blocks/prayers/AV" xpointer="AV"/>
    </div>
    <Speaker>
        <SpeakerInfo>
            <div>zōt: vid. VVrS0.3 wāz gīrišnīh.</div>
        </SpeakerInfo>
    </Speaker>
    <Commentary/>
    <Apparatus>
        <Critical/>
        <Commentary>            
            <ab>VVrS0.4] Indian mss. om.</ab>
        </Commentary>
    </Apparatus>
    <Parallels/>
    <Ritual>
        <Quotations id="ritualQuotations">
            <ab><ab>Revāyat of Kāmdin Šapur (var. a) (MU1, p. I. 580), cf. Revāyat of Kāmdin Šapur (var. b.) (MU1, p. I. 584), on the Nērang ī Āb ud Padyāb ceremony:</ab>
                <ab class="ab_indent">(Pāz.) u. zōt̰. gāh. ābarətārą̇n. ṣ̌udan. u. rāspī. vāj. guftan. pa. gāhi. asnauuārą̇n. ṣ̌ūdan. u. drust. naṣ̌istan. u. vāj. gə̄riftan. īāni. <em>xṣ̌naoϑra ahurahe mazdā̊ aṣ̌əm vōhū</em> 
                    ẏak. u. dast. ātaš. dāštan. u. xušak. kardan. u. darə. nīrəṇg. bar. gə̄rə̄ftan. u. zōt̰. <em>aṣ̌əm vōhū</em> guftan. u. nīrəṇg. nigarδan. <em>vōhū</em> āv. nigarīδan. <em>vaištəm</em> tā. sar. guftan. āt̰.ẏašt. šastan. si 
                    <em>aṣ̌əm vōhū</em> barīn. dastūr. x́ą̇nadan. u. nigarīdan. ādušt. šustan.</ab>
                <ab class="ab_indent">"The <em>zōt</em> should go to the place of the <em>ābarətār</em> and the <em>rāspīg</em> should utter the <em>wāz</em> and go to the place of the <em>asnuuār</em> and seat erected.
                    And (the <em>zōt</em>) should take the <em>wāz</em> saying <em>xṣ̌naoϑra ahurahe mazdā̊ aṣ̌əm vōhū</em> once and he should the hands (over) the fire and make them dry. And he should up the top (of the vessel)
                    of the <em>nērang</em> and the <em>zōt</em> should say the <em>aṣ̌əm vōhū</em> and look at the <em>nērang</em> at <em>vōhū</em> and look at the water at <em>vaištəm</em> and say until the end (while) cleaning the <em>ādušt</em>.
                    He should read three <em>aṣ̌əm vōhū</em> this way</ab> and looking and cleaning the <em>ādušt</em>."</ab>
            
            <ab><ab>Revāyat of Behdin Ǧāsā (MU1, p. I. 592), on the Nērang ī Āb ud Padyāb ceremony:</ab>
                <ab class="ab_indent">pas az cap-e dast-e ādušt šodan va dast durtar kardan āheste dast bordan miyān-e ādušt tar kardan cenānke nami qaṭre-ye āb bar mašrabe-ye gomiz 
                    narizand miyān-e ādušt šostan pas ānkas ke barsam baste ast vāǧ begoftan dast az barsam ǧodā kardan ḫod rā az arvis ǧodā kardan ḫod rā az arvis bāyad ke ǧodā šode bāšad </ab>
                <ab class="ab_indent">"Then he should go to the left side of the <em>ādušt</em>, should hold his hand aloof, carry it over slowly, and throw water on the surface of <em>ādušt</em>, in such a way that not a single drop of water may fall over the vessel of urine. 
                    He should then wash the surface of the <em>ādušt</em>. Then the person who has tied the <em>barsom</em> should finish off the <em>wāz</em>, separate his hands from the <em>barsom</em>, and come out of the <em>urvis</em>."</ab></ab>
        </Quotations>
    </Ritual>
    <translation>
        <include type="CAB" corresp="CABTrVVrS0.4"/>
    </translation>
</text>