<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text xml:id="VVrS87.8" status="created">
   <!-- created, approved, updated-->
   <header>
      <creators>
         <creator>Porro</creator>
         <creator>Cantera</creator>
      </creators>
      <created>1 June 2019</created>
   </header>
   <div type="Stanza" sameAs="" xml:id="VVrS87.8">
      <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/static/Videvdad_Static" xpointer="VrS39.4"/>
   </div>
   <Apparatus>
      <Critical/>
      <Commentary/>
   </Apparatus>
   <Parallels/>
   <Ritual>
      <Nerangs id="ritualNerangs">
         <ab>VVrS87.8 (mss. 4020, 4025, 4040, 4050, 4055, 4060, 4161, 4162):</ab>
         <ab class="ab_indent">
            <em>daitikanąmcā aidiiūnąm hiiat̰ urunō yazamaidē</em> pad <em>aṣ̌āunąm āat̰ urunō yazamaidē</em> rāspīg ō ī dast ī hōy ī zōt šawišn hāwan abar griftan pad <em>kudō.zātanąmcīt̰</em> 
            zōt pārag ī zōhr andar hāwan kunišn <em>narąmcā nāirinąmcā</em> abarhāwan abar hāwan zanišn <em>yaēšąm vahehīš daēnā̊ vanaiṇtī vā</em> rāspīg hāwan abar urwēs nihišn
            <em>və̄ṇghən vā</em> abar wars-dān nihišn <em>vaōnarə̄</em> andarag ī ādišt ud urwēs abar zamīg nihišn <em>vā</em> abar ādišt nihišn zōhr abāg gyāg kunišn zōt <em>vaṇtąm</em>. ...</ab> 
         <ab class="ab_indent">
            "(The zōt should recite) <em>daitikanąmcā aidiiūnąm hiiat̰ urunō yazamaidē</em> and at <em>aṣ̌āunąm āat̰ urunō yazamaidē</em>, the <em>rāspīg</em> has to go to the left 
            hand of the <em>zōt</em> and to take the <em>hāwan</em>. At <em>kudō.zātanąmcīt̰</em>, the <em>zōt</em> has to pour a drop of <em>zōhr</em> into the <em>hāwan</em>. 
            At <em>narąmcā nāirinąmcā</em>, he has to hit the <em>hāwan</em> with the <em>abarhāwan</em>. At <em>yaēšąm vahehīš daēnā̊ vanaiṇtī vā</em>, the rāspīg has to put 
            the <em>hāwan</em> on the <em>urwēs</em>. At <em>və̄ṇghən vā</em>, he has to put it ovedr the <em>wars-dān</em>. At <em>vaōnarə̄</em>, he has to touch with it the
            earth in the <em>andarag</em> between the <em>ādušt</em> and the <em>urwēs</em>. At <em>vā</em>, he has to touch the <em>ādišt</em> with it and give back the 
            <em>zōhr</em> to its place (and continue with) <em>vaṇtąm</em>. ..."</ab>
      </Nerangs>
   </Ritual>
   <translation>
      <include type="CAB" corresp="CABTrVVrS87.8"/>
   </translation>
</text>