<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div type="ceremony" n="HomastP">
    <header>
        <creators>
            <creator>Cantera</creator>
        </creators>
        <created>11 February 2020</created>
        <updated>14 December 2020</updated>
        <updated/>
    </header>

    <div n="2" type="chapter">
        <div n="3" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="HomastP2.3NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">cašm andar esm wa buy konišn <em>imąm. aēsmanąsca. baōδīmca.</em> cašm andar ātaxš
                konišn <em>tauua āθrō...</em></ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="HomastP2.3NerangEnglish.a">He should gaze
                at the <em>esm</em> and <em>buy</em> and (recite) <em>imąm. aēsmanąsca. baōδīmca.
                </em>. He should gaze at the fire and (recite) <em>tauua. āθrō. ...</em></ab1>
        </div>
        <div n="13" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="HomastP2.13NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">sukure wa hum *pālā (bālā) ō ruy-e sang-e urwis nahādan</ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="HomastP2.13NerangEnglish.a" xml:lang="Pers">He has to put the <em>sukure</em> and the <em>hum-pālā</em> on the stone of the
                    <em>urwis</em>.</ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="HomastP2.13NerangTransc.b" xml:lang="Pers">dast-e rāst bordan wa daste-ye hāwan dar hāwan zadan hāwan škāftan wa bar dāštan
                āwardan-e ō dast-e rāst-e zud bar ruy-e sang-e urwis sar nagān kardan daste durtar
                ruy-e sang-urwis nahādan </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="HomastP2.13NerangEnglish.b" xml:lang="Pers">He has to near the right hand and hit the pestle against the <em>hāwan</em>. He has
                to strike the <em>hāwan</em> and raise it and bring it to the right hand of the
                    <em>zud</em>. He has to put it on the stone of the <em>urwis</em> and put the
                pestle as well on the stone of the <em>urwis</em>, but further.</ab1>
        </div>
        <div n="14" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="HomastP2.14NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">neke-ye ruz wa māh har ruz ke bāšad az urmazd tā anirān neke-ye ān ruz beguyand har
                māh ke bāšad neke-ye ān māh begyuand tā sar </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="HomastP2.14NerangEnglish.a" xml:lang="Pers">the day and the month. He has to say the corresponding day, from Urzmazd to Anirān.
                He has to say the corresponding month until the end</ab1>
        </div>
    </div>

    <div n="3" type="chapter">
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="HomastP3.1NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">hāwan-e rāst be zanišn</ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="HomastP3.1NerangEnglish.a">He should turn
                the <em>hāwan</em> right side.</ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="HomastP3.1NerangTransc.b" xml:lang="Pers">hum wa urwarān andar hāwan nahādan</ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="HomastP3.1NerangEnglish.b">He should put
                the <em>hum</em> and the <em>urwarān</em> into the <em>hāwan</em>.</ab1>
        </div>
        <div n="6" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="HomastP3.6NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">esm wa buy yektā ke nahāde ba ruy-e ātaš nahišn</ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="HomastP3.6NerangEnglish.a">He should put a
                piece of <em>esm</em> and <em>buy</em> on the fire</ab1>

        </div>
    </div>
    <div n="4" type="chapter">
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.b" source="K7c" xml:id="HomastP4.1NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers"><em>aētaṯ.dəm vīspanąm</em> daste-ye hāwan az ruy-e sang-e urwis be-dast
                gereftan </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.b" source="K7c" xml:id="HomastP4.1NerangEnglish.a">At
                    <em>aētaṯ.dəm vīspanąm</em> he should take the pestle from the stone of the
                    <em>urwis</em>with the hand.</ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.c" source="K7c" xml:id="HomastP4.1NerangTransc.b" xml:lang="Pers">čašm wa ruy andar wāxtar afšānidan <em>snaϑāi. aŋhrahe. mainiiə̄uš. druuatō. </em>
                yaʾni zanišn b-ahreman druwand <em>snaθāi aešmahe xruuī.draōš</em> čašm wa ruy andar
                awāxtar afšānidan yaʾni zanišn be-hišm xore dir zaxš diw dādan <em>snaθāi
                    mazaniianąm daēuuanąm</em> čašm wa ruy andar awāxtar afšānidan yaʾni zanišn be
                mazanegān diwān dãdan <em> snaθāi vīspanąm daēuuanąm</em> čašm wa ruy andar awāxtar
                afšānidan yaʾni zanišn bā hamān diwān dādan <em> varənīnąmca druuatąm </em> daste az
                ruy-e sang-urwis bar dāštan se bār bar se sān hāwan zadan yekbār az ānsu ke xoršid
                bar-āyad yeki az ānsuy-e nimruz yeki az ānsuy ke xoršid foru sšawad pas daste bar
                dast negāh dāštan</ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.c" source="K7c" xml:id="HomastP4.1NerangEnglish.b" xml:lang="Pers">At <em>snaϑāi. aŋhrahe. mainiiə̄uš. druuatō. </em> he has to turn the eyes and the
                face towards the west, that means, he has to hit the lying Ahreman. At <em>snaθāi
                    aešmahe xruuī.draōš</em> he has to turn the eyes and the face towards the west,
                that means, he has to hit the <em>diw</em><em>hišm</em> .. .(?). At <em>snaθāi
                    mazaniianąm daēuuanąm</em> he has to turn the eyes and the face towards the
                west, that means, he has to hit the <em>diw mazanegān</em>. At <em> snaθāi vīspanąm
                    daēuuanąm</em> he has to turn the eyes and the face towards the west, that
                means, he has to hit all the <em>diw</em>. At <em> varənīnąmca druuatąm </em> he has
                to raise the pestle from the stone of the <em>urwis</em> and to strike the
                    <em>hāwan</em> three times in three different ways: once in the direction in
                which the sun rises; once, in the south direction and once in the direction in which
                the sun goes down.Afterwards, he gazes at the pestle in the hand. </ab1>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="HomastP4.2NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">daste čahār angušt bālā bordan yaʾni bozorg dāram ormazd riyōmand xorremand rā </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="HomastP4.2NerangEnglish.a" xml:lang="Pers">He has to raise the pestle four fingers, that is, I make great Urzmazd, the rich
                and glorious.</ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.b" source="K7c" xml:id="HomastP4.2NerangTransc.b" xml:lang="Pers">čahār angušt digar daste bālā bordan yaʾni bozorg dāram amešāsfandān rā </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.b" source="K7c" xml:id="HomastP4.2NerangEnglish.b" xml:lang="Pers">He has to raise the pestle another four fingers, that is, I make great the
                Amešāsfandān.</ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.c" source="K7c" xml:id="HomastP4.1NerangTransc.c" xml:lang="Pers">čahār angušt digar daste bālātar bar dãštan yaʾni bozorg dāram tštar setar
                urmazd-dād </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.c" source="K7c" xml:id="HomastP4.2NerangEnglish.d" xml:lang="Pers">He has to raise the pestle another four fingers, that is, I make great the star
                Tištar, created by Urmazd.</ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.d" source="K7c" xml:id="HomastP4.1NerangTransc.d" xml:lang="Pers">daste-ye hāwand čahār angušt digar bālātar dāštan yaʾni bozorg dāram amešāsfandān
                hamā-ye minuān wa hamā-ye ašuān pas daste forud āwardan se bār ruy-e hāwan
                gardānidan mšl (?) ke xoršid mi-gardad </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.d" source="K7c" xml:id="HomastP4.2NerangEnglish.d" xml:lang="Pers">He has to raise the pestle another four fingers, that is, I make great the
                Amešāsfandān, all the immaterial and the material ones. Afterwards, he has to put
                down the pestleand turn it three tiomes in the <em>hāwan</em> in the direction in
                which the sun goes.</ab1>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="HomastP4.3NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">pas čahār <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō </em> xāndan <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō </em> awwal xāndan
                tā <em>š́iiaoθananąm</em> yekbār hum [wa] urwarān kuftan <em>aŋhə̄uš</em> yekbār
                kuftan <em>mazdā̊ </em> yekbār kuftan <em>xšaθrəmca ahurāi ā. yim. darəɤubiiō
                    vāstārəm</em> xāndan čahār angušt daste az hāwan ǧodā kardan pas <em>yaθā ahū
                    vairiiō </em> dowwom be <em>š́iiaoθnanąm</em> do bār kuftan <em>aŋhə̄uš</em> do
                bār kuftan <em>mazdā</em> do bār kuftan <en>xšaθrəmcā </en> tā sar xāndan <em>yaθā
                    ahū vairiiō</em> seiwom be <em>š́iiaoθnanąm </em> se bār kuftan be <em>aŋhə̄uš
                </em> se bār kuftan wa se bār kuftan <em>xšaθrəmcā</em> tā sar xāndan <em>yaθā ahū
                    vairiiō</em> čahārom tā <em>vāstārəm</em> *hum (hāwan) kuftan wa hāwan škāftan </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="HomastP4.3NerangEnglish.a" xml:lang="Pers">Afterwards, he has to recite four <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō </em>. He has to recite the
                first <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō </em> until <em>š́iiaoθananąm</em> and pound once the
                    <em>hum</em> and the <em>urwarām</em>; at <em>aŋhə̄uš </em> he has to pound once; at <em>mazdā̊ </em> he has to pound once and then to recite <em>xšaθrəmca ahurāi ā. yim. darəɤubiiō
                vāstārəm</em>. He has to move the pestle four fingers off from the mortar. Then, (he
            has to recite ) the second <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō </em>. At <em>š́iiaoθananąm</em>, he has to pound two times; at <em>aŋhə̄uš </em>, he has to pound two times; at <em>mazdā̊ </em>,
                he has to pound two times and then to recite until the end. In the third <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō </em>, at <em>š́iiaoθananąm</em>, he has to pound three times; at <em>aŋhə̄uš </em>, he has to pound three times; at <em>mazdā̊ </em> he has to pound three times and then to recite it until the end. During the fourth <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō </em> until <em>vāstārəm</em>, he has to pound the <em>hum</em> and strike the mortar.</ab1>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="HomastP4.4NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">
                in wačast čahār bār xāndan hum wa urwarān andar hāwan kuftan</ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="HomastP4.4NerangEnglish.a" xml:lang="Pers">He has to recite this stanza four times and to pound the <em>hum</em> and the
                    <em>urwarān</em> in the <em>hāwan</em>.</ab1>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="MU1" xml:id="HomastP4.5NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">in wacašt čahār bār xāndan har yek bār hum wa urwarām kuftan hāwan škāftan</ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="MU1" xml:id="HomastP4.4NerangEnglish.a" xml:lang="Pers">He has to recite this stanza four times and to pound the <em>hum</em> and the
                    <em>urwarān</em> and hit the <em>hāwan</em>.</ab1>
        </div>
        <div n="6" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="MU1" xml:id="HomastP4.6NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">se bār xāndan har yek <em>aṣ̌əm vohū</em> yek bār zur andar hāwan rixtan</ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="MU1" xml:id="HomastP4.6NerangEnglish.a" xml:lang="Pers">He has to recite it three times and at each <em>aṣ̌əm vohū</em> he has to pour
                    <em>zur</em> in the <em>hāwan</em>.</ab1>
        </div>
        <div n="8" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="MU1" xml:id="HomastP4.8NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers"><em>aθā</em>wa daste-ye hāwan čonke xoršid gardad wa se bār gardeš <em>zī.nə̄. humāiiō. tarā̊ŋhnəm.</em></ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="MU1" xml:id="HomastP4.8NerangEnglish.a" xml:lang="Pers">At <em>aθā</em> he has to turn the pestle three times (around the <em>hāwan</em> in the direction
                in which the sun rotates (and to continue with) <em>zī.nə̄. humāiiō. tarā̊ŋhnəm.</em>.</ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.b" source="MU1" xml:id="HomastP4.8NerangTransc.b" xml:lang="Pers">
                hum wa urwarān kufte andar sar-e daste-ye hāwan nahādan wa bordan be-suy-e čab-e
                barsom nahādan </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.b" source="MU1" xml:id="HomastP4.8NerangEnglish.b" xml:lang="Pers">He has to put the <em>hum</em> and <em>urwarān</em> that have been pounded in the
                end of the pestle and bring it and put it in the left side of the
                <em>barsom</em>.</ab1>
        </div>
        <div n="9" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="MU1" xml:id="HomastP4.9NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers"><em>yaθā ahū vairiiō</em> čahār bār xāndan wa hum wa urwarān kuftan b-āb-e zur
                andar kardan wa hum pyāle kardan be <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō</em> har čahār <em>yaθā ahū
                    vairiiō</em> hamčenin bāyad kard</ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="MU1" xml:id="HomastP4.9NerangEnglish.a" xml:lang="Pers">He has to recite the Ahuna Vairiia four times and pound the <em>hum</em> and the
                    <em> urwarān</em> und put them into the <em>zur</em>-water and in the
                    <em>hum</em>-cup (<em>pyāle</em>). At any of the four Ahuna Vairiia he has to
                repeat it in the same way.</ab1>
        </div>
        <div n="10" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="MU1" xml:id="HomastP4.10NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers"><em>sraotā.mōi. mərəždātā.mōi.</em> hum wa urwarān *āšordan</ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="MU1" xml:id="HomastP4.10NerangEnglish.a" xml:lang="Pers">At <em>sraotā.mōi. mərəždātā.mōi.</em> he has to press the
                    <em>hum</em> and the <em> urwarān</em>
            </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.b" source="MU1" xml:id="HomastP4.10NerangTransc.b" xml:lang="Pers">har se bār xāndan pas dast andar hāwan nahādan ān sukure-e farāhum be-ruy-e hāwan-e
                daste nahādan wa ān sukure ke šeib-e hum pyāle nahāde ast ke-š farāhum andar-ast
                be-dast-e rāst bar dāštan yek qaṯre be-sukure ruy-e hāwan kardan bāqi andar
                farāhum-dān kardan digar yek qaṯre be sukure-ye pas farāhum-dān kardan </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.b" source="MU1" xml:id="HomastP4.10NerangEnglish.b" xml:lang="Pers">He has to recite this stanza three times. Then he has to put the
                hand in the <em>hāwan</em>. The goblet (<em>sukure</em>) for the <em>hum</em> has to
                be put next to the pestle. He has to raise  with the right hand the bowl (<em>sukure</em>) that is put below the <em>hum</em>-filter
                (<em>pyāle</em>)  and in which the <em>farāhum</em> . He has to pour a drop into the bowl next to the <em>hāwan</em> and a bit into the <em>farāhum-dān</em> and another drop into the
                bowl (<em>sukure</em>) that is behind the <em>farāhum-dān</em>.</ab1>
        </div>
        <div n="13" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="MU1" xml:id="HomastP4.13NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">pas ān hum wa urwarān kufte andar guše-ye sang-e urwis nahādan waras andar hum pyāle gozāštan pas dast be-pādyāb bordan ān hum wa ān urwarām ke be-dast-e čab
                nahāde ast āwardan piš-e hum pyāle nahādan pas dast be-pādyāb bordan ān zur ke
                be-dast-e čab nahāde ast āwardan piš-e hum pyāle nahādan ān zur ke be-dast-e čab
                nahāde ast āwardan piš-e hum pyāle nahādan pas qatre-ye šir andar ǧām-dān rixtan az
                ān rixtan az ān naguftim inǧā imąmcā. gąm. jīuuiiąm. čon šir nabud pas be-dast-e čab
                barsom ke andar māhruy nahāde gereftan</ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="MU1" xml:id="HomastP4.13NerangEnglish.a" xml:lang="Pers">Afterwards, he has to put the <em>hum</em> and <em>urwarān</em> that
                have been pressed in one corner of the stone of the <em>urwis</em> . He has to put
                the <em>waras</em> in the <em>hum</em>-filter. He has to wash his hands with
                    <em>padyāb</em> and bring the <em>hum</em> and <em>urwarān</em> that have been
                put on the left hand before the <em>hum</em>-filter and put (them
                there). Then, he has to wash his hand with <em>padyāb</em> and bring the
                    <em>zur</em> that have been put on the left hand before the <em>hum</em>-filter and put (it there). Then, he has to pour one drop of milk into
                the <em>ǧām-dān</em>: because of the pouring (into the <em>ǧām-dān</em>, but not the
                    <em>hum-dān</em>) I omitted <em> imąmcā. gąm. jīuuiiąm.</em>, because there was
                no milk. Then, he has to take with the left hand the <em>barsom</em> that was
                located on the <em>māhruy</em>. </ab1>
        </div>
    </div>
    <div n="5" type="chapter">
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="MU1" xml:id="HomastP5.1NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">andar dast-e čab ādišt šodan ādišt šostan</ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="MU1" xml:id="HomastP5.1NerangEnglish.a" xml:lang="Pers">He has to go to the left sid of the <em>ādišt</em> and wash it.</ab1>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="MU1" xml:id="HomastP5.2NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers"><em>aṣ̌əm vohū</em> 3 xāndan ādišt šostan az čab tā rāst wa miyān-e ādišt
                šostan </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="MU1" xml:id="HomastP5.2NerangEnglish.a" xml:lang="Pers">He recites three times the Aṣ̌əm Vohū and has to clean the <em>ādišt</em>. He has
                to clean it from the left to the right and the middle of the <em>ādišt</em>.</ab1>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="MU1" xml:id="HomastP5.3NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">pas ānke dast-e u bar barsom dārad <em>yaθā. ahū. vairiiō. </em> dō xāndan</ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="MU1" xml:id="HomastP5.3NerangEnglish.a" xml:lang="Pers">Then, the one who holds his hand on the <em>barsom</em> has top recite two Ahuna
                Vairiia. </ab1>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="MU1" xml:id="HomastP5.4NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">pas dast az barsom bar dāštan az pas sang-e urwis be-dar āmadan</ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="MU1" xml:id="HomastP5.4NerangEnglish.a" xml:lang="Pers">Then, he has to take his hand away from the <em>barsom</em> and then to come inside
                from the stone of the <em>urwis</em>. </ab1>
        </div>
    </div>
</div>