<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text xml:id="Y0.2" status="created">
    <!-- created, approved, updated-->
    <header>
        <creators>
            <creator>Porro</creator>
            <creator>Cantera</creator>
        </creators>
        <created>1 June 2019</created>
        <approved/>
        <updated/>
    </header>
    <div type="Stanza" sameAs="" xml:id="Y0.2">
        <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/nerang/yasna_nerang" xpointer="Y0.2NerangTransc.a"/>
        <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/blocks/prayers/AV" xpointer="AV" times="3"/>
    </div>
    <Speaker>
        <SpeakerInfo>
            <div>zōt: vid. Y0.1.</div>
        </SpeakerInfo>
        <Commentary/>
    </Speaker>
    <Apparatus>
        <Critical/>
        <RecitationInstruction>
            <ab>III gwptn'] 5, 40, 400, 410; III 15.</ab>
        </RecitationInstruction>
        <Commentary/>
    </Apparatus>
    <Parallels/>
    <Ritual>
        <Nerangs id="ritualNerangs">
            <ab>Y0.2 Var.a (mss.5, 40, 400, 410, 2007, 2010, 2038, 2040, 2101, 2104a, 2106, 2109, 4000a, 4020, 4025, 4050, 4056a):</ab>  
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                ō ī gāh ī ātrawaxšān šudan war ī ō ī ātaxšgāh ud barsom kardan <em>aṣ̌əm vōhū</em> sē guftan</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                He should go to the place of the <em>ātrawaxš</em> and recite three <em>aṣ̌əm vōhū</em> facing the <em>ātaxšgāh</em> and the <em>barsom</em>.</ab> 
            <ab>Y0.2 Var.b (ms.82) </ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                ō ī gāh ī ātrawaxš šawēd war ō ī ātaxšgāh ud barsom kardan <em>xšnaōϑra. ahurahe. mazdā̊.</em>: <em>aṣ̌əm vohū</em> ēk 
                <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō</em> haft guftan <em>xšnaōϑra ahurahe mazdā̊.</em>: <em>aṣ̌əm vohū</em> ēk <em>nəmasə.tē ātarš mazdā̊ ahurahe hudā̊ mazišta yazata xšnaōϑra ahurahe mazdā̊</em> :
                <em>aṣ̌əm vohū</em> sē guftan</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                He goes to the place of the <em>ātrawaxš</em>, facing the <em>ātaxšgāh</em> and the <em>barsom</em> and recite <em>xšnaōϑra ahurahe mazdā̊</em> 
                and one <em>aṣ̌əm vohū</em>, seven <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō</em>, further <em>xšnaōϑra ahurahe mazdā̊</em> and one <em>aṣ̌əm vohū</em>, 
                then <em>nəmasə.tē ātarš mazdā̊ ahurahe hudā̊ mazišta yazata xšnaōϑra ahurahe mazdā̊</em> and three <em>aṣ̌əm vohū</em>. </ab>
        </Nerangs>
        <Quotations id="ritualQuotations">
            <ab>N28.30-1 <bibl>Kotwal and Kreyenbroek, 2003</bibl>, pp. 86-87:</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">pad ān sē <em>aṣ̌əm vohū</em> gōspand ān gyāg abāyēd ka andar
                nayēd ā be nē nayišn zōt ka andar †ō yazišn āyēd az kust ī dašn pad gāh ī ātarwaxšān be
                estišn u-š war ō ātaxš ud barsom rōn kunišn <em>aṣ̌əm vohū</em> sē </ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">"During those three Aṣ̌əm Vohū the sacrificial animal must be
                there; if he leads it, he should not lead it. When the <em>zōt</em> goes to the <em>yazišn</em>, he has to stay at the right side, at the place of the <em>ātrawaxš</em>, facing the
                fire and the <em>barsom</em> and (he has to recite) three Aṣ̌əm Vohū. </ab>
        </Quotations>
    </Ritual>
    <translation>
        <include type="CAB" corresp="CABTrY0.2"/>
        <include type="W" corresp="WTrY0.1b"/>
        <include type="K" corresp="KTrY0.1"/>
        <include type="D" corresp="DTrY0.1b"/>
    </translation>
</text>