<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text xml:id="Y0.3" status="created">
    <!-- created, approved, updated-->
    <header>
        <creators>
            <creator>Porro</creator>
            <creator>Cantera</creator>
        </creators>
        <created>1 June 2019</created>
        <approved/>
        <updated/>
    </header>
    <div type="Stanza" sameAs="" xml:id="Y0.3">
        <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/blocks/Frauuarane_BP" xpointer="Frauuarane_BP1"/>
    </div>
    <Speaker>
        <SpeakerInfo>
            <div>zōt: Anklesaria.</div>
        </SpeakerInfo>
        <Commentary/>
    </Speaker>
    <Apparatus>
        <Critical/>
        <Commentary>
            <ab>
                <em>yaϑā. ahū. vairiiō. zaōtā.</em>...<em>mraōtū. yaϑā. ahū. vairiiō. yō.
                    zaōtā.</em>... <em>mraōtū</em>] Indian mss. only <em>yaϑā. ahū. vairiiō. yō.
                    zaōtā.</em>...<em>mraōtū</em>
            </ab>
        </Commentary>
    </Apparatus>
    <Parallels/>
    <Ritual>
        <Nerangs id="ritualNerangs">
            <ab>Y0.3 šnūman (ms.5, 15, 40, 82, 300, 355, 360, 370, 400, 410, 2007, 2010, 2038, 2040,
                2065, 2101, 2103, 2104a, 2106, 4000a, 4010, 4020, 4025, 4050, 4055, 4056a, 4063,
                4080, 4161): </ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent"> pad mān ī ātaxšān <em>āθrō ahurahe mazdå tauua ātarš puϑra
                    ahurahe mazdå xšnaōϑra y v x f</em> pad mān ī wehān <em>tauua ātarš puϑra
                    ahurahe mazdå xšnaōϑra y v x f </em></ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent"> "In the fire temple, (he should recite): <em>āθrō ahurahe mazdå
                    tauua ātarš puϑra ahurahe mazdå xšnaōϑra y v x f</em> In the house of the
                believers, (he should recite): <em>tauua ātarš puϑra ahurahe mazdå xšnaōϑra y v x
                    f</em>" </ab>

            <ab>Y0.3 wāz gīrišnīh (ms. 40, 82, 300, 355, 360, 370, 400, 410, 2007, 2010, 2030, 2038,
                2040, 2101, 2103, 2104a, 2106, 4000a, 4010, 4020, 4025, 4050, 4055, 4056a, 4063,
                4080, 4161):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent"> agar ham zōt xwēštan yašt sāxtag bēd <em>yaϑā ahū vairiiō zaotā
                    frā.mē mrūtē aϑā ratuš aṣ̌āt̰cīt̰ haca frā aṣ̌auua vīδuuå mraōtū</em> agar
                rāspīg yašt sāxtag bēd zōt <em>yaϑā ahū vairiiō yō zaotā frā.mē mrūtē</em> rāspīg
                    <em>aϑā ratuš haca frā aṣ̌auua vīδuuå mraōtū</em></ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent"> "When the <em>zōt</em> himself has prepared the <em>yašt</em>,
                (then he should recite:) <em>yaϑā ahū vairiiō zaotā frā.mē mrūtē aϑā ratuš
                    aṣ̌āt̰cīt̰ haca frā aṣ̌auua vīδuuå mraōtū</em> When the <em>rāspīg</em> has
                prepared the <em>yašt</em>, (then) the <em>zōt</em> (should recite): <em>yaϑā ahū
                    vairiiō yō zaotā frā.mē mrūtē</em>; the <em>rāspīg</em> (should answer): <em>aϑā
                    ratuš haca frā aṣ̌auua vīδuuå mraōtū</em>." </ab>
        </Nerangs>
        <Quotations id="ritualQuotations">
            <ab>N28.31b-32 <bibl>Kotwal and Kreyenbroek, 2003</bibl>, pp. 86-87:</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">N28.31b-2</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                <em>frauuarānē mazdaiiasnō</em> gāh ān ī bawēd pad mān ī wehān <em>tauua ātarš puϑra
                    ahurahe mazdā̊ xšnaōϑra</em> ast kē ēdōn gōwēd ay hamē <em>āϑrō ahurahe mazdā̊
                    puϑra tauua ātarš puϑra ahurahe mazdā̊ xšnaōϑra</em> ka az ān kē barsom bandēd
                parāhōm kard wāz dārēd wāz az ōy gīrišn ka nē [[ēn wāzag-ē]] ka az xwēš gīrēd weh-iz
                ast āzādmard guft hād har yazišn-ē ān xūbtar ka [az] rāspīg ī abēgumān wāz frāz
                gīrēd ud ātaxšgāh pad pādyāb be kunēd har kē andar ān yazišn kār-ē kāmēd kardan wāz
                az †ōy gīrēd u-š wāz frāz gīrēd</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">"(He has to recite:) <em>frauuarānē mazdaiiasnō</em> with the
                corresponding <em>gāh</em> and, when (the performance) takes place in the house of
                the good ones, (with the <em>šnūman</em>) <em>tauua ātarš puϑra ahurahe mazdā̊
                    xšnaōϑra</em>. There is one who says: "Always (with the <em>šnūman</em>)
                    <em>āϑrō ahurahe mazdā̊ puϑra tauua ātarš puϑra ahurahe mazdā̊ xšnaōϑra</em>".
                If the (priest) who ties the <em>barsom</em> and prepared the <em>parāhōm</em> holds
                the <em>wāz</em>, (the <em>zōt</em>) has to take the <em>wāz</em> from him. If not
                [[this is one uttenrance]], it is indeed better if he takes it from himself.
                Āzādmard said: "It is best for any <em>yazišn</em> if (the <em>zōt</em>) takes the
                    <em>wāz</em> from a well-qualified <em>rāspīg</em> and (then) purifies the seat
                of the fire. Any (priest) who desires to officiate at that <em>yazišn</em> takes the
                    <em>wāz</em> from him. He takes the <em>wāz</em>" </ab>
            <ab>WZ8.18-9</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">čīyōn gōwīhēd pad dēn kū-š pad zāyišn guft kū čīyōn ox kāmag tō kē
                zōt hē kū pēšōbāy ī dāmān hē frāz ō man gōw kū dastwar bawišn</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">čīyōn zarduxšt gētīy tanīh rāy gētīy ēwāzīhā guft Ohrmazd mēnōyīhā
                rāy ā-š pāsox guft kū ēdōn radīhā ēdōn frārōnīhā az ahlȳīh čēgām-iz-ēw frāz ahlawān
                āgāhīhā gōwam kū-t dastwar hom</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">As it is said in the dēn that at the time of his birth, Zaraθuštra
                received from Ohrmazd the authority regarding the dēn. As it is said in the dēn,
                (Zardušt) said at his birth: “Like the lord’s will you, who are the zōt [that is,
                you are the pēšōbāy of the creatures], say it to me [that is, you should act as the
                dastwar]. </ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">As Zardušt spoke with material words because of the materiality of
                his body, thus (spoke) Ohrmazd immaterially because of his immateriality. He
                answered: “Thus are the rad [thus are the virtuous ones] according to the Order
                whatever it is, I say it knowingly to the orderly ones [that is, I am the dastwar]
            </ab>
            <ab>Dk9.24 [DkM819.6 ff.]</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">guftan ī zardušt mēnōgīhā pad waγdān garān zāyišn kū-t čīyōn axw
                kāmag kē zōt hē frāz ō man gōwē ud passox ī az ohrmazd kū ēdōn
                radīhā az ahlāyīh čēgām-iz-ē frāz ahlaw āgāhīhā gōwam [tō hē frāyiz
                arztar ud tō ahlawtar ud tō āgāstom ud tō gōwē dēn ī māzdēsnān
                ō harwispīn dāmān ]</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">Regarding Zardušt’s words at the time of the difficult birth
                of his head: “Like the lord’s will you, who are the zōt. Ahura,
                say it to me. Mazdā answered: “Thus are the rad [thus are
                the virtuous ones] according to the Order, whatever it is, I, the
                virtuous one, say it knowingly [you are far more valuable, you
                are more virtuous and you are the wisest. You announce the
                dēn to all the creatures].</ab>
        </Quotations>

        <ModernPractice id="ritualModernPractice">
            <ab>
                <ab>
                    <bib>Kotwal and Boyd, 1991</bib>, p. 87:</ab>
                <ab class="ab_indent">"The chief priest (<em>zōt</em>) establishes eye contact with
                    his assistant (<em>rāspī</em>") (who continues to occupy the chief priest's seat
                    with his hand on the <em>barsom</em>) and proclaims the first phrase of an
                    antiphonal recitation, called an exchange of <em>bāj</em> ("utterance")."</ab>
            </ab>
        </ModernPractice>
    </Ritual>
    <translation>
        <include type="CAB" corresp="CABTrY0.3"/>
        <include type="W" corresp="WTrY0.1c-3a"/>
        <include type="K" corresp="KTrY0.1"/>
        <include type="D" corresp="DTrY0.1c-3a"/>
    </translation>
</text>