<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text xml:id="Y0.Ext3" status="created">
    <!-- created, approved, updated-->
    <header>
        <creators>
            <creator>Porro</creator>
            <creator>Cantera</creator>
        </creators>
        <created>1 June 2019</created>
        <approved/>
        <updated/>
    </header>
    <div xml:id="Y0.Ext3">
        <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/blocks/prayers/YAV" xpointer="YAV" times="7"/>
    </div>
    <Speaker>
        <SpeakerInfo>
            <div>zōt: vid. Y0.1.</div>
        </SpeakerInfo>
        <Commentary/>
    </Speaker>
    <Apparatus>

        <Critical/>
        <RecitationInstruction/>
        <Commentary>
            <ab><em>yaϑā. ahū. vairiiō.</em>] 15, 60, 82, 100, 110, 235. Number of Ahuna Vairiiias variable depending on the šnūman, see Ritual Information</ab>
        </Commentary>

    </Apparatus>
    <Parallels/>
    <Ritual>
        <Nerangs id="ritualNerangs">
            <ab>Vid. Y0.1.</ab>
            <ab>NērY0.1 Var c (Nērang ī Nō-nāwar yaštan)</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                <em> ka ādurgāh kāmēd šustan naxost dast pad pādyāb bē kunišn u-š ātaxš ud barsom bē
                    nigerišn u-š az nōg dast pad pādyāb abāz kunišn u-š</em> xšnaoθra. ahurahe.
                mazdā̊. tarōidite.<em> tā </em> fərašaōtəməm <em>bē gōwišn u-š az nōg dast pad
                    pādyāb abāz kunišn ud ašemwohū sē ...</em></ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                <em>rōz ī dudīgar ka yašt ī srōš kunēd pēš az ādurgāh suštan yatāhūwairyō panǰ bē
                    gōwišn u-š ādurgāh šustan ...</em>
            </ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent"><em>rōz ī sidīgar pēš az ādurgāh šustan </em>yaθā. ahū. vairiiō.
                    <em>dō ...</em></ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent"> When he wants to clean the <em>ādurgāh</em>, first, he has to made his
                hands clean with <em>pādyāb</em> and to look at the fire and the <em>barsom</em>. He
                has to made anew his hands clean. He has to recite <em>xšnaoθra ahurahe mazdā̊
                    tarōidite</em> until <em>fərašaōtəməm</em>. He has to made anew his hands clean
                with <em>pādyāb</em>. (He has to continue with) three Ašemwohū. ... The second day,
                when he performs the Yašt for Srōš, before cleaning the <em>ādurgāh</em>, he has to
                recite five Yatāhuwairyō. He should clean the <em>ādurgāh</em>. ... The third day,
                before cleaning the <em>ādurgāh</em>, (he should recite) two <em>yaθā ahū
                    vairiiō.</em>
            </ab>
            <ab>NērY0.1 Var d (Nērang ī Nō-nāwar yaštan)</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent"><em>ka ādurgāh kāmēd šustan naxost dast pad pādyāb abāz kunišn
                    u-š</em> xšnaōθra. ahurahe. mazdā̊. taraōi.diti. <em>tā</em> staōmi. aṣ̌əm <em>
                    bē gōwišn u-š nōg dast pad pādyāb abāz kunišn</em> aṣ̌əm. vohū. <em>sē
                </em>...</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent"><em>rōz ī dudīgar ka yašt ī srōš kunēd pēš az ādurgāh suštan
                yatāhūwairyō panǰ bē gōwišn u-š ādurgāh šustan </em>...</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent"><em>rōz ī sidīgar pēš az ādurgāh šustan</em> yaθā. ahū. vairiiō. <em>dō bē
                gōwišn</em></ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent"> When he wants to clean the <em>ādurgāh</em>, first, he has to made his
                hands clean with <em>pādyāb</em>. He has to recite <em>xšnaoθra ahurahe mazdā̊ taraōi.dīti.</em> until
                <em>staōmi aṣ̌əm</em>. He has to made anew his hands clean with <em>pādyāb</em>. (He has to continue
                with) three Ašemwohū. ... The second day, when he performs the Yašt for Srōš, before
                cleaning the <em>ādurgāh</em>, he has to recite five Yatāhuwairyō. He should clean the
                <em>ādurgāh</em>. ... The third day, before cleaning the <em>ādurgāh</em>, (he should recite) two <em>yaθā
                ahū vairiiō </em>.</ab>
            <ab>Ms. 0060 (cf. ms. 4075, same scribe):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent" n="NerangTranslit.a" xml:id="Y0.1NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">
                <em>yaθā. ahū. vairiiō. </em> agar yašt ašōān bāšad hašt agar yašt srōš bāšad panǧ
                ḫvandan agar yašt ruz bāšad haft agar yašt *nōnāvar bāšad haft ḫvandan agar yašt
                siruze bāšad dō ḫvandan agar yašt raftvan dvāzdah tā ḫvandan agar yašt humane bāšad
                hft tā ḫvandan tā sar ʾ </ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent" n="NerangEnglish.a" source="0060" xml:id="Y0.1NerangEnglish.a">
                    "<em>yaθā ahū vairiiō</em>. If it is a <em>yašt</em> for <em>ašōān</em>, eight
                times. If it is a <em>yašt</em> for Srōš, five times. If it is the <em>yašt</em> for
                the patron of the day, seven times. If it is a <em>yašt</em> Nōnāwar, seven times.
                If it is a <em>yašt</em> Siruze, two times. If it is a <em>yašt</em> for Rapihbin,
                twelve times. If it is a <em>yašt</em> for Vahman, seven times. (He should recite:)
                    <em>xšnōϑra. ahurahe. mazdā̊. aṣ̌əm. vohī.</em>" </ab>
        </Nerangs>
        <ModernPractice id="ritualModernPractice">
            <ab>
                <ab>
                    <bibl>Redard and Daruwalla, 2021</bibl>, pp. 69-70: </ab>
                <ab class="ab_indent">"... and if the Yasna of the day Ahuramajd is to be performed,
                    then he recites 10 Ahuna Vairiia, if the Yasna of Ardafrauuaš or of the Gāthā is
                    to be performed, then 8 (<em>Ahuna Vairiia</em>), if the Yasna to Sraoša is to
                    be performed, then 5 (<em>Ahuna Vairiia</em>), if the Yasna to Sīroza is to be
                    performed, then 2 (<em>Ahuna Vairiia</em>), if the Yasna to the Gāhānbār is to
                    be performed, then 4 (<em>Ahuna Vairiia</em>), and if the Yasna of Mīno Nāwar or
                    any of the days is to be performed, then 7 (<em>Ahuna Vairiia</em>).</ab>
                <ab class="ab_indent">Then, the chief priest taking the jug which has been made
                    pure, in his right hand, <em>xšnaoϑra ahurahe mazdā̊</em> 1x <em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū</em>
                </ab>
                <ab class="ab_indent">While reciting, he makes his left hand pure and inserting that
                    hand, which has been made pure, into the jug, he holds the jug. Then the second
                    time <em>xšnaoϑra ahurahe mazdā̊</em> 1x <em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū</em>
                </ab>
                <ab class="ab_indent">While reciting, he makes his right hand pure."</ab>
            </ab>
        </ModernPractice>
    </Ritual>
    <translation>
        <include type="CAB" corresp="CABTrY0.Ext3"/>
    </translation>
</text>