<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text xml:id="Y11.9" status="created">  <!-- created, approved, updated--> <header>
        <creators>
            <creator>Porro</creator>
            <creator>Cantera</creator>
        </creators>
        <created>1 June 2019</created>
    </header>
    <div type="Stanza" sameAs="" xml:id="Y11.9">
               <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/nerang/yasna_nerang" xpointer="Y11.9NerangTransc.a"/>
               <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/static/Yasna_static" xpointer="GY11.9"/>
            </div>
    <Apparatus>
        <Speaker>
            <SpeakerInfo>
                <div>
                    <ab class="ab_indent">rāspīg: vid. Nērangs, Anklesaria, Kotwal and Boyd, Geldner.</ab>
                </div>
            </SpeakerInfo>
            <Commentary/>
        </Speaker>
        <Critical/>
        <Commentary>
            <ab>Y11.9] Pirart del. and analyzes them as a collection of text in Old Avestan (cf. Parallels); <bibl>Bartholomae, 1904</bibl> p. 1171: "Ein kabbalistisches Gemengsel aus meist gāϑischen Wörtern, die zum guten Teil in andrer als der ihnen zukommenden Bedeutung gebraucht sind".</ab>
            <ab>Y11.9a <em>ϑrāiiōidiiāi</em>] Pirart <em>ϑrāiiō.diiāi</em>.</ab>
            <ab>Y11.9a <em>məṇdāidiiāi</em>] Kellens (Bartholomae), Hoffmann and Forssman; Geldner <em>maṇdāidiiāi</em>; Pirart <em>məṇdaidiiāi</em> (<bibl>Kellens, 1984</bibl> p. 350 and <bibl>Kellens and Pirart, 1991</bibl> p. 177).</ab>
            <ab>Y11.9a <em>haptāždiiāi</em>] Pirart <em>hapti āždiiāi</em>.</ab>
        </Commentary>
    </Apparatus>
    <Parallels>
        <ab><bibl>Pirart, 2003</bibl> pp. 113-114: <em>yō nō aēuuō</em> ~ Y29.8 <em>yə̄.nə̄ aēuuō</em>; <em>at̰ tē uiiē </em> ~ Y34.11 <em>at̰ tōi ubē</em>; <em>ϑrāiiōidiiāi</em> = Y34.5 <em>ϑrāiiōidiiāi</em>; <em>tūrahe</em> ~ Y46.12 <em>tūrahiiā</em>; <em>məṇdāidiiāi</em> = Y44.8 <em>məṇdāidiiāi</em>; <em>xšuuīdəm</em> ~ Y29.7 <em>xšuuīdəmcā</em>; <em>hapti</em> (first part of <em>haptāždiiāi</em>) ~ Y31.22 <em>haptī</em>; <em>āždiiāi</em> (second part) = Y51.17 <em>āždiiāi</em>; <em>nauua</em> ~ Y35.6 <em>nā.vā</em>; <em>dasme</em> ~ Y28.11 <em>dasəmē</em>; <em>yōi və̄ yaēϑma</em> ~ Y28.11 <em>yōi və̄ yōiϑəmā</em>.</ab>
    </Parallels>
    <Ritual>
        <Nerangs id="ritualNerangs">
            <ab>NerY11.9 Var.a (mss. 5, 6, 15, 60, 400, 410, 2065):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                rāspīg parāhōm pad dast ī hōy abar griftan pad gāh ī frabardārān barišn dast čahār angušt barsom dārišn bē gōwišn <em>yō nō aēuuō at̰ tē uiiē ϑrāiiōidiiāi tūrahe maṇdāidiiāi xšuuīdəm haptāždiiāi nauua dasme  yōi və̄ yaēϑma</em></ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "The <em>rāspīg</em> should take the <em>parāhōm</em> with the left hand and bring it to the place of the <em>frabardarān</em>.
                He has to hold his hand (at a distance of four finger of)  the <em>barsom</em>. He has to say: 
                <em>yō. nō. aēuuō. at̰. tē. uiiē. ϑrāiiōidiiāi. tūrahe. maṇdāidiiāi. xšuuīdəm. haptāždiiāi. nauua. dasme.  yōi. və̄. yaēϑma.</em>."</ab>
            <ab>NerY11.9 Var. b (mss. 40, 88):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                rāspīg parāhōm pad dast ī hōy abar griftan pad gāh ī frabardārān barišn bē ō gāh ī xwēš 
                pad war ī zōhrag dast čahār angušt barsom dārišn bē gōwišn <em>yō nō aēuuō at̰ tē uiiē ϑrāiiōidiiāi tūrahe manḍāidiiāi xšuuīdəm haptāždiiāi nauua dasme yōi və̄ yaēϑma</em></ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">"The <em>rāspīg</em> should take the <em>parāhōm</em> with the left hand and bring it to the place of the <em>frabardarān</em>, to its own place facing the <em>zōhrag</em>. 
                He has to hold his hand (at a distance of four finger of) the <em>barsom</em>. He has to say: <em>yō nō aēuuō at̰ tē uiiē ϑrāiiōidiiāi tūrahe maṇdāidiiāi xšuuīdəm haptāždiiāi nauua dasme yōi və̄ yaēϑma</em>"</ab>
        </Nerangs>
        <Quotations id="ritualQuotations">
        <ab>N28.42 </ab>
        <ab class="ab_indent">
            pad <em>ẏō nō aēuuō at̰ te</em> parāhōm pad war ī zōhrag barišn u-š <em>ẏō nō aēuuō</em> pad war ī zōhrag gōwišn ast kē ēdōn gōwēd ay ka andar rāh-ē be gōwēd ā šāyēd</ab>
        <ab class="ab_indent">
            "At <em>ẏō nō aēuuō at̰ </em> he has to bring the <em>parāhōm</em> next to the <em>zōhrag</em>. He has to recite <em>ẏō nō aēuuō </em> facing the <em>zōhrag</em>. 
            There is one commentator who says: "If he recites it on the way, it is allowed."</ab>
        </Quotations>
        <ModernPractice id="ritualModernPractice">
            <ab><ab><bibl>Redard and Daruwalla, 2021</bibl>, p. 81:</ab>
                <ab class="ab_indent">"The chief priest, after reciting upto here, sits quietly. The assistant priest, without saying anything, after making his left hand pure, 
                    picking up the <em>hom</em> cup with that left hand from the top of the table, going near the fire, 
                    with the right hand, he puts on the ladle that one (piece of) wood (and) incense  which has been kept on the second stone, 
                    he puts (it) on the fire and then coming towards the chief priest’s left side, 
                    putting the <em>hom</em> cup on the <em>barsam</em> holder, the assistant priest recites alone the below Avestan (text)"</ab></ab>
            
            <ab><ab><bibl>Kotwal and Boyd, 1991</bibl> p. 98:</ab> 
                <ab class="ab_indent">"Before concluding st. 8, the <em>rāspī</em> purifies his left hand with water poured from the vaselike pot located next to the large
                    basin of water. With his purified left hand he picks up the <em>parāhōm</em> cup, returns to his place, and while holding the cup before the
                    fire, takes the last remaining set of sandalwood and frankincense (<em>ēsm-bōy</em>) from the stone block nearest the fire and offers it on a ladle to the
                    fire. Returning the ladle to its tray, he walks around the south side of the fire to the ritual table and touches the <em>parāshōm</em> cup to the southern edge
                    of the <em>barsom</em> wires. He recites st. 9 alone, directing his words to the <em>zōt</em>: "May this (the <em>parāhōm</em>) have ten-fold blessings on you." 
                    He pours a few drops of the <em>parāhōm</em> juice on the date-palm cord tied around the <em>barsom</em>, and hands the cup to the <em>zōt</em>, 
                    who takes it in his right hand."</ab></ab>
        </ModernPractice>
    </Ritual>
    <translation>
        <include type="CAB" corresp="CABTrY11.9"/>
        <include type="W" corresp="WTrY11.9"/>
        <include type="K" corresp="KTrY11.9"/>
        <include type="D" corresp="DTrY11.9"/></translation>
</text>