<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text xml:id="Y11.4" status="created">
   <!-- created, approved, updated-->
   <header>
      <creators>
         <creator>Porro</creator>
         <creator>Cantera</creator>
      </creators>
      <created>1 June 2019</created>
      <updated>10 July 2021</updated>
   </header>
   <div type="Stanza" sameAs="" xml:id="Y11.4">
      <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/static/Yasna_static" xpointer="GY11.4"/>
   </div>
   <Speaker>
      <SpeakerInfo>
         <div>
            <ab class="ab_indent">zōt ud rāspīg: vid. Y11.1.</ab>
         </div>
      </SpeakerInfo>
      <Commentary/>
   </Speaker>
   <Apparatus>
      <Critical/>
      <Commentary>
         <ab> Y11.4a <em>us.mē ... frə̄rənaōt̰</em>] Form with double praeverb unusual (<bibl>Delbrück, 1893</bibl> p. 434 ff. <em>us°</em> + <em>ar-</em> is a hapax. <bibl>Pirart, 2004</bibl> p. 111 n. 367 corrects in <em>uši</em> (unattested).</ab>
         <ab>Y11.4a <em>pita</em>] Pirart <em>pta</em>.</ab>
         <ab>Y11.4a <em>mat̰ hizuuō</em>] Geldner, Kellens, Pirart <em>mat̰.hizuuō</em>. Bartholomae gen. instead of instr., but cf. Yt19.95 instr. sg. <em>xᵛaēpaiθiia hizuuō</em>. Maybe OAv. <em>hizuuā</em>, YAv. <em>hizuuō</em> (<em>hizuua</em> unattested).</ab>
      </Commentary>
   </Apparatus>
   <Parallels>
      <ab><em>ahurō mazdā̊ aṣ̌auua haŋᵛharəne mat̰ hizuuō hōiiumca dōiϑrəm</em> = Y11.5.</ab>
   </Parallels>
   <Ritual>
      <Quotations id="ritualQuotations">
         <ab>PRDd26.4:</ab>
         <ab class="ab_indent">ud hōm yazd ō kas rāy nifrīn kunēd gōwēd kū-t frazend ma bawād u-t dusrawīh-iz ud abārīg anāgīh xwēš bawād kē man andar yazišn kār 
            nē +framāyē ud sūr ī pid ohrmazd bē ō man dād ērwārag abāg uzwān ud čašm ī hōy ī hamāg gōspand ud gōspand sardagān nē yazē bē +jōyē 
            kē ān sūr ī pid ī man ohrmazd bē ō man dād nē yazēd bē jōyēd andar mān ī ōy nē zāyēd nē āsrōn nē artēštār ud nē wāstaryōš ud andar mān ī ōy zāyēnd mardōm ī čihr ī jādūgān 
            ud +wināhēd +dahišn +ī ohrmazd kirrēnīdār +ī tis tabāh kunēd ud ka kār ud dādestān was frāz kunēd tis-iz bē ō frazām nē āwarēd 
            u-š mēnōyīhā pad ān band bandēm ī-m tūr ī frāsyāb bast </ab>
         <ab class="ab_indent">And the yazad Hōm curses that person, he says: (~ Y11.4-7) "May you not have children, and may dishonour and other afflictions be yours, 
            you who do not use me in worship. Nor do you consecrate the meal which (my) father Ohrmazd gave to me the jaw along with the tongue and left eye of all beneficent animals, 
            and the varieties of beneficent animals you do not consecrate (for me), but you devour (it)! Whoever does not consecrate that food which my father Ohrmazd gave to me, 
            but devours it, in his house will be born neither priest nor warrior nor husband man. In his house people of the line of sorcerers will be born, and will destroy the creations of Ohrmazd. 
            (He is) the miscreator who ruins things, and (even if) he will undertake many duties and obligations, he will bring nothing at all to completion,
            and I shall bind him in the spiritual slate with those bonds with which I bound Frasyab the Tūr."
         </ab>
         
         <ab>ŠnŠ11.4 (<bibl>Kotwal, 1969</bibl> pp. 22-23)</ab>
         <ab class="ab_indent">gōspand ka kušt ud pārag judāg kard ā-š gāušudāg ēdōn baxšišn huzwān ērwārag ud cašm ī hōy hōm yazad xwēš gardan.</ab>
         <ab class="ab_indent">"When a <em>gōspand</em> is slaughtered and divided into pieces, its <em>gōšōdō</em> should be distributed in this manner: the tongue, jaw and left eye (are) <em>Hōm Yazad's</em> own.</ab>
         
         <ab>ŠnŠ11.6 (<bibl>Kotwal, 1969</bibl> pp. 24-25)</ab>
         <ab class="ab_indent">ka ēk did rāy ul yazēd *ā šāyēd bē uzwān ud ērwārag ud čašm ī hōy čē ān hōm yazd xwēš az ān gyāg paydāg <em>hizuuąm frərənaōt̰</em> .</ab>
         <ab class="ab_indent">"(If) one offers up one (part) to another (<em>yazad</em>), it shall be proper, except for the tongue and jaw and left eye, for those (are) Hōm Yazad. 
            (This is) manifest from that passage (containing the words) <em>hizuuąm</em> (and) <em>frərənaōt̰</em>."</ab>
         
         <ab>Revāyat Kāmdin Šāpur <bibl>Unvala, 1922</bibl> p. 540:</ab>
         <ab class="ab_indent">con sar-e gusfand ḫᵛāhand yaštan sar tamām nahand yā aravāra yaʿni guš-e cap həzvą̇n yaʿni zabān va cašm-e cap va gušt az ān gusfand gušodā kardan va
            ḫešnuman-e darun in ast <em>ahurahe mazdā̊ raēuuatō x́arənaŋhatō aməṣ̌ną̇m spəṇtaną̇m haomahe aṣ̌auua.zaŋhō aoxtō.nāmanō ẏazatahe</em> pa yazamaydi 
            <em>ahurəm mazdą̇m raēuuṇtəm x́arənaŋhuuṇtəm ẏaz• aməṣ̌āspəṇtā huxṣ̌aϑrā huδā̊ŋhō ẏaz• huməm zāirīm bərəzṇtəm
            ẏaz• huməm frāsmīm frādat̰.gaēϑəm ẏaz• huməm dūraošəm ẏaz• aṣ̌āuną̇m vaŋhuīš sūrā̊ spəṇtā̊ fruuaš́aiiō ẏaz•</em> arvār pa guǧodā nemišāyad 
            <em>usmē paiti haomāi dronō  frə̄ri.nōit̰. ahurōmazdā̊ aṣ̌auua haŋharəna mat̰.hizuuō hōiiumca dōiϑrəm</em> ni pə̄dir həmēṣ̌a ą̇n ō hmə̄surxfrājit aormazd aṣ̌ō uruuār vā hizuuą̇n ą̇ni 
            cap dōsr yʿani cašm.</ab>
         <ab class="ab_indent">"If one wishes to consecrate the head of a <em>gusfand</em>, the whole head should be put (for consecration), (if not), the <em>arvār</em> i.e., the left ear,
            the <em>hizvān</em> i.e., the tongue and the left eye (should be consecrated). The <em>goshodā</em> (to be placed with the Darun) should be (a piece of) flesh of that
            <em>gusfand</em>. The Khshnuman (for the consecration) of the Darun is <em>ahurahe mazdā̊ raēuuatō x́arənaŋhatō aməṣ̌ną̇m spəṇtaną̇m haomahe aṣ̌auua.zaŋhō 
               aoxtō.nāmanō ẏazatahe</em> pa yazamaydi <em>ahurəm mazdą̇m raēuuṇtəm x́arənaŋhuuṇtəm ẏaz• aməṣ̌āspəṇtā huxṣ̌aϑrā huδā̊ŋhō ẏaz• huməm zāirīm bərəzṇtəm
                  ẏaz• huməm frāsmīm frādat̰.gaēϑəm ẏaz• huməm dūraošəm ẏaz• aṣ̌āuną̇m vaŋhuīš sūrā̊ spəṇtā̊ fruuaš́aiiō ẏaz•</em>. 
            The <em>arvār</em> (i.e., the left ear, the tongue and the eye) should not be used as <em>goshodā</em> (as according to the following passage of Y11): 
            <em>usmē paiti haomāi dronō  frə̄ri.nōit̰. ahurōmazdā̊ aṣ̌auua haŋharəna mat̰.hizuuō hōiiumca dōiϑrəm</em>" (<bibl>Dhabhar, 1932</bibl>, pp. 262).</ab>
      </Quotations>
   </Ritual>
   <translation>
      <include type="CAB" corresp="CABTrY11.4"/>
   <include type="W" corresp="WTrY11.4"/><include type="K" corresp="KTrY11.4"/><include type="D" corresp="DTrY11.4"/></translation>
</text>