<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text xml:id="Y11.11" status="created">
    <!-- created, approved, updated-->
    <header>
        <creators>
            <creator>Porro</creator>
            <creator>Cantera</creator>
        </creators>
        <created>1 June 2019</created>
    </header>
    <div type="Stanza" sameAs="" xml:id="Y11.11">
        <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/blocks/prayers/AV" xpointer="AV2"/>
        <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/nerang/yasna_nerang" xpointer="Y11.11NerangTransc.a"/>
        <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/blocks/prayers/AV" xpointer="AV3"/>
        <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/blocks/prayers/AV" xpointer="AV"/>
        <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/blocks/prayers/AV" xpointer="AV2"/>
        <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/blocks/prayers/AV" xpointer="AV3"/>
        <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/blocks/prayers/AV" xpointer="AV"/>
        <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/blocks/prayers/AV" xpointer="AV2"/>
        <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/blocks/prayers/AV" xpointer="AV3"/>
        <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/blocks/prayers/AV" xpointer="AV"/>
    </div>
    <Speaker>
        <SpeakerInfo>
            <div>
                <ab class="ab_indent">zōt ud rāspīg: vid. Nērangs, Quotations, Modern Practice.</ab>
            </div>
        </SpeakerInfo>
        <Commentary/>
    </Speaker>
    <Apparatus>
        <Critical/>
        <Commentary/>
        <RecitationInstruction>
            <ab>Vid. Nērangs.</ab>
        </RecitationInstruction>
    </Apparatus>
    <Parallels/>

    <Ritual>
        <Nerangs id="ritualNerangs">
            <ab>Y11.11 Var.a (mss. 88, 2101):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                <em>aṣ̌əm vohū</em> sē guftan parāhōm pad panǰ dō abāz xwarišn ud dahān pāk kardan pad sar nimāyišn rāspīg <em>aṣ̌əm vohū</em> dō guftan zōt parāhōm pad panǰ sē xwardan dahān pāk kardan rāspīg 
                <em>aṣ̌əm vohū</em> dō guftan ud zōt parāhōm hamāg xwardan dahān pāk kardan dast pad sar abardahomin kardan rāspīg ašemwohū dō guftan edōn kē fradom nēmag-ē abāg xwarišn ud bār ī did az ān ī abāg nēm-ē abāg xwarišn bār ī sidigar hamāg abāg xwarišn ka čahār bār xwardan bawēd ā-š drāyīd bēd</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "He should recite three <em>aṣ̌əm vohū.</em> He has to drink the <em>parāhōm</em> in a portion of two fifths and clean his mouth. When the <em>zōt</em> ends (the first sip), 
                the <em>rāspīg</em> should recite two <em>aṣ̌əm vohū</em>. The <em>zōt</em> should drink the <em>parāhōm</em> in a portion of three fifths (of the remaining quantity) 
                and clean his mouth. The <em>zōt</em> should drink the whole (rest of the) <em>parāhōm</em> and clean his mouth. He should put his hand on the top of the <em>abardahomin</em> (?). 
                The <em>rāspīg</em> should say two <em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū</em>. There is one who (says) that : "First, he has to drink one half of the avaible (<em>parāhōm</em>). 
                The second time he has to drink a half of the still available. The third time, he drinks all the available (<em>parāhōm</em>). When he has drunk four times, then he has chattered."</ab>
            <ab>Y11.11 Var. b (mss. 5, 6, 40, 400, 410):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent"><em>aṣ̌əm vohū</em> sē guftan ud parāhōm pad panǰ ud dō abāz
                xwarišn ud harw bār rāspīg ašemwohū dō guftan zōt dahān pāk kardan ud dast harw dō pad pādyāb kardan abar barsom nihādan ast kē fradom nēmag-ē abāg xwarišn bār
                ī did az ān ī abāg nēm-ē abāg xwarišn bār ī sidigar hamāg abāg xwarišn</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">"He has to say three <em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū</em>. He has to drink the <em>parāhōm</em>
                in portions of two fifths and each time, the <em>rāspīg</em> should say two <em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū</em>. 
                The <em>zōt</em> should clean his mouth and wash both hands with <em>pādyāb</em>. He should put (his hand) on the <em>barsom</em>. 
                There is one who (says that) first, he has to drink one half of the avaible (<em>parāhōm</em>). The second time he has to drink an half of the still available.
                The third time, he drinks all the available (<em>parāhōm</em>). Then they should say four <em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū</em>."</ab>
            
            <ab>Y11.11 Var. c (ms. 15):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent"><em>aṣ̌əm vohū</em> se guftan ud parāhōm pad sē bār xwardan harw
                bār rāspīg <em>aṣ̌əm vohū</em> dō guftan bōy ō ātaxš dādan</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">"He should recite three <em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū</em> and drink the <em>parāhōm</em>
                in three times. Each time the <em>rāspīg</em> should recite two <em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū</em> and give <em>bōy</em> to the fire"</ab>
        </Nerangs>
        <Quotations id="ritualQuotations">
            <ab>Cf. N28.43-44  (<bibl>Kotwal and Kreyenbroek, 1995</bibl>: pp. 100-103): </ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">nēmag-ē abāg xwarišn ud bār ī did az ān ī abāg nēm-ē abāg xwarišn, ud bār ī sidīgar hamē abāg xwarišn ka IV
                bār xwarēd ā-š drāyīd bawēd ka ēk bār ayāb dō bār xwarēd ayāb rāspīg abestāg nē gōwēd ayāb-iš ātaxš-ē
                *abd ī ōh nišīnīhēd wāzag-ē be gōwēd ayāb zōt dast nē pad barsom dārēd ašə̣ m vohū be ēk nē rōšnag ēdōn
                uskārd kū hamāg šāyēd be ān ī ēw-tom kū zōt dast nē pad barsom dārišn ašə̣ m vohū be gōwēd čē ān kē abāg gōwēd
                u-š gumānīg ast kē ēdōn gōwēd ay hād <em>vaŋhuca vaŋhā̊sca</em> †ōh rāyēnišn u-š gumānīg wizārd bawēdkay-ādur-bōzēd
                guft hād pōryōtkēšān abastāg anēraxt nē cāšt estēd pad ēn †wāzag ā ham-dādestān bawēd ast kē ēdōn gōwēd pad-iz
                abārīg nē bawēd ast kē ōwōn [ēdōn] gōwēd ay pad-iz ēn nē bawēd</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">"He has to drink one half with (the first <em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū</em>), and the second time, with (the second <em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū</em>), he should drink half of what is left; and
                the third time she should drink the rest with (the final <em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū</em>). If he drinks a fourth time, he has 'chattered'. If he drinks once or two times, or if the
                <em>rāspīg</em> does not recite the <em>abastāg</em>, or if he sets down the marvelous fire and says (only) one prayer, or if the <em>zōt</em> does not have his hand on
                the <em>barsom</em> and only recites one <em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū</em>, then it is not clear. It has been considered thus that everything is permissible except if the foremost one, that
                is, the <em>zōt</em>, does not keep his hand on the <em>barsom</em>. He should recite the <em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū</em>. (alone), for if he recites it together (with the
                    <em>rāspīg</em>), then it is doubtful for him. There is one who says thus: 'He has to continue up to <em>vaŋhuca vaŋhā̊sca</em>, then he has completed it
                doubtfully.' Kay-Ādur-bōzēd said: 'The <em>pōryōtkēšān</em> have not taught the <em>abastāg</em> without dissent. Concerning the (recitation ) this prayer (the
                <em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū</em> at this point), there is agreement.' There is, however, a commentator who says: 'Also concerning other issues, there is not agreement.' There is one
                commentator who says: 'Also concerning this one issue, there is no (agreement).'</ab>
            
            <ab>Cf. Purs. 28, <bibl>Jamaspasa and Humbach, 1971</bibl> pp. 44-45:</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">ka parāhōm xwarēnd naxust ud dudīgar wēš ud sisīgar wēštar xwarēnd šāyēd ayāb nē</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">nē xūb nē kunišn  <em>xᵛarōiš haōməm zaraϑuštra bisarəmca ϑrəsarəmca yaϑa ϑrəsarəmca nitəməm</em>xwarē hōm zarduxšt pad dō kunišnīh sē kunišn
                    ēdōn pad sē kunišnyh nidom bār ī sidīgar kem xwar dastwarān pad harw bahr-ē az panǰ bahr-ē sē bahr xward guft hēnd</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">"If he (i. e. the Zōt) drinks the Parāhōm the first (time), the second (time) more and the third (time) even more, is it proper, or not?"</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">"It is not good, it should not be done. <em>xᵛarōiš haōməm zaraϑuštra bisarəmca ϑrəsarəmca yaϑa ϑrəsarəmca nitəməm</em>. 
                Thou should partake of Hōm, o Zartuxšt, in 2 actions and 3 actions so that at the third, (it is) the least [the third time, partake of the least]. The <em>dastwar</em>s have said to
                partake of 3 portions from 5 portions for each portion</ab>
            
            <ab>Cf. Purs. 29, <bibl>Jamaspasa and Humbach, 1971</bibl> pp. 46-47:</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">ān <em>aṣ̌əm</em> šaš ka xwandār nē gōwēnd u-š saxwan andar gōwēnd šāyēd ayāb nē</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">nē <em>vīspaēca aṇtarə aṣ̌əm *upa.stuiiā̊</em> harwisp andarag ī ahlāyīh xūb abar ē stāyēnd [rāspīg] <em>fraōrət̰ *fraxšni aōi manō
                zrazdātōit̰ aŋhuiiāt̰ haca</em> pad franāmišnīh was [kū was bār ō ēn kār *franabīnīh] abar pad menišn [kū menišn frōdīhā] pad rawāg-dahišnīh az axw [ī pad dastwar]</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">"If the <em>reciter</em> does not say the six Aṣ̌əm Vohū and he  does say something in between, is this allowed or not?</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent"> No. <em>vīspaēca aṇtarə aṣ̌əm *upa.stuiiā̊</em> At all pauses (between the three sips) the must praise <em>ahlāyīh</em> well  [the <em>rāspīg</em>]
                    <em>fraōrət ̰*fraxšni aōi manō zrazdātōit̰ aŋhuiiāt̰ haca</em> Which much celebration [that is, the performance several times to this purpose], with lofty
                thought [that is, thougthful] and with progress-giving thorugh the lord [ for the dastwar]. </ab>
            
            <ab>Cf. Purs. 30, <bibl>Jamaspasa and Humbach, 1971</bibl> pp. 46-47:</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">ka harw šaš pad ēw-bār bē gōwēd šāyēd ayāb nē</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">nē šāyēd mā agar dēwēzagīh-iz bēd u-š harw dō <em>aṣ̌əm</em> bē gōwišn u-š bē pāyišn tāg abg xwarēd u-š pas  <em>aṣ̌əm</em> gōwišn
                <em>vīspā̊ aṇtarə viiānīš</em> u-š pad harwisp andarag *pārē [kū-š bē *pāyē]</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">When (the <em>rāspīg</em>) recites all six (Aṣ̌əm Vohū) without pause, is this allowed or not?</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">No. In this case, it would be <em>dēw-</em>worship. (The <em>rāspīg</em> has to say the two Aṣ̌əm Vohū and has to watch one one (while
                the <em>zōt</em>) drinks (the <em>parāhōm</em>. Then , he has to recite Aṣ̌əm Vohū. <em> vīspā̊ aṇtarə viiānīš</em>. 
                He has to stop at all the pauses [that is, he has to watch it].</ab>
        </Quotations>
        <ModernPractice id="ritualModernPractice">
            <ab><ab><bibl>Redard and Daruwalla, 2021</bibl>, p. 81-83:</ab>
                <ab class="ab_indent">"The assistant priest recites with (the chief priest) the above 3 <em>Aṣ̌ǝm Vohū.</em>. 
                    The chief priest taking care that the left hand does not touch the mouth sheet (and) become impure, after lifting the mouth sheet with the left hand,
                    drinks one third part of the <em>hom</em> inside the cup and gazes towards the assistant priest. The assistant priest, standing on the Western side, while putting
                    fragrant incense on the fire, recites alone:</ab>
                <ab class="ab_indent">"1×Aṣ̌ǝm Vohū"</ab>
                <ab class="ab_indent">"The chief priest, lifting the mouth sheet with care, drinks half part of the remaining <em>hom</em>, and gazes towards the assistant priest.
                    The assistant priest, for the second time, looking at the bundle, while putting the fragrant incense on the fire, recites alone:"</ab>
                <ab class="ab_indent">"1×Aṣ̌ǝm Vohū"</ab>
                <ab class="ab_indent">"The chief priest, lifting the mouth sheet with care, drinks the entire remaining <em>hom</em> and gazes towards the assistant priest 
                    and the assistant priest, for the third time, while offering the fragrant incense on the fire, recites:"</ab>
                <ab class="ab_indent">"1×Aṣ̌ǝm Vohū"</ab>
                <ab class="ab_indent">The chief priest washing (and) making pure that <em>hom</em> cup three times, filling (it) with water, puts it back at its place. 
                    Then, cleaning his own mouth, wipes (it). Making the right hand pure again, he puts (it) on the cup and puts the left hand on the bundle. 
                    The chief priest and the assistant priest both remember in a low tone:</ab>
                <ab class="ab_indent"><em>anaošahī gaβāzišta gōš yak yazašnǝ i nǝ̄k pāβ kart ̰yazašnǝ i xvūb xvuršǝ̄δ saošiiōis ahuramazda amǝšāspǝṇdąn bǝ̄rasāt ̰gurja xvarǝhe aβazāiiāt ̰īn
                    xšnūmaine</em></ab>
                <ab class="ab_indent">Recite here that dedication in whose honour the Yasna is being performed. Below the example of the dedication of Mīno Nāvar has been given.</ab>
                <ab class="ab_indent"><em>mīnō nāβar vīspaešā ardā.frauuaš bǝ̄rasāδ nīraṇg pīrōzgar bāδ xvarǝh i vǝ̄h.dīn i māzdaiiasnąn rauuā bāδ … 
                    ǝž hamā gunāh patit pašǝ̄mąn.hom pa patit.hom</em></ab>
            </ab>
            
            <ab><ab><bibl>Kotwal and Boyd, 1991</bibl> p. 98-99:</ab> 
                <ab class="ab_indent">"After the <em>rāspī</em> returned to his place, both priests say a. v.3. The <em>zōt</em> removes his left hand from the
                    <em>barsom</em>, lifts his face mask with his left forearm, touches the cup to the outer portion of his lower lip, and takes the first sip of the <em>parāhōm</em>.
                    Looking directly at the <em>rāspī</em>, the <em>rāspī</em> recites a.v.1 and offers sandalwood and frankincense (<em>khūsh-bōy</em>) to the fire. 
                    This sequence is repeated two more times, the <em>zōt</em> drinking the entire contents of the <em>parahōm</em> cup by the third sip.</ab>
                <ab class="ab_indent">Having drunk the <em>parahōm</em>, the <em>zōt</em> with his left hand takes out a metal saucer from the large basin 
                    and rinses the emptied cup in his right hand three times, each time dipping water from the basin. He returns the saucer to the basin, 
                    places his left hand on the <em>barsom</em>, fills the cup with water from the basin, and places it back on the ritual table, resting his
                    right hand on it. The rtispr places a new set of sandalwood and frankincense (<em>ēsm-bōy</em>) on each of the two blocks near the fire, and
                    recites with the <em>zōt</em> in an undertone (<em>bista</em>) the Pazand dedication (<em>dībāchā</em>). When the name of the spirit being and the
                    remembrance of the soul of the deceased are being uttered in the Pazand dedication, the <em>rāspī</em> offers some sandalwood and frankincense (<em>khūsh-bōy</em>)
                    to the fire.</ab></ab>
        </ModernPractice>
    </Ritual>
    <translation>
        <include type="CAB" corresp="CABTrY11.11"/>
        <include type="W" corresp="WTrY11.11"/>
        <include type="K" corresp="KTrY11.11"/>
        <include type="D" corresp="DTrY11.11"/>
    </translation>
</text>