<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text xml:id="Y24.0" status="created">
    <!-- created, approved, updated-->
    <header>
        <creators>
            <creator>Porro</creator>
            <creator>Cantera</creator>
        </creators>
        <created>1 June 2019</created>
    </header>
    <div type="Stanza" sameAs="" xml:id="Y24.0">
        <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/nerang/yasna_nerang" xpointer="Y24.1NerangTransc.a"/>
        <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/static/Yasna_static" xpointer="GY24.1a"/>
    </div>
    <Speaker>
        <SpeakerInfo>
            <div>
                <ab class="ab_indent">zōt ud rāspīg: Anklesaria, Kotwal and Boyd, Geldner.</ab>
            </div>
        </SpeakerInfo>
    </Speaker>
    <Apparatus>
        <Critical/>
        <Commentary/>
        <RecitationInstruction>
            <ab>Y24.0a <em>ahurāi mazdāi</em> ...] <em>ahurāi mazdāi</em> OD LOYŠE <em>daϑušō
                    ahurahe mazdā̊</em> (Y24.12) 40.</ab>
        </RecitationInstruction>
    </Apparatus>
    <Parallels/>
    <Ritual>
        <Nerangs id="ritualNerangs">
            <ab>Y24.0 Var. a (mss. 15, 88, 400, 410 (sec.m.), 2007, 2010, 2030, 2101, 2104, 2106,
                2109):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent"> taštag kē-š hōm ud urwarām andar ān-iz ī-š ǰām andar dast stānišn
                abāg abastāg ul dārišn <em>ahurāi mazdāi</em>. ...</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent"> "He has to take in his hand the saucer that contains the
                    <em>hōm</em> and the <em>urwarām</em> and the one that contains the
                    <em>ǰīwām</em> and lift them up while reciting the <em>abastāg</em>
                <em>ahurāi mazdāi</em>. ..."</ab>
            <ab>Y24.0 Var. b (ms. 40): </ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent"> taštag kē-š hōm ud urwarām andar ān-iz ī-š ǰām andar dast stānišn
                abāg abastāg ul dārišn ēn kū čiyōn ud čand dārišn ā-m nē rōšnag dādweh guft hād gōš
                bālā dārišn frāz ō pēš dārišn u-š pad be nigerišn <em>ahurāi mazdāi</em>. ...</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent"> "He has to take in his hand the saucer that contains the
                    <em>hōm</em> and the <em>urwarām</em> and the one that contains the
                    <em>ǰīwām</em> and hold them up while reciting the Avestan text. It is not clear
                to me how, and how long, it should be held up. Dādweh said that he has to hold it to
                the height of his ears, he has to hold it in front of (his face) and gaze at it
                (while reciting) <em>ahurāi mazdāi</em>. ..." </ab>
        </Nerangs>
        <Quotations id="ritualQuotations">
            <ab>Cf. N28.46b <bibl>Kotwal and Kreyenbroek, 2003</bibl>, pp. 104-105:</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">u-š pad <em>ahurāi mazdāi</em> hōm ud urwarām †be †war ī ǰīuu ul
                dārišn ēn kū čiyōn ud čand dārišn ā-m nē rōšnag dādweh guft hād gōš bālāy dārišn
                frāz ō pēš dārišn u-š pad be nigerišn Ka-š <em>ahurāi mazdāi</em>be guft hāwan be
                šōyišn.</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">"And at <em>ahurāi mazdāi</em> he should lift up the <em>hōm</em>
                and <em>urwarām</em> together face on face with <em>jīw</em>. It is not clear to me
                how, and how long, it should be held up. <em>Dādweh</em> said: "He should hold it up
                to the height of his ears, he has to hold it in front of (his face), and gaze at it.
                When he has finished reciting <em>ahurāi mazdāi</em> he should wash the
                mortar."</ab>
            <ab>Cf. ŠnŠ13.9 ( <bibl>Kotwal, 1969</bibl>, pp. 42-3): </ab>
            <ab><em>ēd rāy pad </em> ahurāi mazdāi <em> hassārīh ī </em>daθuš <em>zōhr ham dil ī ōy
                    zōt rāst dārišn ud *ātrawaxšān ham bāzag ī ōy zōt rāst dārišn kū tā ardēštārān
                    andar kōxšišin ī abāg anērān nēwdiltarud wāstryōšān pad warz ud ābādīh ī gēhān
                    bāzāyōztar </em>
            </ab>
            <ab>"On account of this, at <em>ahurāi mazdāi</em>, the <em>zōhr</em> should be held on
                top of the <em>daθuš</em> exactly level with the heart of the Zōt, and the
                *Ātrawaxšān should hold (their) hands exactly level with the arm of the Zōt. so that
                the warriors may become mor brave in fighting with non-Iranians, and the husbandmen
                more strongarmed in the culituvation of the land and care of the creatures."</ab>
        </Quotations>
        <ModernPractice id="ritualModernPractice">
            <ab><bibl>Redard and Daruwalla, 2021</bibl>, p. 90:</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">"The chief priest, removing the mortar outside the water
                container, places (it) upside-down in front of him on the table and recites with the
                assistant priest:"</ab>

            <ab><bibl>Kotwal and Boyd, 1991</bibl> 109:</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">"As both priests recite the first line of st. I, the <em>zōt</em>
                takes the mortar out of the large basin of water and sets it upside down on the
                ritual table directly in front of him"</ab>
        </ModernPractice>
    </Ritual>
    <translation>
        <include type="CAB" corresp="CABTrY24.1"/>
        <include type="W" corresp="WTrY24.1"/>
        <include type="K" corresp="KTrY24.1"/>
        <include type="D" corresp="DTrY24.1"/>
    </translation>
</text>