<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text xml:id="Y25.1" status="created">  <!-- created, approved, updated--> <header>
        <creators>
            <creator>Porro</creator>
            <creator>Cantera</creator>
        </creators>
        <created>1 June 2019</created>
    </header>
    <div type="Stanza" sameAs="" xml:id="Y25.1">
               <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/static/Yasna_static" xpointer="GY25.1b"/>
               <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/nerang/yasna_nerang" xpointer="Y25.1NerangTransc.b"/>
               <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/static/Yasna_static" xpointer="GY25.1c"/>
               <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/static/Yasna_static" xpointer="GY25.1d"/>
            </div>
    <Speaker>
        <SpeakerInfo>
            <div>
                <ab class="ab_indent">zōt ud rāspīg: vid. Y25.0.</ab>
            </div>
        </SpeakerInfo>
    </Speaker>
    <Apparatus>
        <Critical/>
        <Commentary/>
        <RecitationInstruction>
            <ab>Y25.1a <em>iməm haōməm</em> ...] <em>aṣ̌aiia uzdātəm y.</em> OD LOYŠE <em>staōmi zbaiiemi</em> (Y25.4) 40.</ab>
        </RecitationInstruction>
    </Apparatus>
    <Parallels>
        <ab>VrS29.1 = DoHom6.1.</ab>
        <ab><em>iməm haōməm aṣ̌aiia uzdātəm yazamaide imąmcā gąm jīuuiiąm aṣ̌aiia uzdātąm yazamaide imąmcā uruuarąm haδānaēpatąm aṣ̌aiia uzdātąm yazamaide</em> 
            ~ Y22.2, Y22.22, Y22.25 <em>iməm haōməm aṣ̌aiia uzdātəm āiiese yešti imąmcā gąm jīuuiiąm aṣ̌aiia uzdātąm āiiese yešti imąmcā uruuarąm haδānaēpatąm aṣ̌aiia uzdātąm āiiese yešti</em>.</ab>
        <ab><em>imąmcā gąm jīuuiiąm aṣ̌aiia uzdātąm yazamaide imąmcā uruuarąm haδānaēpatąm aṣ̌aiia uzdātąm yazamaide</em>; ~ Y24.6 <em>imąmcā gąm jīuuiiąm aṣ̌aiia uzdātąm imąmcā uruuarąm haδānaēpatąm aṣ̌aiia uzdātąm</em>;
            ~ Y3.3 <em>gąm jīuuiiąm āiiese yešti uruuarąm haδānaēpatąm aṣ̌aiia uzdātąm āiiese yešti</em>; ~ Y7.4 <em>aṣ̌aiia daδąmi gąm jīuuiiąm aṣ̌aiia daδąmi uruuarąm haδānaēpatąm aṣ̌aiia uzdātąm</em>.</ab>
        <ab><em>uruuarąm haδānaēptąm</em> ~ Y62.9 <em>uruuarąm vā haδānaēpatąm</em>.</ab>
    </Parallels>
    <Ritual>
        <Nerangs id="ritualNerangs">
            <ab>Y25.1a  (mss. 40, 88, 400, 410):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                <em>aməṣ̌ā spəṇtā</em> (Y25.0) hāwan abāz wardēnišn <em>huxšaϑrā huδā̊ŋhō yazamaide iməm haōməm</em> (Y25.1) hōm ud urwarām andar hāwan abganišn <em>aṣ̌aiia uzdātəm</em> ...</ab> 
            <ab class="ab_indent">"At <em>aməṣ̌ā spəṇtā</em> (Y25.0), he has to turn the <em>hāwan</em> right side (and continue with) <em>huxšaϑrā huδā̊ŋhō yazamaide.</em>                
                At <em>iməm haōməm</em> (Y25.1), he has to throw the <em>hōm</em> and <em>urwarām</em> into the <em>hāwan</em> (and continue with) <em>aṣ̌aiia uzdātəm</em> ..."</ab>
            <ab>Y25.1b (40, 88, 400, 410):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent"><em>iməm haōməm</em> hōm ud urwarām andar hāwan abganišn <em>aṣ̌aiia uzdātəm</em> ...</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent"> "At <em>iməm haōməm</em>, he has to throw the <em>hōm</em> and <em>urwarām</em> into the <em>hāwan</em> (and continue with) <em>aṣ̌aiia uzdātəm</em>..."</ab>
        </Nerangs>
        
        <Quotations id="ritualQuotations">
            <ab>N28.46d (<bibl>Kotwal and Kreyenbroek, 2003</bibl>, pp. 104-105):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">u-š pad <em>iməm haōməm</em> hōm ud urwarām andar hāwan abganēd</ab>   
            <ab class="ab_indent">"At <em>iməm haōməm</em>, he throws the <em>hōm</em> and <em>urwarām</em> into the <em>hāwan</em>."</ab>
            <ab>Vid. also Y25.0.</ab>
        </Quotations>
        <ModernPractice id="ritualModernPractice">
            <ab><bibl>Redard and Daruwalla, 2021</bibl>, p. 91-92:</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">"The chief priest, after striking the inverted mortar on the table three times, turns it upright, and wiping the inside by hand, cleans (it). The chief priest puts
                the <em>hom</em> twigs into the mortar. <em>imǝm haomǝm aṣ̌aiia uzdātǝm yazamaide</em>. He pours the milk into the mortar. <em>imąmcā gąm jīuuiiąm aṣ̌aiia uzdātąm yazamaide imąmcā uruuarąm
                    haδānaēpatąm aṣ̌aiia uzdātąm yazamaide</em>".</ab>
            <ab><ab><bibl>Kotwal and Boyd, 1991</bibl>, p. 106: </ab>
                <ab class="ab_indent">"With his right hand he picks up the three <em>hōm</em> twigs from the saucer and drops them into the mortar, saying "We revere this <em>hōm</em> offered with righteousness" (<em>imem haomem
                ashaya uzdātem yazamaidē</em>). With the words "We revere this mixture of milk and consecrated water offered with righteousness" (<em>imāmcha gām jīvyām ashaya uzdātām yazamaidē</em>), the <em>zōt</em> picks up
                the cup located near the base of the <em>barsom</em> stand and pours a small amount of the goat's milk into the mortar, then returns the cup to its place. As he says the next phrases, "and we revere the pomegranate tree
                offered with righteousness" (<em>imāmcha urvarām hadhānaēpatām ashaya uzdātām yazamaidē)</em>, the <em>zōt</em> picks up the pomegranate twig from the saucer and drops it into the mortar",</ab></ab>
        </ModernPractice>
    </Ritual>
    <translation>
        <include type="CAB" corresp="CABTrY25.1"/>
    <include type="W" corresp="WTrY25.1"/>
        <include type="K" corresp="KTrY25.1"/>
        <include type="D" corresp="DTrY25.1"/>
    </translation>
</text>