<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text xml:id="Y62.10" status="created">
   <!-- created, approved, updated-->
   <header>
      <creators>
         <creator>Porro</creator>
         <creator>Cantera</creator>
      </creators>
      <created>1 June 2019</created>
   </header>
   <div type="Stanza" sameAs="" xml:id="Y62.10">
      <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/static/Yasna_static" xpointer="GY62.10"/>
   </div>
   <Apparatus>
      <Critical/>
      <Commentary/>
   </Apparatus>
   <Parallels/>
   <Ritual>
      <Quotations id="ritualQuotations">
         <ab>Revayat of Kāvus Kāmdin (MU1, pp. 506-507):</ab>
         <ab class="ab_indent">(Pers.) porseš inke dah ruz-e farvardiyān ce ciz rasm mikonand avval-e aršesang ruz-e māh-e esfandārmaẕ tā ḥad-e ruz-e ḫurdād māh-e farvārdin</ab>
         <ab class="ab_indent">"Question: During the ten days of Frawardigān, which usages do you observe? (From) the first day Aršhesang of the month Spandarmad, to the day Xordād of the month Frawardin.</ab>
         <ab class="ab_indent">(Pers.) pāsoḫ ānke az avval-e ruz-e āstād yazešn-e faravahr-e ašavān kardim va zamāni ke ātaš niyāyeš beǧāy ḫᵛāndim
            <em>frauuarāne</em> (SupplYĀbZ1) (Paz.) gāh rā (Per.) ḫᵛāndim <em>ahurahe mazdā̊ raēuuatō x́arənaŋhatō aməṣ̌ną̇m spəṇtaną̇m</em> (Pahl.) OD <em>ẏaϑā ahū vairiiō zaotā frāmē marūtē</em> (Per.) rāspi
            <em>ẏaϑā ahū vairiiō ẏō zaotā frā.mē marūtē</em> (Per.) goftan <em>ahurəm mazdą̇m raēuuṇtəm x́arənaŋhuuṇtəm ẏaz.</em> (SupplYĀbZ2) <em>aṣ̌ā̊ną̇m vaŋhuīš sūrā̊ spə̄ṇtā̊ frauuaṣ̌iiō ẏaz. ẏā vīsāt̰</em> (SupplYĀbZ3) (Pahl.) OD (Paz.) tā <em>y.</em>
            (Per.) beḫᵛānand (Paz.) aēsmabōī nuhtāk (Per.) har yek be <em>gumata jasta vastaruuata asnāsnəmaŋha</em> (SupplYĀbZ4-6) (Pers.) har yek esm-o buy dar ātaš benahand dar inǧāy va panǧ ruz-e farvārdiyān yazešn-e ašavān faravahr mikonand 
            va digar yazešthāy be minovān kardan.</ab>
         <ab class="ab_indent">Answer: From the first day Āstād we celebrate a Yasna to the Frawahr of the righteous and at the moment of the Ātaš Neyayešn at its place we recite: <em>frauuarāne</em> (SupplYĀbZ1), (then) we recite the <em>gāh</em>
            (and) <em>ahurahe mazdā̊ raēuuatō x́arənaŋhatō aməṣ̌ną̇m spəṇtaną̇m</em> until <em>ẏaϑā ahū vairiiō zaotā frāmē marūtē</em> (and then) the <em>rāspī</em> must say <em>ẏaϑā ahū vairiiō ẏō zaotā frā.mē marūtē</em>.
            (Then) we read <em>ahurəm mazdą̇m raēuuṇtəm x́arənaŋhuuṇtəm ẏaz.</em> (SupplYĀbZ2) <em>aṣ̌ā̊ną̇m vaŋhuīš sūrā̊ spə̄ṇtā̊ frauuaṣ̌iiō ẏaz. ẏā vīsāt̰</em> (SupplYĀbZ3) until <em>y.</em> and nine pieces of <em>ēsm</em> and <em>bōy</em> at each
            <em>gumata jasta vastaruuata asnāsnəmaŋha</em> (SupplYĀbZ4-6) once each time of <em>ēsm</em> and <em>bōy</em> must be placed at the fire. During the five days of the Frawardigān we perform the Yasna to the Frawahr of the righteous
            and we celebrate other Yasna to the spiritual beings.</ab>
         <ab>From "the book of Avesta and Zand" (MU1, pp. 351):</ab>
         <ab class="ab_indent">(Per.) az ketāb-e avestā va zand māh espandārmaẕ ruz-e āstād māci rā hurak guyand az avval yazešn-e faravahr-e ašavān kardan va zamāni ātaš niyāyeš beǧāy ḫᵛāndan pas har do hirbad āfringān-e ardāfaravāš ḫᵛāndan 
            va esm va buy bar ātaš nahādan va har yek be <em>gaomata jasta vastaruuata as nāisnəmaŋha</em> har yek beʾin soḫan esm va buy bar ātaš nahādan.</ab>
         <ab class="ab_indent">From the book of the Avesta and the Zand: (at) the month Spandarmad, (at) the day Āstād the Māci is called Hurak. First a Yasna to the Frawahr of the righteous must be performed and the Ātaš Neyayešn must be recited
            at its proper place. Then each of both Herbad should recite the Āfrinagān to the Ardāfrawahr and they should put <em>ēsm</em> and <em>bōy</em> over the fire. Each time at <em>gaomata jasta vastaruuata as nāisnəmaŋha</em> (SupplYĀbZ4-6) they should put the
            <em>ēsm</em> and <em>bōy</em> over the fire.</ab>
      </Quotations>
   </Ritual>
   <translation>
      <include type="CAB" corresp="CABTrY62.10"/>
      <include type="W" corresp="WTrY62.10"/>
      <include type="K" corresp="KTrY62.10"/>
      <include type="D" corresp="DTrY62.10"/>
   </translation>
</text>