<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text xml:id="Y63.6" status="created">  <!-- created, approved, updated--> <header>
        <creators>
            <creator>Porro</creator>
            <creator>Cantera</creator>
        </creators>
        <created>1 June 2019</created>
    </header>
    <div type="Stanza" sameAs="" xml:id="Y63.6">
               <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/nerang/yasna_nerang" xpointer="Y63.3NerangTransc.a"/>
               <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/static/Yasna_static" xpointer="GY63.3a"/>
               <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/nerang/yasna_nerang" xpointer="Y63.3NerangTransc.b"/>
               <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/static/Yasna_static" xpointer="GY63.3b"/>
               <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/nerang/yasna_nerang" xpointer="Y63.3NerangTransc.c"/>
               <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/static/Yasna_static" xpointer="GY63.3c"/>
               <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/nerang/yasna_nerang" xpointer="Y63.3NerangTransc.d"/>
               <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/static/Yasna_static" xpointer="GY63.3d"/>
               <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/nerang/yasna_nerang" xpointer="Y63.3NerangTransc.e"/>
               <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/nerang/yasna_nerang" xpointer="Y63.3NerangTransc.f"/>
            </div>
    <Apparatus>
        <Critical/>
        <Commentary/>
    </Apparatus>
    <Parallels/>
    <Ritual>
        <Nerangs id="ritualNerangs">
            <ab>Y63.6 Var. a (mss. 40, 88):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                skūrag kē-š zōhr padiš abar ǰām gāh ud barsom nihādan <em>ahurəm mazdąm aṣ̌auuanəm aṣ̌ahe ratūm yazamaide</em> pad mayānag ī barsom nihādan abar war ī zōhrag az 
                sar ī barsom pad čahār angust <em>aməṣ̌ā. spəṇtā huxšaϑrā huδā̊ŋhō yazamaide</em>. pad hōy ī barsom nihišn frāztom sar ī barsom <em>apō at̰ yazamaide</em>. abar āb 
                nihišn abar hōytar ī barsom pad war ī zōhrag az sar ī barsom pad čahār angust <em>aṣ̌āunąm urunascā frauuaṣ̌īšcā yazamaide</em>. abar ē barēd ō dašntar ī barsom pad war ī 
                zōhrag ham ēdōn pad čahār angust</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "He should put the cup that contains the <em>zōhr</em> next to the place of the <em>ǰīw</em> and next to the <em>barsom</em>. At <em>ahurәm mazdąm aѕauuanәm aѕahe ratūm yazamaide</em>, 
                he should put it in the middle of the <em>barsom</em>, next to the <em>zōhrag</em>, four finger away from the end of the <em>barsom</em>. At <em>aməṣ̌ā spəṇtā huxšaϑrā huδā̊ŋhō yazamaide</em>, 
                he should put it at the left side of the <em>barsom</em>, at the front of the <em>barsom</em>. At <em>apō at̰ yazamaide</em>, he has to put it over the water, at the left side of the <em>barsom</em>, 
                next to the <em>zōhrag</em>, four finger away from the end of the <em>barsom</em>. At <em>aṣ̌āunąm urunascā frauuaṣ̌īšcā yazamaide</em>, he should bring it to the right side 
                of the <em>barsom</em>, next to the <em>zōhrag</em>, again thus, four finger (away from the end of the <em>barsom</em>)."</ab>
            <ab>Y63.6 Var. b (mss. 400, 410):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                <em>ahurəm mazdąm</em>. pad mayānag ī barsom abar ē barēd <em>aṣ̌auuanəm aṣ̌ahe ratūm yazamaide</em>. abar war ī zōhrag az sar ī barsom pad čahār angust 
                <em>aməṣ̌ā spəṇtā huxšaϑrā huδā̊ŋhō yazamaide</em>. frāztom sar ī barsom <em>apō at̰ yazamaide</em>. abar hōytar ī barsom pad war ī zōhrag az sar ī barsom pad 
                čahār angust <em>aṣ̌āunąm urunascā</em>. ō dašntar ī barsom pad war ī zōhrag az sar ī barsom pad čahār angust <em>frauuaṣ̌īšcā yazamaide</em>.</ab> 
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "At <em>ahurəm mazdąm</em>, he should bring it to the middle of the <em>barsom</em>. At <em>aṣ̌auuanəm aṣ̌ahe ratūm yazamaide</em>, next to the <em>zōhrag</em>, 
                four fingers away from the end of the <em>barsom</em>. At <em>aməṣ̌ā spəṇtā huxšaϑrā huδā̊ŋhō yazamaide</em>, to the front of the <em>barsom</em>. At <em>apō at̰ yazamaide</em>, 
                to the left side of the <em>barsom</em>, at the level of the <em>barsom</em>, four fingers away from the end of the <em>barsom</em>. At <em>aṣ̌āunąm urunascā</em>, 
                to the right side of the <em>barsom</em>, at the level of the <em>barsom</em>, four fingers away from the end of the <em>barsom</em> (and continue with) <em>frauuaṣ̌īšcā yazamaide</em>."</ab>
        </Nerangs>
   <ab>~ VrS87.7</ab>
        <Quotations id="ritualQuotations">
            <ab>N52.3-8 (Avestan):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                <em>ẏat̰ zaōta ahurəm mazdąm ẏazāiti †maδəmāi barəsmąn paiti.barōit̰ aməṣ̌ə̄ spəṇtə̄ yazāiti †fratəmāi barəsmąn paiti.barōit̰ apō at̰ ẏazamaide †hauuiiōtəmāi barəsmąn paiti.barōit̰
                    aṣ̌āunąm urunasca †frauuaṣ̌īšca ẏazamaide †dašinōtəmāi barəsmąn paiti.barōit̰ vīspaēibiiō ẏasnō.kərətaēibiiō maδəmāi †barəsmąn paiti.barōit̰</em> </ab>  
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "When the <em>zaōtar</em> says <em>ahurəm mazdąm yazamaide</em>, he should bring (the libation) to the middle of the <em>barəsman</em>. When he says <em>aməṣ̌ə̄ spəṇtə̄ yazamaide</em>, 
                he should bring (the libation) to the front of the <em>barəsman</em>. (When he says), <em>apō at̰ ẏazamaide</em>, he should bring (the libation) to the left side of the <em>barəsman</em>.
                (When he says) <em>aṣ̌āunąm urunasca frauuaṣ̌īšca ẏazamaide</em>, he should bring (the libation) to the right side of the <em>barəsman</em>.  At each <em>yeŋ́hē.hātā</em>, 
                he should bring (the libation) to the middle of the <em>barəsman</em>."</ab>
            
            <ab>N52.3-8 (Pahlavi):</ab>
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                ka zōt ohrmazd yazēd [kū ēn abestāg gōwēd ay kū <em>ahurəm mazdąm</em>] pad mayānag ī barsom abar ē barēd ka amahraspandān yazēd [pad ān ī meh ud weh nām] frāztom 
                pad barsom abar ē barēd [pad sar ī barsom] ka āb ēdōn yazēd ō hōytom ī barsom abar ē barēd [pad war ī zōhrag] ka ahlawān ruwān frawahr yazād ō dašntom pad barsom abar ē barēd
                [pad hassārīh ī zōhrag] ud pad harwispīn yazišn-kardārīh [pad ẏeŋ́he hātąm] pad mayānag ī barsom abar ē barēd [pad war ī zōhrag]</ab>  
            <ab class="ab_indent">
                "When the <em>zōt</em> worships Ohrmazd [that is, he says following Avestan text: <em>ahurəm mazdąm</em>], he should bring (the libation) to the middle of the <em>barsom</em>. 
                When he worships the Amahraspandān, [with their big and best names], he should bring (the libation) to the front of the <em>barsom</em> [to the end of the <em>barsom</em>]. 
                When he worships thus the waters, he should bring (the libation) to the left side of the <em>barsom</em> [at the level of the <em>zōhrag</em>]. When he worships the souls and
                <em>frawahr</em> of the orderly ones, he should bring (the libation) to the right side of the <em>barsom</em> [at the level of the <em>zōhrag</em>]. At each <em>yazišn</em>-making
                [at the <em>Yeŋ́hē.hātā</em>], he should bring (the libation) to the middle of the <em>barsom</em> [at the level of the <em>zōhrag</em>]."</ab>
    <ab>Cf. N52.4(Avestan)(cf. <bibl>Kotwal and Kreyenbroek, 2003</bibl>: p. ****)</ab>
    <ab class="ab_indent">
                <em>ẏat̰ zaōta ahurəm mazdąm ẏazāiti *maδəmāi barəsmąn
paiti.barōit̰ aməṣ̌ə̄ spəṇtə̄ yazāiti *fratəmāi barəsmąn paiti.barōit̰ apō at̰ ẏazamaide *hauuiiōtəmāi barəsmąn paiti.barōit̰ aṣ̌āunąm urunasca *frauuaṣ̌īšca ẏazamaide *dašinōtəmāi barəsmąn paiti.barōit̰.</em>
            </ab>
<ab class="ab_indent">When the <em>zaōtar</em> makes the <em>yasna</em> for Ahura Mazdā, he should bring (the offering) on the middle part of the <em>barəsman</em>. When he makes the <em>yasna</em> for the Aməṣ̌a Spəṇta, he should bring ()the offering) to the middle part of the <em>barəsman</em>. (At) <em>apō at̰ ẏazamaide</em>he should bring (the offering) on the fartest part to the left of the <em>barəsman</em>. At <em>aṣ̌āunąm urunasca *frauuaṣ̌īšca ẏazamaide</em>he should bring(the offering) to the fartest part to the right of the <em>barəsman</em>.</ab>
<ab>The Avestan version describes the procedure as it appears in the Yasna, and the Middle Persian as in the Visperad (<bibl>Cantera, 2014</bibl>: pp. 191 ff.)</ab>
        </Quotations>
    </Ritual>
    <translation>
        <include type="CAB" corresp="CABTrY63.6"/>
    <include type="W" corresp="WTrY63.3a"/><include type="K" corresp="KTrY63.3a"/><include type="D" corresp="DTrY63.3a"/></translation>
</text>