<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text xml:id="Y64.5" status="created">
   <!-- created, approved, updated-->
   <header>
      <creators>
         <creator>Porro</creator>
         <creator>Cantera</creator>
      </creators>
      <created>1 June 2019</created>
   </header>
   <div type="Stanza" sameAs="" xml:id="Y64.5" quote="Y50.8">
      <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/nerang/yasna_nerang" xpointer="Y64.5NerangTransc.a"/>
      <include href="/db/apps/cab_db/cab_rituals/static/Yasna_static" xpointer="GY64.4"/>
   </div>
   <Apparatus>
      <Critical/>
      <Commentary/>
   </Apparatus>
   <Parallels/>
   <Ritual>
      <Nerangs id="ritualNerangs">
         <ab>Y64.5 Var. a (mss. 82, 88, 400, 410):</ab>
         <ab class="ab_indent">
            ... <em>auuaŋ́he</em> barsom az māhrōy ul stānišn az zōtgāh gām-e pad kust ī frabardārān nihišn <em>mat̰ vā̊ padāiš</em> bē kunišn pad ruwān ō ī bun ī ātaxš gāh tā <em>haiϑiiāuuarəštąm</em>. 
            gōwišn <em>mat̰ vā̊</em> gām-ē frāz nihišn namāz ō ī zōhr barišn padāiš gām-ē namāz ō zōhr barišn <em>yā frasrūtā īžaiiā̊</em> gām-ē frāz nihišn be ō ī gāh ābardān šawišn
            <em>pairi.jasāi</em> šaš gōwišn u-š sē gām az kustag ī hōy pad sar ī barsom bē āyišn</ab> 
         <ab class="ab_indent">
            "He has to take the <em>barsom</em> from the <em>māhrōy</em> and make one step towards the side of the <em>frabardārān</em>. Here, he has to recite the section going from 
            <em>mat̰ vā̊ padāiš</em> until <em>haiϑiiāuuarəštąm</em> with the mind put on the beginning of the fire place. At <em>mat̰ vā̊</em>, he has to make a second step and bring homage 
            to the <em>zōhr</em>. At <em>padāiš</em>, one further step and he should bring homage to the <em>zōhr</em>. At <em>yā frasrūtā īžaiiā̊</em>, he has make one step further 
            and to go to the place of the <em>ābardān</em>. He has to recite six times <em>pari.jasāi</em> (?) and he has to make three steps from the left side (of the <em>zōtgāh</em>), (starting) 
            at the (standard) position of the upper end of the <em>barsom</em>."</ab>
         <ab>Y64.5 Var. b (mss. 40, 2030, 2106):</ab>
         <ab class="ab_indent">
            barsom ul stānišn be gāh ī frabardārān šawišn mat̰. vā̊. bē kunišn pad ruwān ō ī bun ī ātaxš gāh tā <em>haiϑiiāuuarəštąm</em>. gōwišn <em>mat̰ vā̊</em> gām-ē frāz nihišn namāz ō 
            zōhr barišn <em>padāiš yā̊</em> gām-ē <em>frasrūtā īžaiiā̊</em> gām-ē frāz nihišn be ō ī gāh ī abardān <em>pairi.jasāi</em> šaš gōwišn u-š sē gām az kustag ī hōy pad sar ī barsom
            bē āyišn čē paydāg kū ka andar zōt gāh bē gōwēd ēzišn dēwēzagīh nē pēš ud nē pas ī gām ka-z abēr kučak ēč šāyēd </ab>  
         <ab class="ab_indent">
            "He has to take the <em>barsom</em> and go to the place of the <em>frabardārān</em>. He has to begin the recitation of <em>mat̰ vā̊</em> and recite until <em>haiϑiiāuuarəštąm</em> 
            with his mind put towards the fire. At <em>mat̰ vā̊</em>, he has to make a stept and bring <em>namāz</em> to the <em>zōhr</em>. At <em>padāiš yā̊</em>, one further step.
            At <em>frasrūtā īžaiiā̊</em>, he has to make a step towards the place of the <em>abardān</em>. He has to recite the six times <em>pari.jasāi</em> (?) and he has to make three
            steps on the left side (of the <em>zōtgāh</em>) (starting) at the (standard) position of the upper end of the <em>barsom</em>, since it is declared that, when he recites (these stanzas) 
            in the <em>zōtgāh</em>, the liturgy is <em>dēw</em>-worship. Not a step before or a step later. Even if it is a small (step), it is not valid."</ab>
         <ab>Y64.5 Var. c (ms. 5):</ab>
         <ab class="ab_indent">
            barsom az māhrōy ul stānišn <em>mat̰ vā̊</em> gām-ē abar kunišn <em>padāiš yā̊</em> gām-ē abar kunišn <em>frasrūtā īžaiiā̊</em> gām-ē abar kunišn <em>pairi.jasāi</em>. ...</ab>
         <ab class="ab_indent">
            "He has to take the <em>barsom</em> from the <em>māhrōy</em>. At <em>mat̰ vā̊</em>, he has to take an step. At <em>padāiš yā̊</em>, he has to take an step. At  
            <em>frasrūtā īžaiiā̊</em>, he has to take an step (and continue with) <em>pairi.jasāi</em>. ..."</ab> 
      <ab>Cf. Dk9.43.7 (DkM866.23):</ab>
      <ab class="ab_indent">
         <em>abar čim ī gām sē az zōtgāh abastāg gōwišnīh frāz āmad ī zōt pas az yašt pad ātaxš sar
            pad franābišn ō āb zōhr-barišnīh ul uzīdan ī amahrspandān hamē hanjaman ī hampursagīh ī
            zardušt sar pad 3 gām az zamīg ō xwaršēd-pāyag pad humad ud hūxt ud huwaršt </em>
      </ab>
      <ab class="ab_indent">About the reason why the zōt goes three steps away from the <em>zōtgāh</em> while
         saying the Avestan text after the end of the yašt for the fire and the introduction to the
         offering of <em>zōhr</em> to the water ; (the reason) is the moving of the Amahrspandān after the
         end of each meeting of Zardušt (with them) through three steps, from the earth to the sun
         station through humad, hūxt and huwaršt</ab>
      </Nerangs>
      
      <Quotations id="ritualQuotations">
         <ab>N52.9:</ab>
         <ab class="ab_indent">
            tā ō ī <em>ẏāiš azāθā mahmāi x́iiātā auuaŋᵛhē mat̰ vā̊ padāiš ẏā frasrūtā īzaiiā̊ pairi.jasāi</em> šaš gōwišn u-š sē gām az kust ī hōy pad sar ī barsom be āyišn</ab>
         <ab class="ab_indent">
            "He has to recite the six (stanzas) including <em>ẏāiš azāθā mahmāi x́iiātā auuaŋᵛhē mat̰ vā̊ padāiš ẏā frasrūtā īzaiiā̊ pairi.jasāi</em> and he has to advance three stpes on the left 
            side, (starting) at the (standard) position of the upper end of the <em>barsom</em>."</ab>
      </Quotations>
   </Ritual>
   <translation>
      <include type="CAB" corresp="CABTrY64.5"/>
      <include type="W" corresp="WTrY64.4"/>
      <include type="K" corresp="KTrY64.4"/>
      <include type="D" corresp="DTrY64.4"/>
   </translation>
</text>