<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<media_library>

    <media>
        <id>2109_urvis</id>
        <name>Name or description comes here</name>
        <type>img</type>
        <link>cab_rituals/nerang/nerang_pictures/2109_urwis.jpg</link>
    </media>

    <media>
        <id>5020_urvis</id>
        <name>Name or description comes here</name>
        <type>img</type>
        <link>cab_rituals/nerang/nerang_pictures/5020_urwis.jpg</link>
    </media>
    
     <media>
        <id>Yasna0_1</id>
        <name>Y0.1. The zōt recite an Aṣ̌əm Vohu before entering the yazišngāh. A Zoroastrian Ritual: The Yasna. 1983. Produced and directed by James W. Boyd and William R. Darrow. Cut for CAB by A. Cantera</name>
        <type>vid</type>
        <link>https://www.youtube.com/embed/Yx8Bbu9ZSPE</link>
    </media>
    
    <media>
        <id>Yasna0_2</id>
        <name>Y0.2. Washing of the hands. A Zoroastrian Ritual: The Yasna. 1983. Produced and directed by James W. Boyd and William R. Darrow. Cut for CAB by A. Cantera</name>
        <type>vid</type>
        <link>https://www.youtube.com/embed/ciuxl1LPY3M</link>
    </media>
    
    <media>
        <id>Yasna0_4</id>
        <name>Y0.4. Washing of the fire altar. A Zoroastrian Ritual: The Yasna. 1983. Produced and directed by James W. Boyd and William R. Darrow. Cut for CAB by A. Cantera</name>
        <type>vid</type>
        <link>https://www.youtube.com/embed/-x-SNwyrpoo</link>
    </media>
     <media>
        <id>Yasna0_5</id>
        <name>Y0.5. The zōt entering the zōtgāh. A Zoroastrian Ritual: The Yasna. 1983. Produced and directed by James W. Boyd and William R. Darrow. Cut for CAB by A. Cantera</name>
        <type>vid</type>
        <link>https://www.youtube.com/embed/efMbnIdXvJs</link>
    </media>
    <media>
        <id>Yasna0_12</id>
        <name>Y0.11-14. Laying down and takin the barsom. A Zoroastrian Ritual: The Yasna. 1983. Produced and directed by James W. Boyd and William R. Darrow. Cut for CAB by A. Cantera</name>
        <type>vid</type>
        <link>https://www.youtube.com/embed/A7HVlEYGIm8</link>
    </media>
    <media>
        <id>Yasna7_29</id>
        <name>Y7.29. The rāspīg brings bōy to the fire. A Zoroastrian Ritual: The Yasna. 1983. Produced and directed by James W. Boyd and William R. Darrow. Cut for CAB by A. Cantera</name>
        <type>vid</type>
        <link>https://www.youtube.com/embed/gU0hcVbKoYM</link>
    </media>
    <media>
        <id>Yasna7_29</id>
        <name>Y7.29. The rāspīg brings bōy to the fire. A Zoroastrian Ritual: The Yasna. 1983. Produced and directed by James W. Boyd and William R. Darrow.Cut for CAB by A. Cantera</name>
        <type>vid</type>
        <link>https://www.youtube.com/embed/gU0hcVbKoYM</link>
    </media>
    
    <media>
        <id>Yasna8_6</id>
        <name>Y8.6. Partaking of the Drōn. A Zoroastrian Ritual: The Yasna. 1983. Produced and directed by James W. Boyd and William R. Darrow.Cut for CAB by A. Cantera</name>
        <type>vid</type>
        <link>https://www.youtube.com/embed/86biSSXvx60</link>
    </media>
    
    <media>
        <id>Yasna11_9</id>
        <name>Y11.9. Offering of the parāhōm to the barsom. A Zoroastrian Ritual: The Yasna. 1983. Produced and directed by James W. Boyd and William R. Darrow.Cut for CAB by A. Cantera</name>
        <type>vid</type>
        <link>https://www.youtube.com/embed/ScfH3_dLER0</link>
    </media>
    
    <media>
    <id>Yasna11_10</id>
        <name>Y11.10. Handling of the parāhōm to the zōt. A Zoroastrian Ritual: The Yasna. 1983. Produced and directed by James W. Boyd and William R. Darrow.Cut for CAB by A. Cantera</name>
        <type>vid</type>
        <link>https://www.youtube.com/embed/vnhSbtHJ_Pw</link>
    </media>
    
    <media>
    <id>Yasna11_11</id>
        <name>Y11.11. Drinking of the parāhōm. A Zoroastrian Ritual: The Yasna. 1983. Produced and directed by James W. Boyd and William R. Darrow.Cut for CAB by A. Cantera</name>
        <type>vid</type>
        <link>https://www.youtube.com/embed/vnhSbtHJ_Pw</link>
    </media>
    
     <media>
    <id>Yasna13_9</id>
        <name>Y13.9. Tying of the barsom to the māhrōy. A Zoroastrian Ritual: The Yasna. 1983. Produced and directed by James W. Boyd and William R. Darrow.Cut for CAB by A. Cantera</name>
        <type>vid</type>
        <link>https://www.youtube.com/embed/UKRo69wMZyQ</link>
    </media>
    
      <media>
    <id>Yasna15_1</id>
        <name>Y15.1. Division of the ǰīwām. A Zoroastrian Ritual: The Yasna. 1983. Produced and directed by James W. Boyd and William R. Darrow.Cut for CAB by A. Cantera</name>
        <type>vid</type>
        <link>https://www.youtube.com/embed/axdxb2T6T2k</link>
    </media>
    
      <media>
    <id>Yasna15_2</id>
        <name>Y15.2. Moiistening of the barsom. A Zoroastrian Ritual: The Yasna. 1983. Produced and directed by James W. Boyd and William R. Darrow.Cut for CAB by A. Cantera</name>
        <type>vid</type>
        <link>https://www.youtube.com/embed/axdxb2T6T2k</link>
    </media>
    
     <media>
    <id>Yasna24_1</id>
        <name>Y23.0 and 24.1. Raising of the hōm and ǰīwām. A Zoroastrian Ritual: The Yasna. 1983. Produced and directed by James W. Boyd and William R. Darrow.Cut for CAB by A. Cantera</name>
        <type>vid</type>
        <link>https://www.youtube.com/embed/ReFPoa1DxB4</link>
    </media>
    
     <media>
    <id>Yasna25_1</id>
        <name>Y25.1. Putting hōm, urwarām, ǰīwām and water into the hāwan. A Zoroastrian Ritual: The Yasna. 1983. Produced and directed by James W. Boyd and William R. Darrow.Cut for CAB by A. Cantera</name>
        <type>vid</type>
        <link>https://www.youtube.com/embed/T-axyJAFKlk</link>
    </media>
    
     <media>
    <id>Yasna27_1</id>
        <name>Y27.1.Putting the hāwan in contact with the urwēs. A Zoroastrian Ritual: The Yasna. 1983. Produced and directed by James W. Boyd and William R. Darrow.Cut for CAB by A. Cantera</name>
        <type>vid</type>
        <link>https://www.youtube.com/embed/_yGHiDtS8Vo</link>
    </media>
    
      <media>
    <id>Yasna27_3</id>
        <name>Y27.3.Striking of the hāwan at Ahuna Vairiia. A Zoroastrian Ritual: The Yasna. 1983. Produced and directed by James W. Boyd and William R. Darrow.Cut for CAB by A. Cantera</name>
        <type>vid</type>
        <link>https://www.youtube.com/embed/ikTu-jv9YcI</link>
    </media>
    
      <media>
    <id>Yasna27_4</id>
        <name>Y27.4.Striking of the hāwan at Y34.15. A Zoroastrian Ritual: The Yasna. 1983. Produced and directed by James W. Boyd and William R. Darrow.Cut for CAB by A. Cantera</name>
        <type>vid</type>
        <link>https://www.youtube.com/embed/7Nj6N8AyZks</link>
    </media>
    
    <media>
    <id>Yasna27_5</id>
        <name>Y27.5.Striking of the hāwan at the Airiiman Išiia. A Zoroastrian Ritual: The Yasna. 1983. Produced and directed by James W. Boyd and William R. Darrow.Cut for CAB by A. Cantera</name>
        <type>vid</type>
        <link>https://www.youtube.com/embed/GL_VlEFOxtk</link>
    </media>
    
       <media>
    <id>Yasna27_6</id>
        <name>Y27.6.Pouring zōhr into the hāwan. A Zoroastrian Ritual: The Yasna. 1983. Produced and directed by James W. Boyd and William R. Darrow.Cut for CAB by A. Cantera</name>
        <type>vid</type>
        <link>https://www.youtube.com/embed/oiSzJprpXYI</link>
    </media>
    
         <media>
    <id>Yasna27_6</id>
        <name>Y27.6.Pouring zōhr into the hāwan. A Zoroastrian Ritual: The Yasna. 1983. Produced and directed by James W. Boyd and William R. Darrow.Cut for CAB by A. Cantera</name>
        <type>vid</type>
        <link>https://www.youtube.com/embed/oiSzJprpXYI</link>
    </media>
    
       <media>
    <id>Yasna27_7</id>
        <name>Y27.7.Turning the hāwan over the barsom. A Zoroastrian Ritual: The Yasna. 1983. Produced and directed by James W. Boyd and William R. Darrow.Cut for CAB by A. Cantera</name>
        <type>vid</type>
        <link>https://www.youtube.com/embed/-4i7Wxv6ZqE</link>
    </media>
    
     <media>
    <id>Yasna27_8</id>
        <name>Y27.8.Taking of the hōm and offering to the barsom. A Zoroastrian Ritual: The Yasna. 1983. Produced and directed by James W. Boyd and William R. Darrow.Cut for CAB by A. Cantera</name>
        <type>vid</type>
        <link>https://www.youtube.com/embed/9fgJSoSwPwg4i7Wxv6ZqE</link>
    </media>
    
     <media>
    <id>Yasna27_9</id>
        <name>Y27.9.Further pounding of the hōm. A Zoroastrian Ritual: The Yasna. 1983. Produced and directed by James W. Boyd and William R. Darrow.Cut for CAB by A. Cantera</name>
        <type>vid</type>
        <link>https://www.youtube.com/embed/E9hm7iWJgl4</link>
        <notes>According to the Iranian manuscripts, at this passage he pour the hōm on the hōm-filter and squeeze it with the finger several times. This action happens in the video, as usual in the Indian practice,at the recitation of the next stanza (Y27.10)</notes>
        <name_person>A. Cantera</name_person>
    </media>
    
      <media>
    <id>Yasna27_10</id>
        <name>Y27.10.Filtering of the hōm. A Zoroastrian Ritual: The Yasna. 1983. Produced and directed by James W. Boyd and William R. Darrow.Cut for CAB by A. Cantera</name>
        <type>vid</type>
        <link>https://www.youtube.com/embed/bOgmpX5jB40</link>
        <notes>The actions performed here are performed according to the Iranian manuscript at the previos stanza, at Y27.9. Note that F. Kotwal recites the abbreviated. First, the complete yə̄. səuuištō, once and then just the first two words folloed by the indication <em>se bār</em> "three times" and the last words of the stanza. </notes>
        <name_person>A. Cantera</name_person>
    </media>
    
      <media>
    <id>Yasna27_11</id>
        <name>Y27.11-Y28.1.Further pounding of the hōm. A Zoroastrian Ritual: The Yasna. 1983. Produced and directed by James W. Boyd and William R. Darrow.Cut for CAB by A. Cantera</name>
        <type>vid</type>
        <link>https://www.youtube.com/embed/EuV_zG-bJjM</link>
        <notes>F. Kotwal recite the text abbreviated. He recites Y27.11a 1-3 (us.moi. uzārəšuuā.) and then the final words of the Y27.13 (us.moi. uzārəšuuā.). Tree Aṣ̌əm Vohū, but only the words aṣ̌əm vohū are recited. The abbreviation implies at the same time that the actions that according tot he Iranian manuscripts are performed along Y27.11-13 extends now until the Frauuarāne of Y28. </notes>
        <name_person>A. Cantera</name_person>
    </media>
    
      <media>
    <id>Yasna34_4</id>
        <name>Y34.4 ff. Offering of the hōm residue to the fire and bringing of the hōm to the left hand of the zōt. A Zoroastrian Ritual: The Yasna. 1983. Produced and directed by James W. Boyd and William R. Darrow.Cut for CAB by A. Cantera</name>
        <type>vid</type>
        <link>https://www.youtube.com/embed/EiDwiiIkhnA</link>
        <notes>The actions performed according tot he Iranian manuscripts during the recitation of Y33.11 are performed in Indian practice at two different moments: the last squeezing and then the transfer of the pressed hōm to the left of the zōt and its preservation on the zōhrdān, covered by the ǰīwdān. In India, whereas the filtering is also done at the end of Y33.11, the bringing of the hōm to the left hand of the zōt and its covering with the ǰīwdān takes place durin the recitation of Y34.4-5.</notes>
        <name_person>A. Cantera</name_person>
        
    </media>
    
       <media>
    <id>Yasna62_1</id>
        <name>Y61.6-62.2 ff. Beginning of the Ātaxš Niyāyišn. A Zoroastrian Ritual: The Yasna. 1983. Produced and directed by James W. Boyd and William R. Darrow.Cut for CAB by A. Cantera</name>
        <type>vid</type>
        <link>https://www.youtube.com/embed/lqMsnckgOnM</link>
        
        <name_person>A. Cantera</name_person>
        
    </media>
    
      <media>
    <id>Yasna64_4_8</id>
        <name>Y64.4-8. Circumambullation of the barsom. A Zoroastrian Ritual: The Yasna. 1983. Produced and directed by James W. Boyd and William R. Darrow.Cut for CAB by A. Cantera</name>
        <type>vid</type>
        <link>https://www.youtube.com/embed/KKnuzagtfuA</link>
        <notes>According to the Iranian manuscripts, the priest goes to the place of the frabardārān in three steps and from there to the place of the ābardān. There, he will make an offering to the fire at Y64.8. Then he returs to the palce of the zōt. This action is substituted in the Indian practice by tipping the barsom to the east side.</notes>
        <name_person>A. Cantera</name_person>
        
        <name_person>A. Cantera</name_person>
        
    </media>
    
    
   
    
    
</media_library>