<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div n="YR">
    <div n="1">
        <ab xml:id="CABTrYR1.3" corresp="YR1.3">
            I announce and I arrange (a sacrifice) for the junctures of the order concerning the parts of the day,
            for the orderly juncture of the order of the noonday;
            I announce and I arrange (a sacrifice)
            for the orderly juncture of the order, that fosters the cattle and of the tribe;
            I announce and I arrange (a sacrifice)
            for Aṣ̌a Vahišta and the Fire of Ahura Mazdā.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrYR1.11" corresp="YR1.11">
        I announce and I arrange (a sacrifice) for all those benefactors receiving sacrifice, mental and material ones,             who are worthy of sacrifice and praise according to the best order.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrYR1.12" corresp="YR1.12">
            Oh, orderly juncture of the order of the lunch-time.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrYR1.14" corresp="YR1.14">
        If I was hostile to (all of) you,
        either with the mind or with a word or with an action,
        either willingly or unwillingly;
        if I excluded you from this, the sacrifice and the praise, I make for you the preliminary praise, I announce you (to         the sacrifice and the praise).
        </ab>
    </div>
    <div n="2">
        <ab xml:id="CABTrYR2.3" corresp="YR2.3">
        With this libation and this <em>barsom</em> I bring with the sacrifice the junctures of the order concerning the            parts of the day;
        I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the order of the noonday;
        I bring with the sacrifice the orderly the orderly juncture of the order, that fosters the cattle and of the tribe;
        With this libation and this <em>barsom</em> I bring with the sacrifice Aṣ̌a Vahišta and the Fire, son of Ahura Mazdā.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrYR2.11" corresp="YR2.11">
        With this libation and this <em>barsom</em> I bring with the sacrifice all the orderly (beings) worthy of sacrifice;
        in the middle of the juncture of the noonday and in the middle of the juncture of the tribe.
        </ab>
        </div>
        <div n="3">
        <ab xml:id="CABTrYR3.1" corresp="YR3.1">
        With the <em>barsom</em> that has been presented, accompanying the libation, at the time of <em>Hāuuani</em>, I             bring with the sacrifice the (edible) offering as nourishment of Hauruuatāt and Amərətatāt, of the generous cow, for         the satisfaction of Ahura Mazda, of the Aməṣ̌a Spəṇta; for the satisfaction of Sraōša, of Aṣ̌i's kin, who holds the         reward, resilient, who increases the creation.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrYR3.4" corresp="YR3.4">
        I bring with the sacrifice this <em>barsom</em> together with the libation, together with the girdle and spread             forward in the proper way, for the satisfaction of the Aməṣ̌a Spəṇta;
        I bring with the sacrifice both words well-thought, well-said, well-perfomed;
        And I bring with the sacrifice the hearing of the Gāϑās;
        I birng with the sacrifice the well-perfomed sacred words;
        I bring with the sacrifice this acquisition of the (other) existence, the acquistion of the Order and the satisfacti         on of the <em>ratu</em>, for the satisfaction of those supporters of the order worthy of sacrifice, the material           and the mental ones; for the satisfaction of my own soul.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrYR3.5" corresp="YR3.5">
         I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings) for the junctures of the order concerning the parts of the day,
         for the orderly juncture of the order and of the lunch-time,
        I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings)
        for the orderly juncture of the order, that increases the cattle and of the tribe,
        I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings)
        of Aṣ̌a Vahišta and the Fire, son of Ahura Mazda.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrYR3.15" corresp="YR3.15">
        I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings) for all those benefactors receiving sacrifice, mental and material one,         who are worthy of sacrifice and praise according to the best order.</ab>
    </div>
    <div n="4">
        <ab xml:id="CABTrYR4.1" corresp="YR4.1">
            These (thoughts) well thought, (these words) well said, (these actions) well performed.
            These <em>haōma</em>, (these) <em>miiazda</em>, (these) <em>zaōϑrā</em>, this <em>barəsman</em> spread forward in the proper way, (this) generous cow,
            Hauruuatāta and Amərətāta, (this) generous cow, (this) <em>haōma</em>, this <em>parahaōma</em>, these <em>aēsma</em>,
            (this) <em>baōiδi</em>.
            This acquisition of the (other) existence, (this) acquisition of the Order and (this) satisfaction of the <em>ratu</em>, 
            (this) hearing of the Gāϑās, (this) well performed sacred words, (all of them) we hand over (them) and we dedicate (them).</ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrYR4.3" corresp="YR4.3">
            We dedicate these: these (thoughts) well thought, (these words) well said, (these actions) well performed.
            These <em>haōma</em>, (these) <em>miiazda</em>, (these) <em>zaōϑrā</em>, this <em>barəsman</em> spread forward in the proper way, (this) generous cow,
            Hauruuatāta and Amərətāta, (this) generous cow, (this) <em>haōma</em>, this <em>parahaōma</em>, these <em>aēsma</em>,
            (this) <em>baōiδi</em>.
            This acquisition of the (other) existence, (this) acquisition of the Order and (this) satisfaction of the <em>ratu</em>, 
            (this) hearing of the Gāϑās, (this) well performed sacred words, (all of them) we hand over (them) and we dedicate (them).</ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrYR4.8" corresp="YR4.8">
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification for the junctures of the order concerning the parts of the day,
            for the orderly juncture of the order and of the lunch-time,
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification
            for the orderly juncture of the order, that fosters the cattle and of the tribe,
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification
            of Aṣ̌a Vahišta and the Fire, son of Ahura Mazda.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrYR4.17" corresp="YR4.17">
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification for all those benefactors receiving sacrifice, mental and material one,         
            who are worthy of sacrifice and praise according to the best order.
            We worship the Aməṣ̌a Spəṇta, of good command, generous.
        </ab>
    </div>
    <div n="6">
        <ab xml:id="CABTrYR6.2" corresp="YR4.2">
            We worship the junctures of the order concerning the parts of the day;
            we worship the orderly juncture of the order of the noonday;
            we worship the orderly juncture of the order, that fosters the cattle and of the tribe;
            We worship Aṣ̌a Vahišta and the Fire, son of Ahura Mazdā.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrYR6.12" corresp="YR4.12">
            We worship all the orderly (beings) worthy of sacrifice
            in the middle of the lunch-time juncture, in the middle of the junture of the clan, that fosters the cattle.
        </ab>
    </div>
    <div n="7">
        <ab xml:id="CABTrYR7.5" corresp="YR7.5">
            I place properly this <em>barəsman</em> together with the <em>zaōϑrā</em>, together with the girdle and spread forward in the proper way, 
            for the satisfaction of the Aməṣ̌a Spəṇta; 
            I place properly both words well-thought, well-said, well-perfomed; 
            and I place properly the hearing of the Gāϑās; 
            I place properly the well-perfomed sacred words; 
            I place properly this acquisition of the (other) existence, the acquistion of the Order and the satisfaction of the <em>ratus</em>, 
            for the satisfaction of those supporters of the Order worthy of sacrifice, the material and the mental ones; for the satisfaction of my own soul.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY7.6" corresp="Y7.6">
            I place properly (these offerings) for the orderly junctures of the Order concerning the parts of the day, for the orderly juncture of the Order of the lunch-time, 
            I place properly (these offerings) for the orderly juncture of the Order, that increases the cattle and of the tribe, 
            I place properly (these offerings) for Aṣ̌a Vahišta and the Fire, son of Ahura Mazda.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY7.17" corresp="Y7.17">
            I place properly (these offerings) for all those benefactors receiving sacrifice, mental and material ones, who are worthy of sacrifice and praise according to the best order.
        </ab>
    </div>
</div>