<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div n="Y">
    <div n="1">
        <ab xml:id="CABTrVrS1.9" corresp="VrS1.9">
            I announce and I arrange (a sacrifice) for the junctures of the order, holding the order, oh junctures of the mental (beings), oh junctures of the material (beings), oh junctures of the accuatic (animals), oh junctures of the terrestrial (animals), oh junctures of aerial (animals), oh junctures of the wild (animals), oh junctures of the domesticated (animals) .
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrVrS1.10" corresp="VrS1.10">
            I announce and I arrange (a sacrifice) for the seasonal junctures of the order; for the orderly juncture of the order of the milky mid-spring;
            I announce and I arrange (a sacrifice) for the orderly juncture of the order of the mid-summer, when the fodder is harvested;
            I announce and I arrange (a sacrifice) for the orderly juncture of the order of the time when the grain is sown;
            I announce and I arrange (a sacrifice) for the orderly juncture of the order of the time when (the flocks) are gathered and stabled and the rams are released;
            I announce and I arrange (a sacrifice) for the orderly juncture of the order of the middle of the cold season;
            I announce and I arrange (a sacrifice) for the orderly juncture of the order of <em>hamaspaϑmaēdaya</em>-festival, when the performance that produces Order takes place.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrVrS1.11" corresp="VrS1.11">
            I announce and I arrange (the sacrifice) of the orderly juncture of the order of the time of the birth of the living-beings, so that the women in labour give birth;        
            I announce and I arrange (the sacrifice) of the orderly juncture of the order of the collected Staōta Yesńiia well-sacrificed in a solemn performance; 
            I announce and I arrange (the sacrifice) of the collected Staōta Yesńiia well-sacrificed in a solemn performance as oblations of the order for the male and female holders of the order.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrVrS1.12" corresp="VrS1.12">
            I announce and I arrange (the sacrifice) of the orderly juncture of the order and  of the year, holding the order; (the sacrifice) of the orderly juncture of the order of the <em>Ahuna Vairiia</em> recitation.        
            I announce and I arrange (the sacrifice) of the orderly juncture of the order of the Best Order (<em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū</em>).
            I announce and I arrange (the sacrifice) of the the orderly juncture of the order <em>Yeŋ́hē.Hātā</em>,  well-sacrificed in a solemn performance.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrVrS1.13" corresp="VrS1.13">
            I announce and I arrange (the sacrifice) of the orderly juncture of the order of the Ahunauuaiti Gāϑā.        
            I announce and I arrange (the sacrifice) of the orderly juncture of the order of the (text of the) women created by Mazdā of many types of hordes of men. 
            I announce and I arrange (the sacrifice) of the orderly juncture of the order of the (text) containing <em>ahu</em> and <em>ratu</em>.        
            I announce and I arrange (the sacrifice) of the orderly juncture of the order of the Yasna Haptaŋhāiti.        
            I announce and I arrange (the sacrifice) of the orderly juncture of the order of the (text of the) moisturizing Anāhita waters.   
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrVrS1.14" corresp="VrS1.14">
            I announce and I arrange (the sacrifice) of the orderly juncture of the order of the Uštauuaiti Gāϑā.
            I announce and I arrange (the sacrifice) of the orderly juncture of the order of the (text of the) mountains that grant the multiple comforts of the Order, created by Mazdā.
            I announce and I arrange (the sacrifice) of the orderly juncture of the order of the Spəṇtā.Maińiiū Gāϑā.
            I announce and I arrange (the sacrifice) of the orderly juncture of the order of the (text of) Vərəϑraγna created by Ahura and the victorious Uparatāt.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrVrS1.15" corresp="VrS1.15">
            I announce and I arrange (the sacrifice) of the orderly juncture of the order of the Vohuxšaϑrā Gāϑā.
            I announce and I arrange (the sacrifice) of the orderly juncture of the order of Miϑra, of wide pasturelandas and of Rāman, of good fodder.
            I announce and I arrange (the sacrifice) of the orderly juncture of the order of the Vahištōištī Gāϑā.
            I announce and I arrange (the sacrifice) of the orderly juncture of the order of the good Daɱa Āfriti, the expert supporter of the order and the strong and powerful Dāmōiš Upamana, worthy of sacrifice.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrVrS1.16" corresp="VrS1.16">
            I announce and I arrange (the sacrifice) of the orderly juncture of the order of the Airiiaman Iš́iia.
            I announce and I arrange (the sacrifice) of the orderly juncture of the order of the Fšūšō Mąϑra.
            I announce and I arrange (the sacrifice) of the orderly juncture of the order of the complementary text of the Great Articulation.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrVrS1.17" corresp="VrS1.17">
            I announce and I arrange (the sacrifice) of the orderly juncture of the order of the interview with Ahura, of the teaching of Ahura, (the juncture) of national rang of Ahura and of the rang of the (realm) governed by the highest Zaraϑuštra of Ahura.
            I announce and I arrange (the sacrifice) of the (text of) dwelling rich in fodder,  of the (text of the) provider of fodder to the generous cow, and of the (text of the) man who holds the order and nourishes the cows.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrVrS1.26" corresp="VrS1.26">
            I announce and I arrange (the sacrifice) of the Ratu (Juncture) Bərəzaṇt, which (is made) of junctures of the order of the days, of the parts of the day, of the months, of the seasons, of the years, that are the junctures of the order,
            (and) of the juncture of the mid-spring.  
        </ab>
    </div>
    <div n="1">
        <ab xml:id="CABTrVrS2.9" corresp="VrS2.9">
        With this libation and this <em>barsom</em> I bring with the sacrifice the mental (beings) junctures;
        I bring with the sacrifice the material (beings) junctures;
        I bring with the sacrifice the accuatic (animals) junctures;
        I bring with the sacrifice the terrestial (animals) junctures;
        I bring with the sacrifice the aerial (animals) junctures;
        I bring with the sacrifice the wild (animals) junctures;
        I bring with the sacrifice the domesticated (animals) junctures.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrVrS2.10" corresp="VrS2.10">
        With this libation and this <em>barsom</em> I bring with the sacrifice the orderly seasonal junctures of the order;
        I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the order of the milky mid-spring;
        With this libation and this <em>barsom</em> I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the order of the mid-summer, when the fodder is harvested;
        With this libation and this <em>barsom</em> I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the order of the time when the grain is sown;
        With this libation and this <em>barsom</em> I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the order of the time when (the flocks) are gathered and stabled and the rams are released;
        With this libation and this <em>barsom</em> I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the order of the middle of the cold season;
        With this libation and this <em>barsom</em> I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the order of <em>hamaspaϑmaēdaya</em>-festival, when the performance that produces Order takes place.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrVrS2.11" corresp="VrS2.11">
        With this libation and this <em>barsom</em> I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the order of the time of the birth of the living-beings, so that the women in labour give birth.
        With this libation and this <em>barsom</em> I bring with the sacrifice for you all the junctures,
        that Ahura Mazdā told Zaraϑuštra (and are) worthy of sacrifice and praise according to the best order.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrVrS2.12" corresp="VrS2.12">
        With this libation and this <em>barsom</em> I bring you with the sacrifice, Ahura Mazdā, as mental existence and juncture of the mental beings and the mental existence.
        With this libation and this <em>barsom</em> I bring you with the sacrifice, Spitama Zaraϑuštra, as material existence and junctureof the material beings and the material existence.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrVrS2.13" corresp="VrS2.13">
        With this libation and this <em>barsom</em> I bring with the sacrifice the reciter of the junctures, who is the man supporter of the order keeping the thought well-thought, the word well-said, the action well-performed; who (are those) getting the sacred word bigger;
        with whose deeds, with the order, multiply the living-beings.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrVrS2.14" corresp="VrS2.14">
        With this libation and this <em>barsom</em> I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the order and of the year, holding the order; 
        I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the order of the <em>Ahuna Vairiia</em> recitation.                
        With this libation and this <em>barsom</em> I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the order of the Best Order (<em>Aṣ̌əm Vohū</em>).
        With this libation and this <em>barsom</em> I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the order <em>Yeŋ́hē.Hātā</em>,  well-sacrificed in a solemn performance.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrVrS2.15" corresp="VrS2.15">
        With this libation and this <em>barsom</em> I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the order of the Ahunauuaiti Gāϑā.        
        I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the order of the (text of the) women, well-proportioned, of good fathers, well grown. 
        With this libation and this <em>barsom</em> I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the order of the (text) containing <em>ahu</em> and <em>ratu</em>.
        With this libation and this <em>barsom</em> I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the order of the Yasna Haptaŋhāiti.        
        I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the order of the (text of the) moisturizing Anāhita waters. 
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrVrS2.16" corresp="VrS2.16">
        With this libation and this <em>barsom</em> I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the order of the Uštauuaiti Gāϑā.
        With this libation and this <em>barsom</em> I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the order of the (text of the) mountains that grant the multiple comforts of the Order, created by Mazdā.
       With this libation and this <em>barsom</em> I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the order of the Spəṇtā.Maińiiū Gāϑā.
        With this libation and this <em>barsom</em> I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the order of the (text of) Vərəϑraγna created by Ahura; I bring with the sacrifice the (text of the) victorious Uparatāt.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrVrS2.17" corresp="VrS2.17">
        With this libation and this <em>barsom</em> I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the order of the Vohuxšaϑrā Gāϑā.
        I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the order of Miϑra, of wide pasturelandas and of Rāman, of good fodder.
        With this libation and this <em>barsom</em> I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the order of the Vahištōištī Gāϑā.
        I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the order of the good Daɱa Āfriti; 
        I bring with the sacrifice the expert supporter of the order;
        I bring with the sacrifice the strong and powerful Dāmōiš Upamana, worthy of sacrifice.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrVrS2.18" corresp="VrS2.18">
        With this libation and this <em>barsom</em> I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the order of the Airiiaman Iš́iia.
        With this libation and this <em>barsom</em> I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the order of the Fšūšō Mąϑra.
        With this libation and this <em>barsom</em> I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the order of the complementary text of the Great Articulation.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrVrS2.19" corresp="VrS2.19">
        With this libation and this <em>barsom</em> I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the order of the interview with Ahura;
        I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the order of the teaching of Ahura.
        With this libation and this <em>barsom</em> I bring with the sacrifice the (text of) dwellings rich in fodder;
        I bring with the sacrifice the (text of the) provider of fodder to the generous cow; 
        I bring with the sacrifice the (text of the) man who holds the order and nourishes the cows.
        </ab>
    </div>
    <div n="3">
    <ab xml:id="CABTrVrS3.20" corresp="VrS3.20">
    I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings) of the Ratu (Juncture) Bərəzaṇt, which (is made) of junctures of the order of the days, of the parts of the day, of the months, of the seasons, of the years, that are the junctures of the order,(and) of the juncture of the mid-spring.
    </ab>
    </div>
    <div n="4">
        <ab xml:id="CABTrVrS4.23" corresp="VrS4.23">
            We dedicate these of the Ratu (Juncture) Bərəzaṇt, which (is made) of junctures of the order of the days, of the parts of the day, of the months, of the seasons, of the years, that are the junctures of the order,(and) of the juncture of the mid-spring.
        </ab>
    </div>
    <div n="7">
        <ab xml:id="CABTrVrS7.21" corresp="VrS7.21">
            I place properly (these offerings) of the Ratu (Juncture) Bərəzaṇt, which (is made) of junctures of the order of the days, of the parts of the day, of the months, of the seasons, of the years, that are the junctures of the order, (and) of the juncture of the mid-spring.
        </ab> 
    </div>
    <div n="65">
        <ab xml:id="CABTrVrS65.33" corresp="VrS65.33">
            Thus, we worship indeed Ahura Mazdā,  who created the cow and the Order, 
            (who) created the (good) waters and the good plants, 
            (who) created the lights and the earth, as well as all the good things 
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrVrS65.34" corresp="VrS65.34">
            with his command, greatness and ability.
            We worship him indeed with the priority of the sacrifices,
            that are aside the cow.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrVrS65.35" corresp="VrS65.35">
            We worship him with his ahuric name, "beloved Mazdā", the most beneficial.
            We worship him with our bones and breathings.
            We worship him through the Frauuaṣ̌iš of the holders of the Order, the men and the women.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrVrS65.336" corresp="VrS65.36">
            We worship indeed Aṣ̌a Vahišta,
            that is the most beautiful, that is one Ameṣ̌a Spəṇta,
            that is holder of light, that is all the good things.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrVrS65.37" corresp="VrS65.37">
            We worship Vohu Mana and the good Xšaϑra,
            the good Daēnā, the good Fsəratu and the good Ārmaiti.
        </ab>
    </div>
</div>