<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div n="Y">
    <div n="1">
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY1.1" corresp="Y1.1">
            I announce and I arrange (a sacrifice) for the creator Ahura Mazdā, holder of wealth and <em>xᵛarənah</em>, the greatest, best and most beatiful, 
            the most solid, the richest in reasoning, the best-looking, who best reaches (the straight ways) in accordance with Order,
            with a good stake and broad support, 
            who has placed us (in the world) and has fashioned us and has fattened us, for him, the most beneficial state of mind. 
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY1.2" corresp="Y1.2">
            I announce and I arrange (a sacrifice) for the Vohu Manah, for Aṣ̌a Vahišta, for Xšaϑra Vairiia, for the beneficial Armaiti, for Hauruuatāt and Amərətatāt,
            for the Fashioner of the cow, for the Soul of the cow, for the Fire of Ahura Mazdā, the first one among the Aməṣ̌a Spəṇta to take up the (ritual) position.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY1.3" corresp="Y1.3">
            I announce and I arrange (a sacrifice) for the junctures of the Order concerning the parts of the day,
            for the orderly juncture of the Order and of the haōma-pressing time,
            I announce and I arrange (a sacrifice)
            for the orderly juncture of the Order, of the success <note anchored="true">"Success" (<em>sauuah-</em>) refers to the rise of the Sun as the succesful result of the performance of the sacrifice.</note> and of the clan.
            I announce and I arrange (a sacrifice)
            of Miϑra, of wide pasturelands, with thousend ears, with ten thousend eyes, worthy of a sacrifice in which his name is mentioned; of Rāman who has good fodder.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY1.4" corresp="Y1.4">
            I announce and I arrange (a sacrifice),
            for the orderly juncture of the Order and of the lunch-time,
            I announce and I arrange (a sacrifice)
            for the orderly juncture of the Order, that increases the cattle and of the tribe,
            I announce and I arrange (a sacrifice)
            of Aṣ̌a Vahišta and the Fire, son of Ahura Mazda.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY1.5" corresp="Y1.5">
            I announce and I arrange (a sacrifice),
            the orderly juncture of the Order and of the evening,
            for I announce and I arrange (a sacrifice)
            for the orderly juncture of the Order, that increases men and of the nation,
            I announce and I arrange (a sacrifice)
            of the great Ahura Apąm Napat and of the waters created by Mazdā.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY1.6" corresp="Y1.6">
            I announce and I arrange (a sacrifice),
            for the orderly juncture of the Order and of the time when the songs are heard (the night),
            I announce and I arrange (a sacrifice)
            for the orderly juncture of the Order, that increases everything leading to a good life and of the realm governed by the highst Zaraϑuštra,
            I announce and I arrange (a sacrifice)
            of the Frauuaṣ̌iš of the holders of the Order, of the Women giving birth hordes of men, of the good settlement for the whole year, of the well fashioned and well grown Assault, of the Breaking of the Obstacle created by Ahura and of the victorious Superiority.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY1.7" corresp="Y1.7">
            I announce and I arrange (a sacrifice),
            for the orderly juncture of the Order and of the dawn,
            I announce and I arrange (a sacrifice)
            for the orderly juncture of the Order, of the ritual perfomance and of the house,
            I announce and I arrange (a sacrifice)
            of Sraōša, kin of Aṣ̌i, carrying reward (<em>aṣ̌i</em>), breaking the obstacles, fostering the living beings; of Rašnu, the most righteous, and of Arštāt, that fosters and makes the living beings grow.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY1.8" corresp="Y1.8">
            I announce and I arrange (a sacrifice) for the monthly orderly junctures of the Order; for the orderly juncture of the Order of the interlunation.
            I announce and I arrange (a sacrifice) for the orderly juncture of the Order of the plenilunium and of the gibbous phase.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY1.9" corresp="Y1.9">
            I announce and I arrange (a sacrifice), for the seasonal junctures of the Order; for the orderly juncture of the Order of the mid-spring;
            I announce and I arrange (a sacrifice), for the orderly juncture of the Order of the mid-summer
            I announce and I arrange (a sacrifice), for the orderly juncture of the Order of the sowing time;
            I announce and I arrange (a sacrifice), for the orderly juncture of the Order of the transhumance, of the bridling and the admission of the rams;
            I announce and I arrange (a sacrifice), for the orderly juncture of the Order of the mid-year articulationr;
            I announce and I arrange (a sacrifice), for the orderly juncture of the Order of <em>hamaspaϑmaēdaya</em>;
            I announce and I arrange (a sacrifice), for the years as junctures of the Order.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY1.10" corresp="Y1.10">
            I announce and I arrange (the sacrifice) to all the junctures, that are the thirty three articulations of the Order that are the closest around <em>hāuuani</em>; that belong to the best order, that were announced by Mazdā (to Zaraϑuštra) and proclaimed by Zaraϑuštra (to mankind).
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY1.11" corresp="Y1.11">
            I announce and I arrange (the sacrifice) for both, Ahura and Miϑra, the great, unthreatened, holding the order; for the stars, creatures of Spəṇta Maińiiu;
            for Tištriia, the star bestower of wealth and <em>xᵛarənah</em>, for the Moon with the appearance of a cow, for the bright Sun, of swift horses, that is the eye of Ahura Mazdā, (and) Miϑra, the national lord of the nations.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY1.12" corresp="Y1.12">
            I announce and I arrange (the sacrifice)
            for Ahura Mazdā holder of wealth and <em>xᵛarənah</em>;
            I announce and I arrange (the sacrifice)
            for the Frauuaṣ̌iš of the holders of the Order.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY1.13" corresp="Y1.13">
            I announce and I arrange (a sacrifice) for you, the fire, oh son of Ahura Mazdā, with all the fires.
            I announce and I arrange (a sacrifice) for the good waters, of all the waters created by Mazdā and of all the plants created by Mazdā.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY1.14" corresp="Y1.14">
            I announce and I arrange (the sacrifice) of the beneficial mąϑra, holding the order, of enjoyable existence; of the law expelling the demons, of the law of Zaraϑuštra, of the long tranmission, of the good vision-soul proper of those performing sacrifices to Mazdā.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY1.15" corresp="Y1.15">
            I announce and I arrange (the sacrifice) of the mountain Ušidarəna created by Mazdā that grant the multiple comforts of the Order and of all the mountains that grant the multiple comforts of the Order, created by Mazdā.
            of the Kayanid <em>xᵛarənah</em> created by Mazdā and the unreachable <em>xᵛarənah</em> created by Mazdā.
            I announce and I arrange (the sacrifice) of the good Aṣ̌i, of the good Cisti, of the good Ərətī, of the good Rasąstāt, of the <em>xᵛarənah</em> created by Mazdā as (synonym of) success.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY1.16" corresp="Y1.16">
            I announce and I arrange (the sacrifice) of the good Daɱa Āfriti, the expert supporter of the Order and the strong and powerful Dāmōiš Upamana, worthy of sacrifice.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY1.17" corresp="Y1.17">
            I announce and I arrange (the sacrifice) of these places, dwellings, pasturelands, residences, ponds, waters, earth and plants, of this earth and that sky and the orderly wind, of the stars, the moon, the Sun and the Anaγra Raōcah, that are placed by themselves; and of all the orderly creations of Spənta Maińiiu and of the (she) orderly junctures of the Order.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY1.18" corresp="Y1.18">
            I announce and I arrange (the sacrifice) of the Ratu (Juncture) Bərəzaṇt, which (is made) of junctures of the Order of the days, of the parts of the day, of the months, of the seasons, of the years, that are the junctures of the Order,(and) of the juncture of the haōma-pressing time.           
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY1.19" corresp="Y1.19">
            I announce and I arrange (the sacrifice) of the Frauuaṣ̌iš of the suporters of the Order, of the Frauuaṣ̌iš  of the first teachers of the doctrine, who were strong and very victorious; of the Frauuaṣ̌iš of the closest relatives, for the Frauuaṣ̌i of my own soul.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY1.20" corresp="Y1.20">
            I announce and I arrange (a sacrifice) for all the junctures of the Order.
            I announce and I arrange (a sacrifice) for all those benefactors receiving sacrifice, mental and material ones, who are worthy of sacrifice and praise according to the best order.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY1.21" corresp="Y1.21">
            Oh, orderly juncture of the Order of the haōma-pressing time; oh, orderly juncture of the Order  of the success; oh, orderly juncture of the Order of the lunch-time; oh, orderly juncture of the Order of the evening; oh, orderly juncture of the Order of the time when the songs are heard (the night); oh, orderly juncture of the Order of the dawn.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY1.22" corresp="Y1.22">
            If I was hostile to you,
            either with the mind or with a word or with an action,
            either willingly or unwillingly;
            if I excluded you from this, the sacrifice and the praise, I make for you the preliminary praise, I announce you (to the sacrifice and the praise).
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY1.23" corresp="Y1.23">
            Oh, you orderly junctures of the Order, that are all the greatest juncutres.
            If I was hostile to (all of) you,
            either with the mind or with a word or with an action,
            either willingly or unwillingly;
            if I excluded you from this, the sacrifice and the praise, I make for you the preliminary praise, I announce you (to the sacrifice and the praise).
        </ab>
    </div>
    <div n="2">
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY2.1" corresp="Y2.1">
        I bring with the sacrifice the <em>zaōϑrā</em>;
        I bring with the sacrifice the <em>barəsman</em>;
        I bring with the sacrifice the <em>barəsman</em>;
        I bring with the sacrifice the <em>zaōϑrā</em>;
        I bring with the sacrifice the <em>zaōϑrā</em> together with the <em>barəsman</em>;
        I bring with the sacrifice the <em>barəsman</em> together with the <em>zaōϑrā</em>;
        In this <em>zaōϑrā</em> I bring with the sacrifice this <em>barəsman</em>.
        With this <em>barəsman</em> I bring with the sacrifice this <em>zaōϑrā</em>;
        I bring with the sacrifice this <em>barəsman</em> together with the <em>zaōϑrā</em>;
        I bring with the sacrifice this <em>barəsman</em> together with the <em>zaōϑrā</em>, together with the girdle and spread forward in the proper way.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY2.2" corresp="Y2.2">
        With this <em>zaōϑrā</em> and this <em>barəsman</em> I bring with the sacrifice Ahura Mazdā.
        With this <em>zaōϑrā</em> and this <em>barəsman</em> I bring with the sacrifice the Aməṣ̌a Spəṇta.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY2.3" corresp="Y2.3">
        With this <em>zaōϑrā</em> and this <em>barəsman</em> I bring with the sacrifice the junctures of the Order concerning the parts of the day; 
        I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the Order and of the haōma-pressing time; 
        I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the Order, of the success and of the clan. 
        With this <em>zaōϑrā</em> and this <em>barəsman</em> I bring with the sacrifice Miϑra, of wide pasturelands, with thousend ears, with ten thousend eyes, worthy of a sacrifice in which his name is mentioned; I bring with the sacrifice Rāman who has good fodder. 
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY2.4" corresp="Y2.4">
        With this <em>zaōϑrā</em> and this <em>barəsman</em> I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the Order and of the lunch-time;
        I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the Order, that increases the cattle and of the tribe.
        With this <em>zaōϑrā</em> and this <em>barəsman</em> I bring with the sacrifice
        Aṣ̌a Vahišta and the Fire, son of Ahura Mazda.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY2.5" corresp="Y2.5">
        With this <em>zaōϑrā</em> and this <em>barəsman</em> I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the Order and of the evening;
        I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the Order, that increases men and of the nation.
        With this <em>zaōϑrā</em> and this <em>barəsman</em> I bring with the sacrifice
        the great Ahura Apąm Napat, powerful and bright, and the water created by Mazdā, holder of Order.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY2.6" corresp="Y2.6">
         With this <em>zaōϑrā</em> and this <em>barəsman</em> I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the Order and of the time when the songs are heard (the night);
            I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the Order, that increases everything leading to a good life and of the realm governed by the highest Zaraϑuštra.
            With this <em>zaōϑrā</em> and this <em>barəsman</em> I bring with the sacrifice
            the good, mighty and beneficial Frauuaṣ̌iš of the holders of the Order; I bring with the sacrifice the Women giving birth hordes of men; I bring with the sacrifice the good settlement for the whole year; I bring with the sacrifice the well fashioned and well grown Assault; I bring with the sacrifice the Breaking of the Obstacle created by Ahura, and I bring with the sacrifice the victorious Superiority.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY2.7" corresp="Y2.7">
            With this <em>zaōϑrā</em> and this <em>barəsman</em> I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the Order and of the dawn;
            I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the Order, of the ritual perfomance and of the house.
            With this <em>zaōϑrā</em> and this <em>barəsman</em> I bring with the sacrifice
            Sraōša, kin of Aṣ̌i, well grown, breaking the obstacles, fostering the living beings; I bring with the sacrifice Rašnu, the most righteous, and I bring with the sacrifice Arštāt, that fosters and makes the living beings grow.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY2.8" corresp="Y2.8">
        With this <em>zaōϑrā</em> and this <em>barəsman</em> I bring with the sacrifice the monthly orderly junctures of the Order;
        I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the Order of the interlunation;
        I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the Order of the plenilunium and of the gibbous phase.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY2.9" corresp="Y2.9">
            With this <em>zaōϑrā</em> and this <em>barəsman</em> I bring with the sacrifice the seasonal junctures of the Order; 
            the orderly juncture of the Order of the mid-spring.
            With this <em>zaōϑrā</em> and this <em>barəsman</em> I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the Order of the mid-summer.
            With this <em>zaōϑrā</em> and this <em>barəsman</em> I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the Order of the sowing time.
            With this <em>zaōϑrā</em> and this <em>barəsman</em> I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the Order of the transhumance, of the bridling and the admission of the rams.
            With this <em>zaōϑrā</em> and this <em>barəsman</em> I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the Order of the mid-year articulation.
            With this <em>zaōϑrā</em> and this <em>barəsman</em> I bring with the sacrifice the orderly juncture of the Order of <em>hamaspaϑmaēdaya</em>.
            With this <em>zaōϑrā</em> and this <em>barəsman</em> I bring with the sacrifice the years as junctures of the Order.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY2.10" corresp="Y2.10">
            With this <em>zaōϑrā</em> and this <em>barəsman</em> I bring with the sacrifice all the junctures, that are the thirty three articulations of the Order that are the closest around <em>hāuuani</em>; that belong to the best order, that were announced by Mazdā (to Zaraϑuštra) and proclaimed by Zaraϑuštra (to mankind).
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY2.11" corresp="Y2.11">
            With this <em>zaōϑrā</em> and this <em>barəsman</em> I bring with the sacrifice both, Ahura and Miϑra, the great, unthreatened, holding the order; 
            the stars, the Moon and the Sun together with the plants (the pomegranate twigs) of the <em>barəsman</em>; Miϑra, the national lord of all the nations.
        </ab>        
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY2.12" corresp="Y2.12">
            With this <em>zaōϑrā</em> and this <em>barəsman</em> I bring with the sacrifice Ahura Mazdā holder of wealth and <em>xᵛarənah</em>.
            With this <em>zaōϑrā</em> and this <em>barəsman</em> I bring with the sacrifice the good mighty beneficial Frauuaṣ̌iš of the holders of the Order.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY2.13" corresp="Y2.13">
            With this <em>zaōϑrā</em> and this <em>barəsman</em> I bring with the sacrifice as orderly juncture of the Order the fire, son of Ahura Mazdā, with all the fires.
             With this <em>zaōϑrā</em> and this <em>barəsman</em> I bring with the sacrifice the good, the best waters created by Mazdā, holders of the Order;
            I bring with the sacrifice all the waters created by Mazdā, holders of the Order;
            I bring with the sacrifice all the plants created by Mazdā, holders of the Order.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY2.14" corresp="Y2.14">
            With this <em>zaōϑrā</em> and this <em>barəsman</em> I bring with the sacrifice the beneficial mąϑra full of <em>xᵛarənah</em>; 
            I bring with the sacrifice the law expelling the demons; 
            I bring with the sacrifice the law of Zaraϑuštra; 
            I bring with the sacrifice the long tranmission; 
            I bring with the sacrifice the good vision-soul proper of those performing sacrifices to Mazdā.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY2.15" corresp="Y2.15">
            With this <em>zaōϑrā</em> and this <em>barəsman</em> I bring with the sacrifice the mountain Ušidarəna created by Mazdā that grant the multiple comforts of the Order; 
            I bring with the sacrifice all the mountains that grant the multiple comforts of the Order, created by Mazdā, as orderly juntures of the Order;
            I bring with the sacrifice the strong Kayanid <em>xᵛarənah</em> created by Mazdā; 
            I bring with the sacrifice the strong unreachable <em>xᵛarənah</em> created by Mazdā.
            With this <em>zaōϑrā</em> and this <em>barəsman</em> I bring with the sacrifice the good, bright, great Aṣ̌i, holding offensive power, well-growth, of good benefits; 
            I bring with the sacrifice the <em>xᵛarənah</em> created by Mazdā; 
            I bring with the sacrifice the success created by Mazdā.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY2.16" corresp="Y2.16">
            With this <em>zaōϑrā</em> and this <em>barəsman</em> I bring with the sacrifice the good Daɱa Āfriti; 
            adn I bring with the sacrifice the expert supporter of the Order;
            I bring with the sacrifice the strong and powerful Dāmōiš Upamana, worthy of sacrifice.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY2.17" corresp="Y2.17">
           With this <em>zaōϑrā</em> and this <em>barəsman</em> I bring with the sacrifice these waters, earths and plants;
           I bring with the sacrifice these places, dwellings, pasturelands, residences and ponds;
           and I bring with the sacrifice this lord of the dwelling, who is Ahura Mazdā.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY2.18" corresp="Y2.18">
            With this <em>zaōϑrā</em> and this <em>barəsman</em> I bring with the sacrifice all the greatest junctures: the daily, that of the part of the day, the monthly, the seasonal and of the year.        
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY2.19" corresp="Y2.19">
            With this <em>zaōϑrā</em> and this <em>barəsman</em> I bring with the sacrifice the good, mighty, beneficial Frauuaṣ̌iš of the suporters of the Order.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY2.20" corresp="Y2.20">
        With this <em>zaōϑrā</em> and this <em>barəsman</em> I bring with the sacrifice all the orderly (beings) worthy of sacrifice.
        I bring with the sacrifice all the juntures of the Order,
        in the middle of the haōma-pressing juncture, in the middle of the junture of the clan, in the middle of the juncture, that is all the greatest junctures.
        </ab>
    </div>
    <div n="3">
    <ab xml:id="CABTrY3.1" corresp="Y3.1">
    With the <em>barəsman</em> that has been presented, accompanying the <em>zaōϑrā</em>, at the haōma-pressing time, I bring with the sacrifice the <em>miiazda</em> as nourishment of Hauruuatāt and Amərətatāt, of the generous cow, for the satisfaction of Ahura Mazda, of the Aməṣ̌a Spəṇta; for the satisfaction of Sraōša, of Aṣ̌i's kin, who holds the reward, resilient, who increases the creation.
    </ab>
    <ab xml:id="CABTrY3.2" corresp="Y3.2">
    I bring with the sacrifice the <em>haōma</em> and the <em>parahaōma</em>, for the satisfaction of the <em>frauuaṣ̌i</em> of the supporter of the Order, the Spitama Zaraϑuštra.
    I bring with the sacrifice <em>aēsma</em> and <em>baōiδi</em> for your satisfaction, the fire, son of Ahura Mazdā</ab>
    <ab xml:id="CABTrY3.3" corresp="Y3.3">I bring with the sacrifice the Haoma twigs, for the satisfaction of the good waters created by Mazdā, (mentioning) "for the good waters";
    I bring with the sacrifice the water (mixed) with <em>haōma</em>;
    I bring with the sacrifice the living cow (i.e. "the milk");
    I bring with the sacrifice the plant of the pomegranate tree, placed erected in the proper way, for the satisfaction of the waters created by Mazdā.</ab>
    <ab xml:id="CABTrY3.4" corresp="Y3.4">I bring with the sacrifice this <em>barəsman</em> together with the <em>zaōϑrā</em>, together with the girdle and spread forward in the proper way, for the satisfaction of the Aməṣ̌a Spəṇta;
    I bring with the sacrifice both words well-thought, well-said, well-perfomed;
    And I bring with the sacrifice the hearing of the Gāϑās;
    I birng with the sacrifice the well-perfomed sacred words;
    I bring with the sacrifice this acquisition of the (other) existence, the acquistion of the Order and the satisfaction of the <em>ratus</em> (of all the <em>ratus</em>), for the satisfaction of those supporters of the Order worthy of sacrifice, the material and the mental ones; for the satisfaction of my own soul.
    </ab>
    <ab xml:id="CABTrY3.5" corresp="Y3.5">
    I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings) for the junctures of the Order concerning the parts of the day,
    for the orderly juncture of the Order and of the haōma-pressing time,
    I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings)
    for the orderly juncture of the Order, of the success <note anchored="true">"Success" (<em>sauuah-</em>) refers to the rise of the Sun as the succesful result of the performance of the sacrifice.</note> and of the clan.
    I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings)
    for Miϑra, of wide pasturelands, with thousend ears, with ten thousend eyes, worthy of a sacrifice in which his name is mentioned; for Rāman who has good fodder.
    </ab>
    <ab xml:id="CABTrY3.6" corresp="Y3.6">
    I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings)
    for the orderly juncture of the Order and of the lunch-time,
    I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings)
    for the orderly juncture of the Order, that increases the cattle and of the tribe,
    I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings)
    for Aṣ̌a Vahišta and the Fire, son of Ahura Mazda.
    </ab>
    <ab xml:id="CABTrY3.7" corresp="Y3.7">
    I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings)
    for the orderly juncture of the Order and of the evening,
    I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings)
    for the orderly juncture of the Order, that increases men and of the nation,
    I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings)
    for the great Ahura Apąm Napat and for the waters created by Mazdā.
    </ab>
    <ab xml:id="CABTrY3.8" corresp="Y3.8">
    I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings)
    for the orderly juncture of the Order and of the time when the songs are heard (the night),
    I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings)
    for the orderly juncture of the Order, that increases everything leading to a good life and of the realm governed by the highst Zaraϑuštra,
    I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings)
    for the Frauuaṣ̌iš of the holders of the Order, for the Women giving birth hordes of men, for the good settlement for the whole year, for the well fashioned and well grown Assault, for the Breaking of the Obstacle created by Ahura and for the victorious Superiority.
    </ab>
    <ab xml:id="CABTrY3.9" corresp="Y3.9">
    I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings)
    for the orderly juncture of the Order and of the dawn,
    I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings)
    for the orderly juncture of the Order, of the ritual perfomance and of the house,
    I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings)
    for Sraōša, kin of Aṣ̌i, carrying reward (<em>aṣ̌i</em>), breaking the obstacles, fostering the living beings; for Rašnu, the most righteous, and for Arštāt, that fosters and makes the living beings grow.
    </ab>
    <ab xml:id="CABTrY3.10" corresp="Y3.10">
    I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings) for the monthly orderly junctures of the Order; for the orderly juncture of the Order of the interlunation.
    I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings) for the orderly juncture of the Order of the plenilunium and of the gibbous phase.
    </ab>
    <ab xml:id="CABTrY3.11" corresp="Y3.11">
    I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings) for the seasonal junctures of the Order; for the orderly juncture of the Order of the mid-spring;
    I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings) for the orderly juncture of the Order of the mid-summer
    I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings) for the orderly juncture of the Order of the sowing time;
    I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings) for the orderly juncture of the Order of the transhumance, of the bridling and the admission of the rams;
    I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings) for the orderly juncture of the Order of the mid-year articulationr;
    I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings) for the orderly juncture of the Order of <em>hamaspaϑmaēdaya</em>;
    I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings) for the years as junctures of the Order.
    </ab>
    <ab xml:id="CABTrY3.12" corresp="Y3.12">
    I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings) for all the junctures, that are the thirty three articulations of the Order that are the closest around <em>hāuuani</em>; that belong to the best order, that were announced by Mazdā (to Zaraϑuštra) and proclaimed by Zaraϑuštra (to mankind).
    </ab>
    <ab xml:id="CABTrY3.13" corresp="Y3.13">
    I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings) for both, Ahura and Miϑra, the great, unthreatened, holding the order; for the stars, creatures of Spəṇta Maińiiu;
            for Tištriia, the star bestower of wealth and <em>xᵛarənah</em>, for the Moon with the appearance of a cow, for the bright Sun, of swift horses, that is the eye of Ahura Mazdā, (and) Miϑra, the national lord of the nations.
    </ab>
    <ab xml:id="CABTrY3.14" corresp="Y3.14">
    I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings)
    for Ahura Mazdā holder of wealth and <em>xᵛarənah</em>;
    I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings)
    for the Frauuaṣ̌iš of the holders of the Order.
    </ab>
    <ab xml:id="CABTrY3.15" corresp="Y3.15">
    I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings) for you, the fire, oh son of Ahura Mazdā, with all the fires.
    I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings) for the good waters, of all the waters created by Mazdā and of all the plants created by Mazdā.
    </ab>
    <ab xml:id="CABTrY3.16" corresp="Y3.16">
    I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings) of the beneficial mąϑra, holding the order, of enjoyable existence; of the law expelling the demons, of the law of Zaraϑuštra, of the long tranmission, of the good vision-soul proper of those performing sacrifices to Mazdā.
    </ab>
    <ab xml:id="CABTrY3.17" corresp="Y3.17">
    I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings) of the mountain Ušidarəna created by Mazdā that grant the multiple comforts of the Order and of all the mountains that grant the multiple comforts of the Order, created by Mazdā.
    of the Kayanid <em>xᵛarənah</em> created by Mazdā and the unreachable <em>xᵛarənah</em> created by Mazdā.
    I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings) of the good Aṣ̌i, of the good Cisti, of the good Ərətī, of the good Rasąstāt, of the <em>xᵛarənah</em> created by Mazdā as (synonym of) success.
    </ab>
    <ab xml:id="CABTrY3.18" corresp="Y3.18">
    I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings) of the good Daɱa Āfriti, the expert supporter of the Order and the strong and powerful Dāmōiš Upamana, worthy of sacrifice.
    </ab>
    <ab xml:id="CABTrY3.19" corresp="Y3.19">
    I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings) of these places, dwellings, pasturelands, residences, ponds, waters, earth and plants, of this earth and that sky and the orderly wind, of the stars, the moon, the Sun and the Anaγra Raōcah, that are placed by themselves; and of all the orderly creations of Spənta Maińiiu and of the (she) orderly junctures of the Order.
    </ab>
    <ab xml:id="CABTrY3.20" corresp="Y3.20">
    I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings) of the Ratu (Juncture) Bərəzaṇt, which (is made) of junctures of the Order of the days, of the parts of the day, of the months, of the seasons, of the years, that are the junctures of the Order,(and) of the juncture of the haōma-pressing time. 
    </ab>
    <ab xml:id="CABTrY3.21" corresp="Y3.21">
   I bring with the sacrifice the <em>miiazda</em> as nourishment of Hauruuatāt and Amərətatāt, of the generous cow, for the satisfaction of Sraōša, of Aṣ̌i's kin, brave, whose body incarnates the <em>mąϑra</em>, with a powerful club, ahuric, worthy of a sacrifice with the mention of his name.
    </ab>
    <ab xml:id="CABTrY3.22" corresp="Y3.22">
    I bring with the sacrifice the <em>haōma</em> and the <em>parahaōma</em>, for the satisfaction of the <em>frauuaṣ̌i</em> of the supporter of the Order, the Spitama Zaraϑuštra, worthy of sacrifice with the mention of his name.
    I bring with the sacrifice <em>aēsma</em> and <em>baōiδi</em> for your satisfaction, the fire, son of Ahura Mazdā, worthy of sacrifice with the mention of your name.
    </ab>
    <ab xml:id="CABTrY3.23" corresp="Y3.23">
    I bring with the sacrifice the <em>miiazda</em> as nourishment of Hauruuatāt and Amərətatāt, of the generous cow, for the satisfaction of Sraōša, of Aṣ̌i's kin, brave, whose body incarnates the <em>mąϑra</em>, with a powerful club, ahuric, worthy of a sacrifice with the mention of his name.
    I bring with the sacrifice the <em>haōma</em> and the <em>parahaōma</em>, for the satisfaction of the <em>frauuaṣ̌i</em> of the supporter of the Order, the Spitama Zaraϑuštra, worthy of sacrifice with the mention of his name.
    I bring with the sacrifice <em>aēsma</em> and <em>baōiδi</em> for your satisfaction, the fire, son of Ahura Mazdā, worthy of sacrifice with the mention of your name.
    </ab>
    <ab xml:id="CABTrY3.24" corresp="Y3.24">
    I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings) of the Frauuaṣ̌iš of the suporters of the Order, of the Frauuaṣ̌iš  of the first teachers of the doctrine, who were strong and very victorious; of the Frauuaṣ̌iš of my closest relatives.
    </ab>
    <ab xml:id="CABTrY3.25" corresp="Y3.25">
    I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings) for all the junctures of the Order.
    I bring with the sacrifice (these offerings) for all those benefactors receiving sacrifice, mental and material ones, who are worthy of sacrifice and praise according to the best order.
    </ab>
    </div>
    <div n="4">
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY4.1" corresp="Y4.1">
            These (thoughts) well thought, (these words) well said, (these actions) well performed.
            These <em>haōma</em>, (these) <em>miiazda</em>, (these) <em>zaōϑrā</em>, this <em>barəsman</em> spread forward in the proper way, (this) generous cow,
            Hauruuatāta and Amərətāta, (this) generous cow, (this) <em>haōma</em>, this <em>parahaōma</em>, these <em>aēsma</em>,
            (this) <em>baōiδi</em>.
            This acquisition of the (other) existence, (this) acquisition of the Order and (this) satisfaction of the <em>ratus</em> (of all the <em>ratus</em>), 
            (this) hearing of the Gāϑās, (this) well performed sacred words, (all of them) we hand over (them) and we dedicate (them).
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY4.2" corresp="Y4.2">
            We dedicate these for Ahura Mazdā, for Sraōša of Ašī's kin, for the Aməṣ̌a Spəṇta, for the Frauuaṣ̌iš of the supporters
            of the Order, for the souls of the supporters of the Order, for the Fire of Ahura Mazdā, for the Ratu Bərəzaṇt, for the
            sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification also of each existence holing the order.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY4.3" corresp="Y4.3">
            We dedicate these: these (thoughts) well thought, (these words) well said, (these actions) well performed.
            These <em>haōma</em>, (these) <em>miiazda</em>, (these) <em>zaōϑrā</em>, this <em>barəsman</em> spread forward in the proper way, (this) generous cow,
            Hauruuatāta and Amərətāta, (this) generous cow, (this) <em>haōma</em>, this <em>parahaōma</em>, these <em>aēsma</em>,
            (this) <em>baōiδi</em>.
            This acquisition of the (other) existence, (this) acquisition of the Order and (this) satisfaction of the <em>ratus</em> (of all the <em>ratus</em>), 
            (this) hearing of the Gāϑās, (this) well performed sacred words, (all of them) we hand over (them) and we dedicate (them).
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY4.4" corresp="Y4.4">
            We dedicate these for the Aməṣ̌a Spəṇta, of good command, generous, alwazs living, always thriving, who, male and female,
            live next to Vohu Manah.            
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY4.5" corresp="Y4.5">
            We dedicate these more and more for the prosperity of this house, of the cattle and the men of these house, those 
supporters of the Order already born and those to be born, whose (house) is this.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY4.6" corresp="Y4.6">
            We dedicate these for the good Frauuaṣ̌iš of the supporters of the Order, that are strong and very victorious for the help
            of the supporters of the Order.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY4.7" corresp="Y4.7">
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification of the creator Ahura Mazdā, holder of wealth and
            <em>xᵛarənah</em>, mental spirit; of the Aməṣ̌a Spəṇta.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY4.8" corresp="Y4.9">
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification for the junctures of the Order concerning the parts of the day,
            for the orderly juncture of the Order and of the haōma-pressing time,
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification for the orderly juncture of the Order, of the success <note anchored="true">"Success" (<em>sauuah-</em>) refers to the rise of the Sun as the succesful result of the performance of the sacrifice.</note> and of the clan.
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification of Miϑra, of wide pasturelands, with thousend ears, with ten thousend eyes, 
            worthy of a sacrifice in which his name is mentioned; for Rāman who has good fodder.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY4.9" corresp="Y4.9">
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification for the orderly juncture of the Order and of the lunch-time,
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification for the orderly juncture of the Order, that increases the cattle and of the tribe,
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification for Aṣ̌a Vahišta and the Fire, son of Ahura Mazda.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY4.10" corresp="Y4.10">
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification for the orderly juncture of the Order and of the evening,
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification for the orderly juncture of the Order, that increases men and of the nation,
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification for the great Ahura Apąm Napat and for the waters created by Mazdā.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY4.11" corresp="Y4.11">
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification for the orderly juncture of the Order and of the time when the songs are heard (the night),
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification for the orderly juncture of the Order, that increases everything leading to a good life and of the realm governed by the highst Zaraϑuštra,
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification for the Frauuaṣ̌iš of the holders of the Order, for the Women giving birth hordes of men, for the good settlement for the whole year, for the well fashioned and well grown Assault, for the Breaking of the Obstacle created by Ahura and for the victorious Superiority.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY4.12" corresp="Y4.12">
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification for the orderly juncture of the Order and of the dawn,
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification for the orderly juncture of the Order, of the ritual perfomance and of the house,
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification for Sraōša, kin of Aṣ̌i, carrying reward (<em>aṣ̌i</em>), breaking the obstacles, fostering the living beings; for Rašnu, the most righteous, and for Arštāt, that fosters and makes the living beings grow.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY4.13" corresp="Y4.13">
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification for the monthly orderly junctures of the Order; for the orderly juncture of the Order of the interlunation.
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification for the orderly juncture of the Order of the plenilunium and of the gibbous phase.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY4.14" corresp="Y4.14">
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification for the seasonal junctures of the Order; of the Orderly juncture of the Order of the mid-spring;
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification for the orderly juncture of the Order of the mid-summer
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification for the orderly juncture of the Order of the sowing time;
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification for the orderly juncture of the Order of the transhumance, of the bridling and the admission of the rams;
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification for the orderly juncture of the Order of the mid-year articulationr;
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification for the orderly juncture of the Order of <em>hamaspaϑmaēdaya</em>;
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification for the years as junctures of the Order.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY4.15" corresp="Y4.15">
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification for all the junctures, that are the thirty three articulations of the Order that are the closest around <em>hāuuani</em>; that belong to the best order, that were announced by Mazdā (to Zaraϑuštra) and proclaimed by Zaraϑuštra (to mankind).
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY4.16" corresp="Y4.16">
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification for both, Ahura and Miϑra, the great, unthreatened, holding the order; for the stars, creatures of Spəṇta Maińiiu;
            for Tištriia, the star bestower of wealth and <em>xᵛarənah</em>, for the Moon with the appearance of a cow, for the bright Sun, of swift horses, that is the eye of Ahura Mazdā, (and) Miϑra, the national lord of the nations.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY4.17" corresp="Y4.17">
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification
            for Ahura Mazdā holder of wealth and <em>xᵛarənah</em>;
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification
            for the Frauuaṣ̌iš of the holders of the Order.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY4.18" corresp="Y4.18">
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification of you, the fire, oh son of Ahura Mazdā, with all the fires.
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification for the good waters, of all the waters created by Mazdā and of all the plants created by Mazdā.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY4.19" corresp="Y4.19">
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification of the beneficial mąϑra, holding the order, of enjoyable existence; of the law expelling the demons, of the law of Zaraϑuštra, of the long tranmission, of the good vision-soul proper of those performing sacrifices to Mazdā.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY4.20" corresp="Y4.20">
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification of the mountain Ušidarəna created by Mazdā that grant the multiple comforts of the Order and of all the mountains that grant the multiple comforts of the Order, created by Mazdā.
            of the Kayanid <em>xᵛarənah</em> created by Mazdā and the unreachable <em>xᵛarənah</em> created by Mazdā.
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification of the good Aṣ̌i, of the good Cisti, of the good Ərətī, of the good Rasąstāt, of the <em>xᵛarənah</em> created by Mazdā as (synonym of) success.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY4.21" corresp="Y4.21">
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification of the good Daɱa Āfriti, the expert supporter of the Order and the strong and powerful Dāmōiš Upamana, worthy of sacrifice.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY4.22" corresp="Y4.22">
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification of these places, dwellings, pasturelands, residences, ponds, waters, earth and plants, of this earth and that sky and the orderly wind, of the stars, the moon, the Sun and the Anaγra Raōcah, that are placed by themselves; and of all the orderly creations of Spənta Maińiiu and of the (she) orderly junctures of the Order.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY4.23" corresp="Y4.23">
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification of the Ratu (Juncture) Bərəzaṇt, which (is made) of junctures of the Order of the days, of the parts of the day, of the months, of the seasons, of the years, that are the junctures of the Order,(and) of the juncture of the haōma-pressing time. 
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY4.24" corresp="Y4.24">
            We dedicate these with <em>"xšnaōϑra"</em> for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification of Sraōša, of Aṣ̌ī's kin,
            brave, whose body incarnates the <em>mąϑra</em>, with a powerful club, ahuric.
            We dedicate these with <em>"xšnaōϑra"</em> for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification for the
            Frauuaṣ̌i of the supporter of the Order, the Spitama Zaraϑuštra.
            We dedicate these with <em>"xšnaōϑra"</em> for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification of you, that is the fire,
            oh son of Ahura Mazdā.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY4.25" corresp="Y4.25">
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification of the Frauuaṣ̌iš of the suporters of the Order, 
            of the Frauuaṣ̌iš  of the first teachers of the doctrine, who were strong and very victorious; 
            of the Frauuaṣ̌iš of my closest relatives.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY4.26" corresp="Y4.26">
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification for all the junctures of the Order.
            We dedicate these for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification all those benefactors receiving sacrifice, 
            mental and material ones, who are worthy of sacrifice and praise according to the best order.
            We worship the Aməṣ̌a Spəṇta, of good command, generous.
        </ab>
    </div>
    <div n="5">
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY5.1" corresp="Y5.1">
            Thus, we worship indeed Ahura Mazdā,  who created the cow and the Order, (who) created the (good) waters and the good plants, (who) created
            the lights and the earth, as well as all the good things with his command, greatness and ability.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY5.2" corresp="Y5.2">
            We worship him indeed with the priority of the sacrifices,
            that are aside the cow.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY5.3" corresp="Y5.3">
            We worship him with his ahuric name, "beloved Mazdā", the most beneficial.
            We worship him with our bones and breathings.
            We worship him through the Frauuaṣ̌iš of the holders of the Order, the men and the women.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY5.4" corresp="Y5.4">
            We worship indeed Aṣ̌a Vahišta,
            that is the most beautiful, that is one Ameṣ̌a Spəṇta,
            that is holder of light, that is all the good things.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY5.5" corresp="Y5.5">
            We worship Vohu Mana and the good Xšaϑra,
            the good Daēnā, the good Fsəratu and the food Ārmaiti.
        </ab>
    </div>
    <div n="6">
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY6.1" corresp="Y6.1">
            We worship the creator Ahura Mazdā.
            We worship the Aməṣ̌a Spəṇta, of good command, generous.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY6.2" corresp="Y6.2">
           We worship the orderly junctures of the Order concerning the parts of the day,
           We worship the orderly juncture of the Order and of the haōma-pressing time,
           We worshop the orderly juncture of the Order, of the success <note anchored="true">"Success" (<em>sauuah-</em>) refers to the rise of the Sun as the succesful result of the performance of the sacrifice.</note> and of the clan.
           We worship Miϑra, of wide pasturelands, with thousend ears, with ten thousend eyes, worthy of a sacrifice in which his name is mentioned; for Rāman who has good fodder.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY6.3" corresp="Y6.3">
           We worship the orderly juncture of the Order and of the lunch-time;
           We worship the orderly juncture of the Order, that increases the cattle and of the tribe.
           We worship Aṣ̌a Vahišta and the Fire, son of Ahura Mazda.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY6.4" corresp="Y6.4">
            We worship the orderly juncture of the Order and of the evening;
            we worship the orderly juncture of the Order, that increases men and of the nation.
            We worship the great Ahura Apąm Napat, powerful, bright, of fast horses; we worship the waters created by Mazdā.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY6.5" corresp="Y6.5">
           We worship the orderly juncture of the Order and of the time when the songs are heard (the night);
           we worship the orderly juncture of the Order, that increases everything leading to a good life and of the realm governed by the highest Zaraϑuštra.
           We worship the good mighty and beneficial Frauuaṣ̌iš of the holders of the Order; 
           we worship the Women giving birth hordes of men; 
           we worship  the good settlement for the whole year; 
           we worship the well fashioned and well grown Assault; 
           we worship the Breaking of the Obstacle created by Ahura; 
           we worship the victorious Superiority.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY6.6" corresp="Y6.6">
            We worship the orderly juncture of the Order and of the dawn;
            we worship the orderly juncture of the Order, of the ritual perfomance and of the house.
            We worship the orderly juncture of the Order Sraōša, kin of Aṣ̌i, well grown, breaking the obstacles, fostering the living beings; 
            we worship Rašnu, the most righteous;
            we worship Arštāt, that fosters and makes the living beings grow.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY6.7" corresp="Y6.7">
            We worship the monthly orderly junctures of the Order;
            we worship the orderly juncture of the Order of the interlunation;
            we worship the orderly juncture of the Order of the plenilunium and of the gibbous phase.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY6.8" corresp="Y6.8">
            We worship the seasonal junctures of the Order; 
            we worship the orderly juncture of the Order of the mid-spring;
            we worship the orderly juncture of the Order of the mid-summer.
            we worship the orderly juncture of the Order of the sowing time.
            we worship the orderly juncture of the Order of the transhumance, of the bridling and the admission of the rams.
            we worship the orderly juncture of the Order of the mid-year articulation.
            we worship the orderly juncture of the Order of <em>hamaspaϑmaēdaya</em>.
            we worship the years as junctures of the Order.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY6.9" corresp="Y6.9">
            We worship all the junctures, that are the thirty three articulations of the Order that are the closest around <em>hāuuani</em>; that belong to the best order, that were announced by Mazdā (to Zaraϑuštra) and proclaimed by Zaraϑuštra (to mankind).
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY6.10" corresp="Y6.10">
            We worship both, Ahura and Miϑra, the great, unthreatened, holding the order; 
            we worship the stars, the Moon and the Sun together with the plants (the pomegranate twigs) of the <em>barəsman</em>; 
            Miϑra, the national lord of all the nations.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY6.11" corresp="Y6.11">
            We worship Ahura Mazdā holder of wealth and <em>xᵛarənah</em>.
            We worship the good mighty beneficial Frauuaṣ̌iš of the holders of the Order.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY6.12" corresp="Y6.12">
            We worship as orderly juncture of the Order the fire, son of Ahura Mazdā, with all the fires.
            we worship the good, the best waters created by Mazdā, holders of the Order;
            we worship all the waters created by Mazdā, holders of the Order;
            we worship all the plants created by Mazdā, holders of the Order.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY6.13" corresp="Y6.13">
            We worship the beneficial mąϑra full of <em>xᵛarənah</em>; 
            we worship the law expelling the demons; 
            we worship the law of Zaraϑuštra; 
            we worship the long tranmission; 
            we worship the good vision-soul proper of those performing sacrifices to Mazdā.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY6.14" corresp="Y6.14">
            We worship the mountain Ušidarəna created by Mazdā that grant the multiple comforts of the Order; 
            we worship all the mountains that grant the multiple comforts of the Order, created by Mazdā, as orderly juntures of the Order;
            we worship the strong Kayanid <em>xᵛarənah</em> created by Mazdā; 
            we worship the strong unreachable <em>xᵛarənah</em> created by Mazdā.
            We worship the good, bright, great Aṣ̌i, holding offensive power, well-growth, of good benefits; 
            we worship the <em>xᵛarənah</em> created by Mazdā; 
            we worship the success created by Mazdā.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY6.15" corresp="Y6.15">
           We worship the good Daɱa Āfriti; 
           we worship the expert supporter of the Order;
           we worship the strong and powerful Dāmōiš Upamana, worthy of sacrifice.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY6.16" corresp="Y6.16">
            We worship these waters, earths and plants;
            we worship these places, dwellings, pasturelands, residences and ponds;
            and we worship this lord of the dwelling, who is Ahura Mazdā.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY6.17" corresp="Y6.17">
            We worship all the greatest junctures: the daily, that of the part of the day, the monthly, the seasonal and of the year.        
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY6.18" corresp="Y6.18">
            We worship Hauruuatāt and Amərətāt;
            we worship the generous cow;
            we worship whe orderly juncture of the Order Sraōša, kin of Aṣ̌i, well grown, breaking the obstacles, fostering the living beings.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY6.19" corresp="Y6.19">
            We worship the <em>haōma</em> and the <em>parahaōma</em>.
            We worship now the reward and the <em>Frauuaṣ̌i</em> of the Spitāma Zaraϑuštra, holder of the Order.
            We worship the <em>aēsma</em> and the <em>baōiδi</em>.
            We worship you, the fire, son of Ahura Mazdā, as orderly juncture of the Order.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY6.20" corresp="Y6.20">
            We worship the good, mighty, beneficial Frauuaṣ̌iš of the suporters of the Order.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY6.21" corresp="Y6.21">
            We worship all the orderly (beings) worthy of sacrifice.
            We worship all the junctures of the Order,
            in the middle of the haōma-pressing juncture, in the middle of the juncture of the success and of the clan, in the middle of the juncture, that is all the greatest junctures.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY6.22" corresp="Y6.22">
            
        </ab>
    </div>
    <div n="7">
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY7.0" corresp="Y7.0"/>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY7.1" corresp="Y7.1"/>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY7.2" corresp="Y7.2">
            I place properly the <em>miiazda</em> as nourishment of Hauruuatāt and Amərətatāt, of the generous cow, 
            for the satisfaction of Ahura Mazda, of the Aməṣ̌a Spəṇta; 
            for the satisfaction of Sraōša, of Aṣ̌i's kin, who holds the reward, resilient, who increases the creation.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY7.3" corresp="Y7.3">
            I place properly the <em>haōma</em> and the <em>parahaōma</em>,
            for the satisfaction of the <em>frauuaṣ̌i</em> of the supporter of the Order, the Spitama Zaraϑuštra. 
            I place properly <em>aēsma</em> and <em>baōiδi</em> for your satisfaction, the fire, son of Ahura Mazdā
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY7.4" corresp="Y7.4">
            I place properly the <em>haōma</em> twigs, 
            for the satisfaction of the good waters created by Mazdā, (mentioning) "for the good waters"; 
            I place properly the water (mixed) with <em>haōma</em>; 
            I place properly the living cow (i.e. "the milk"); 
            I place properly the plant of the pomegranate tree, placed erected in the proper way, for the satisfaction of the waters created by Mazdā.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY7.5" corresp="Y7.5">
            I place properly this <em>barəsman</em> together with the <em>zaōϑrā</em>, together with the girdle and spread forward in the proper way, 
            for the satisfaction of the Aməṣ̌a Spəṇta; 
            I place properly both words well-thought, well-said, well-perfomed; 
            and I place properly the hearing of the Gāϑās; 
            I place properly the well-perfomed sacred words; 
            I place properly this acquisition of the (other) existence, the acquistion of the Order and the satisfaction of the <em>ratus</em> (of all the <em>ratus</em>), 
            for the satisfaction of those supporters of the Order worthy of sacrifice, the material and the mental ones; for the satisfaction of my own soul.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY7.6" corresp="Y7.6">
            I place properly (these offerings) for the junctures of the Order concerning the parts of the day, for the orderly juncture of the Order and of the haōma-pressing time, 
            I place properly (these offerings) for the orderly juncture of the Order, of the success and of the clan. 
            I place properly (these offerings) for Miϑra, of wide pasturelands, with thousend ears, with ten thousend eyes, worthy of a sacrifice in which his name is mentioned; for Rāman who has good fodder.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY7.7" corresp="Y7.7">
            I place properly (these offerings) for the orderly juncture of the Order and of the lunch-time, 
            I place properly (these offerings) for the orderly juncture of the Order, that increases the cattle and of the tribe, 
            I place properly (these offerings) for Aṣ̌a Vahišta and the Fire, son of Ahura Mazda.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY7.8" corresp="Y7.8">
            I place properly (these offerings) for the orderly juncture of the Order and of the evening, 
            I place properly (these offerings) for the orderly juncture of the Order, that increases men and of the nation, 
            I place properly (these offerings) for the great Ahura Apąm Napat and for the waters created by Mazdā.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY7.9" corresp="Y7.9">
            I place properly (these offerings) for the orderly juncture of the Order and of the time when the songs are heard (the night), 
            I place properly (these offerings) for the orderly juncture of the Order, that increases everything leading to a good life and of the realm governed by the highst Zaraϑuštra, 
            I place properly (these offerings) for the Frauuaṣ̌iš of the holders of the Order, for the Women giving birth hordes of men, for the good settlement for the whole year, for the well fashioned and well grown Assault, for the Breaking of the Obstacle created by Ahura and for the victorious Superiority.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY7.10" corresp="Y7.10">
            I place properly (these offerings) for the orderly juncture of the Order and of the dawn, 
            I place properly (these offerings) for the orderly juncture of the Order, of the ritual perfomance and of the house, 
            I place properly (these offerings) for Sraōša, kin of Aṣ̌i, carrying reward (<em>aṣ̌i</em>), breaking the obstacles, fostering the living beings; for Rašnu, the most righteous, and for Arštāt, that fosters and makes the living beings grow.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY7.11" corresp="Y7.11">
            I place properly (these offerings) for the monthly orderly junctures of the Order; for the orderly juncture of the Order of the interlunation. 
            I place properly (these offerings) for the orderly juncture of the Order of the plenilunium and of the gibbous phase.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY7.12" corresp="Y7.12">
            I place properly (these offerings) for the seasonal junctures of the Order; for the orderly juncture of the Order of the mid-spring;
            I place properly (these offerings) for the orderly juncture of the Order of the mid-summer
            I place properly (these offerings) for the orderly juncture of the Order of the sowing time;
            I place properly (these offerings) for the orderly juncture of the Order of the transhumance, of the bridling and the admission of the rams;
            I place properly (these offerings) for the orderly juncture of the Order of the mid-year articulationr;
            I place properly (these offerings) for the orderly juncture of the Order of <em>hamaspaϑmaēdaya</em>;
            I place properly (these offerings) for the years as junctures of the Order.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY7.13" corresp="Y7.13">
            I place properly (these offerings) for all the junctures, that are the thirty three articulations of the Order that are the closest around <em>hāuuani</em>; that belong to the best order, that were announced by Mazdā (to Zaraϑuštra) and proclaimed by Zaraϑuštra (to mankind).
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY7.14" corresp="Y7.14">
            I place properly (these offerings) for both, Ahura and Miϑra, the great, unthreatened, holding the order; for the stars, creatures of Spəṇta Maińiiu;
            for Tištriia, the star bestower of wealth and <em>xᵛarənah</em>, for the Moon with the appearance of a cow, for the bright Sun, of swift horses, that is the eye of Ahura Mazdā, (and) Miϑra, the national lord of the nations.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY7.15" corresp="Y7.15">
            I place properly (these offerings)
            for Ahura Mazdā holder of wealth and <em>xᵛarənah</em>;
            I place properly (these offerings)
            for the Frauuaṣ̌iš of the holders of the Order.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY7.16" corresp="Y7.16">
            I place properly (these offerings) for you, the fire, oh son of Ahura Mazdā, with all the fires.
            I place properly (these offerings) for the good waters, of all the waters created by Mazdā and of all the plants created by Mazdā.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY7.17" corresp="Y7.17"> 
            I place properly (these offerings) of the beneficial mąϑra, holding the order, of enjoyable existence; of the law expelling the demons, of the law of Zaraϑuštra, of the long tranmission, of the good vision-soul proper of those performing sacrifices to Mazdā.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY7.18" corresp="Y7.18">
            I place properly (these offerings) of the mountain Ušidarəna created by Mazdā that grant the multiple comforts of the Order and of all the mountains that grant the multiple comforts of the Order, created by Mazdā.
            of the Kayanid <em>xᵛarənah</em> created by Mazdā and the unreachable <em>xᵛarənah</em> created by Mazdā.
            I place properly (these offerings) of the good Aṣ̌i, of the good Cisti, of the good Ərətī, of the good Rasąstāt, of the <em>xᵛarənah</em> created by Mazdā as (synonym of) success.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY7.19" corresp="Y7.19">
            I place properly (these offerings) of the good Daɱa Āfriti, the expert supporter of the Order and the strong and powerful Dāmōiš Upamana, worthy of sacrifice.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY7.20" corresp="Y7.20">
            I place properly (these offerings) of these places, dwellings, pasturelands, residences, ponds, waters, earth and plants, of this earth and that sky and the orderly wind, of the stars, the moon, the Sun and the Anaγra Raōcah, that are placed by themselves; and of all the orderly creations of Spənta Maińiiu and of the (she) orderly junctures of the Order.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY7.21" corresp="Y7.21">
            I place properly (these offerings) of the Ratu (Juncture) Bərəzaṇt, which (is made) of junctures of the Order of the days, of the parts of the day, of the months, of the seasons, of the years, that are the junctures of the Order,(and) of the juncture of the haōma-pressing time.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY7.22" corresp="Y7.22">
            I place properly the <em>miiazda</em> as nourishment of Hauruuatāt and Amərətatāt, of the generous cow, for the satisfaction of Sraōša, of Aṣ̌i's kin, brave, whose body incarnates the <em>mąϑra</em>, with a powerful club, ahuric, worthy of a sacrifice with the mention of his name.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY7.23" corresp="Y7.23">
            I place properly the <em>haōma</em> and the <em>parahaōma</em>, for the satisfaction of the <em>frauuaṣ̌i</em> of the supporter of the Order, the Spitama Zaraϑuštra, worthy of sacrifice with the mention of his name.
            I place properly <em>aēsma</em> and <em>baōiδi</em> for your satisfaction, the fire, son of Ahura Mazdā, worthy of sacrifice with the mention of your name.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY7.24" corresp="Y7.24">
            I place properly the <em>miiazda</em> as nourishment of Hauruuatāt and Amərətatāt, of the generous cow, for the satisfaction of Sraōša, of Aṣ̌i's kin, brave, whose body incarnates the <em>mąϑra</em>, with a powerful club, ahuric, worthy of a sacrifice with the mention of his name.
            I place properly the <em>haōma</em> and the <em>parahaōma</em>, for the satisfaction of the <em>frauuaṣ̌i</em> of the supporter of the Order, the Spitama Zaraϑuštra, worthy of sacrifice with the mention of his name.
            I place properly <em>aēsma</em> and <em>baōiδi</em> for your satisfaction, the fire, son of Ahura Mazdā, worthy of sacrifice with the mention of your name.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY7.25" corresp="Y7.25">
            I place properly (these offerings) of the Frauuaṣ̌iš of the suporters of the Order, of the Frauuaṣ̌iš  of the first teachers of the doctrine, who were strong and very victorious; of the Frauuaṣ̌iš of my closest relatives.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY7.26" corresp="Y7.26">
            I place properly (these offerings) for all the junctures of the Order.
            I place properly (these offerings) for all those benefactors receiving sacrifice, mental and material ones, who are worthy of sacrifice and praise according to the best order.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY7.27" corresp="Y7.27">
            Let approach to us properly (this),
            whose successes set in motion the profits.
            On your behalf, as prayers and keepers of the <em>mąϑra</em>, oh Ahura Mazdā,
            we say, we want and we accept,
            this reward that, worthy of me, you have bestowed for the <em>Daēna</em>s.
            On your behalf, as prayers and keepers of the <em>mąϑra</em>, oh Ahura Mazdā,
            we say, we want and we accept,
            this reward that, worthy of me, you have bestowed for the <em>Daēna</em>s.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY7.28" corresp="Y7.28">
            Give us from it, you there, for this existence and the mental one,
            (give us) this from it, that let us attain your fellowship and the fellowship of the Order for the whole duration (of life).
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY7.29" corresp="Y7.29"/>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY7.30" corresp="Y7.30">
            We worship the Ahuna Vairiia.
            We worship the word well-pronunced.
            We worship the good Daɱa Afritī.
            We worship the strong and powerful Damōiš Upamana, worthy of sacrifice.
            We worship Hauruuatād and Amərətatāt.
            We worship the generous cow.
            We worship the <em>haōma</em> and the <em>parahaōma</em>.
            We worship the <em>aēsma</em> and the <em>baōiδi</em>.
           Glorification of the good Daɱa Afritī!
        </ab>
    </div><div n="8">
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY8.0" corresp="Y8.0"/>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY8.1" corresp="Y8.1"/>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY8.2" corresp="Y8.2">
            I place properly the <em>miiazda</em> as nourishment of Hauruuatāt and Amərətatāt, of the generous cow, the <em>haōma</em> and the <em>parahaōma</em>, <em>aēsma</em> and <em>baōiδi</em>.
            Let approach to us properly the glorification of Ahura Mazdā̊,
            the word of the Ahuna Vairiia well-pronounced, of the good Daɱā Āfriti for the strong Dāmōiš Upamana and of the sacred word of Haoma and Zaraϑuštra, holder odf the Order.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY8.3" corresp="Y8.3">
            Eat this <em>miiazda</em>, you men, who have conquered it with the Order and the attendance!
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY8.4" corresp="Y8.4">
            Oh, Aməṣ̌a Spəṇta! Oh, Daēna of those performing sacrifices to Mazdā! Oh, good (gods and goddess)! Oh, libations!
            Who among those perfoming sacrifices to Mazdā it is called performer of sacrifices to Mazdā and passes himself off as mingling with Aṣ̌a,
            this who (however) destroys with sorcery the creation of Aṣ̌a, that are the waters, the plants and the libations,
            expose precisely him!            
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY8.5" corresp="Y8.5">
            and, who among these adults requested as performers of sacrifices to Mazdā
            does not want to proclaim the words, (this one) goes towards the liability of the one praticing sorcery.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY8.6" corresp="Y8.6"/>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY8.7" corresp="Y8.7"/>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY8.8" corresp="Y8.8">
            May you, Ahura Mazdā, rule at will and at pleasure over your own creatures.
            May you waters, may you plants, may you all good beings having Aṣ̌a as characteristic
            offer yourselves to the holder of the Order at his will, to the holder of the Lie not at his will.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY8.9" corresp="Y8.9">
          May the holder of the Order command what he wants, may the holder of the Lie not command what he wants.
          Away, thrown down, carried out of the creations of Spəṇta Maińiiu, may not command at will what he wishes.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY8.10" corresp="Y8.10">
            May I follow myself, Zaraϑuštra, the leaders of the houses, of the clans, of the tribes and of the nations,
            for the pursuit of the thought, of the word and of the deed of this Daēnā, that is the the one of Ahura and Zaraϑuštra.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY8.11" corresp="Y8.11">
            I bless the feedom and the comfort of the whole existence of the holder of Aṣ̌a.
            I bless the anguish and the discomfort of the whole existence of the holder of Lie.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY8.12" corresp="Y8.12"/>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY8.13" corresp="Y8.13">
            With <em>"xšnaōϑra"</em> for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification of Haōma, who encourages Aṣ̌a.
        </ab>
    </div>
    
    <div n="9">
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY9.1" corresp="Y9.1">
            At the <em>haōma</em>-pressing time, Haōma approached Zaraϑuštra.
            while he was going around the fire purifying it, while he was reciting the Gāϑās.
            Zaraϑuštra asked him: "Who are you, man
            whom I have seen as the most beautiful of all the material existence, of your own sunny immortal life?"
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY9.2" corresp="Y9.2">
            Then, the holder of the order Haōma, who burns badly, answered this to me:
            "I am, oh Zaraϑuštra, the holder of the order Haōma, who burns badly.
            Take me, press me to (make a) drink,
            make a praise to me, as the Saōš́iiaṇt will praise me in the future."
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY9.3" corresp="Y9.3">
            Then said Zaraϑuštra: "Homage to Haōma!
            Who was the first man, who pressed you for the material creation? Which reward was set in motion for him? Which profit came to him?"
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY9.4" corresp="Y9.4">
            Then, the holder of the order Haōma, who burns badly, answered this to me:
            "Vīvaŋᵛhant was the first man, who pressed me for the material creation. This reward was set in motion for him. This profit came to him:
            a son was born to him, who was the bright Yima, of good flocks,
            the greatest holder of <em>xᵛarənah</em> of the born (people), looking like the sun among the men.
            In whose reign he made cattle and men inmortal, that water and plants never dry up,
            that the nourishment to consume did not decrease."
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY9.5" corresp="Y9.5">
            "In the reign of the fast Yima there was no cold and no hot;
            there was no senectitude, no death and no envy created by the Daēvas;
            father and son, the one and the other, advance with the age of fifteen years old,
            as long as the bright Yima, of good flocks, was ruling."
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY9.6" corresp="Y9.6">
            "Who was the second man, who pressed you for the material creation? Which reward was set in motion for him? Which profit came to him?"
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY9.7" corresp="Y9.7">
            Then, the holder of the order Haōma, who burns badly, answered this to me:
            "Āϑβya was the second man, who pressed me for the material creation. This reward was set in motion for him. This profit came to him:
            a son was born to him, Thraētaōna, of a mighty clan."
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY9.8" corresp="Y9.8">
            "who killed Aži Dahāka, of three jaws, of three heads, of six eyes, with thousend skills;
            the very strong demon Druj, evil for all the creations, holder of lie;
            who is the strongest Druj that Aŋhra Maińiiu shaped against the material creation, for the destruction of the living-beings of the Order".
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY9.9" corresp="Y9.9">
            "Who was the third man, who pressed you for the material creation? Which reward was set in motion for him? Which profit came to him?"
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY9.10" corresp="Y9.10">
            Then, the holder of the order Haōma, who burns badly, answered this to me:
            "Thrito, the mightiest of the Sāma, was the third man, who pressed me for the material creation. This reward was set in motion for him. This profit came to him:
            two sons were born to him, Urvāxšaya and Kərəsāspa,
            one as the teacher who runs the ritual,
            the other as a crinkly young man, whose deeds are superior and who carries a club,"
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY9.11" corresp="Y9.11">
            "who killed Aži Sruvara, who devoured horses and men, who was venomous and yellowish;
            above whom a yellowish poison grew as high as a spear,
            above whom Kərəsāspa cooked his meal with a cauldron.
            At the time of Rapiϑβina this scoundrel was becaming hot and was sweating,
            it was treading forward of the cauldron, it was throwing around the boiling water.
            Scared, Kərəsaspa, of virile mind, ran away."
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY9.12" corresp="Y9.12">
            "Who was the fourth man, who pressed you for the material creation? Which reward was set in motion for him? Which profit came to him?"
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY9.13" corresp="Y9.13">
            Then, the holder of the order Haōma, who burns badly, answered this to me:
            "Pourušaspa was the fourth man, who pressed me for the material creation. This reward was set in motion for him. This profit came to him:
            that you, Zaraϑuštra, was born to him, you who are upright, who expells the demons and holds Ahura's doctrine."
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY9.14" corresp="Y9.14">
            "You were heared in Airiiana Vaējah, when you recited the first the Ahuna Vairiia four times taking into consideration the pauses (during the recitation),
            with a very sharp recitation one after the other."
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY9.15" corresp="Y9.15">
            "You, Zaraϑuštra,made all the Daēuua hide in the earth, those who, before this (action) were rushing at this earth with virile figure,
            you who became the strongest, the most brave, the most enthusiastic, the fastest, the most resilient of the creation of both spirits".
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY9.16" corresp="Y9.16">
            Then said Zaraϑuštra: "Homage to Haōma!
            You are the good Haōma well created, the good (Haōma) upright created;
            you have created as good, healer,
            good looking, of good deeds,
            resilient, of yellow colour, with a flexible stem,
            in such a way that you are the best for the one consuming (you), your are the best viaticum for the soul.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY9.17" corresp="Y9.17">
            I demand from you, oh golden, drunkenness,
            offensive power, resilience,
            health, healing,
            prosperity, growth,
            strength all over the body, comprehension of the whole constellation,
            (I demand from you) this, in such a way that I can wander commanding at will among the living-beings, overcoming the hostility, defeating the lie.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY9.18" corresp="Y9.18">
            (I demand from you) this, in such a way that I can overcome the hostilities of all the hostiles, demons and mortals,
            sorcerers and witches; <em>sātars</em>, <em>kavis</em> and <em>karapans</em>;
            scoundrels of two paws, <em>aṣ̌əmaōγas</em> of two paws and wolfs of four paws;
            the army of wide front falling on with deceives.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY9.19" corresp="Y9.19">
            I demand from you this first favour, oh Haōma, you who burn badly: the best bright existence of the holders of the Order, full of comfort;
            I demand from you this second favour, oh Haōma, you who burn badly: health for this body.
            I demand from you this third favour, oh Haōma, you who burn badly: a long life of breathing.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY9.20" corresp="Y9.20">
            I demand from you this fourth favour, oh Haōma, you who burn badly: that I can proceed capable, holding offensive power, sated to the earth, overcoming the hostilities, defeating the lie.
            I demand from you this fifth favour, oh Haōma, you who burn badly: that I can proceed resilient, victorious in the battle, to the earth, overcoming the hostilities, defeating the lie.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY9.21" corresp="Y9.21">
            I demand from you this sixth favour, oh Haōma, you who burn badly: that we can sense first the thief, first the bandit, first the wolf;
            that whoever may not be able to sense us first, that we all sense (them) the first.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY9.22" corresp="Y9.22">
            Haōma distributes power and strength to those who run brave. harnessed, to the battle.
            Haōma gives to those giving birth the possesion of bright sons and an offspring that supports the Order.
            Haōma distributes enlightment and comprehension to those who are seated staying at home studying the Nasks.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY9.23" corresp="Y9.23">
            Haōma distributes soon to those unmarried maids, who are seated unmarried for a long a time, what is real (?) and a partner (who is) being demanded as one of a good insight.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY9.24" corresp="Y9.24">
            Haōma has placed him away of the power, the Kərəsāni, who moans with the concern for the rule,
            who jabbers: "may the Ātravan not wander far away in my land increasing the studies."
            He usurps every growth, he strikes every growth.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY9.25" corresp="Y9.25">
            At your will, oh Haōma, you who commands at will with your own power.
            At your will, you who are acquainted with many words well pronounced.
            At your will, you who are not asking by questioning around the word well pronounced.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY9.26" corresp="Y9.26">
            Mazdā̊ offers to you the girdle made of tufts of wool, adorned with stars, fashioned in the spiritual sphere, as the good Daēnā proper of those performing sacrifices to Mazdā.
            Then you are girdled by this at the summits of the mountains, in order to keep the bridles and the grips of the <em>mąϑra</em>.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY9.27" corresp="Y9.27">
            Oh Haōma, lord of the house, lord of the clan, lord of the tribe, lord of the nation, lord of the wisdom with your intelligence.
            I address you for offensive power and resilience for mí, as well as very releasing nourishment for the body.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY9.28" corresp="Y9.28">
            Move our mind away from the hostiles with their hostilities, away from those irritating,
           and whoever man who is practicing violence at his house, at this clan, at this tribe, at this nation,
           take his power of his feet,
           cover his ears, make his mind broken.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY9.29" corresp="Y9.29">
            "May you not have power over your (daevic) feet, may you not have the control of your (daevic) hands."
            May he not see the earth with the eyes, may he not see the cow with the eyes,
            who violates our mind, who violates our body.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY9.30" corresp="Y9.30">
            Oh golden Haōma, strike the weapon on behalf of the supporter of the Order, if he has been reached, against
            the body of the yellowish horrible snake that throws poison.
            Oh golden Haōma, strike the weapon on behalf of the supporter of the Order, if he has been reached, against
            the body of the bandit, who alienates the gains, scavenger, enraged.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY9.31" corresp="Y9.31">
            Oh golden Haōma, strike the weapon on behalf of the supporter of the Order, if he has been reached, against
            the body of the deceitful man, the <em>Sāstar</em> who keeps up high the (daevic) head.
            Oh golden Haōma, strike the weapon on behalf of the supporter of the Order, if he has been reached, against
            the body of the <em>Aṣ̌əmaōγa</em> who does not hold the Order, who destroys the existence, who puts in the mind the words of this Daēnā, but does not reach (it) with his deeds.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY9.32" corresp="Y9.32">
            Oh golden Haōma, strike the weapon on behalf of the supporter of the Order, if he has been reached, against
            the body of the slut who practices sorcery, who is grieving, who brings punishes with the whip, whose mind vanishes as a wind-blown cloud.
        </ab>
    </div> 
    <div n="10">
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY10.1" corresp="Y10.1">
            May the <em>daēvas</em> and the <em>daēva</em>-worshiper flee now away.
            May the good Sraōša dwell (here).
            May the good Aṣ̌i dwell (here) and may the good Aṣ̌i rest now at this house, which is ahuric, which is (the one) of the Haōma that encourages Aṣ̌a.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY10.2" corresp="Y10.2">
            I praise for you with a word the prior (part) of the mortar, oh you of good insight, that contains (your) branches.
            I praise for you with a word the superior (part) of the mortar, oh you of good insight, where it strikes down with the strenght of a man.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY10.3" corresp="Y10.3">
            I praise the cloud and the rain, that make your body grow at the summit of the mountains.
            I praise the high mountains where you, Haōma, have grown.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY10.4" corresp="Y10.4">
            I praise the wide, broad Earth of enjoyable existence, of good benefits, pregnant for you, oh Haōma holder of the Order.
            I praise the fields, where you grow fragant, fast, <em>carānəm</em> (?),
            and you, oh great, well-grown Haōma, grow at the mountain;
           and you multiply everywhere, and you are indeed the source of the Order.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY10.5" corresp="Y10.5"/>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY10.6" corresp="Y10.6"/>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY10.7" corresp="Y10.7"/>
    </div>
    <div n="22">
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY22.26" corresp="Y22.26">I bring with the sacrifice those Frauuaṣ̌iš, that have been the first of the houses, of the clans, of the tribes and of the nations; that underpined the sky, that underpined the water, that underpined the earth, that underpined the cow, that underpined the children protected in the (wombs of) pregnants, avoiding them to die.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY22.27" corresp="Y22.27">
            I bring in with the sacrifice the Frauuaṣ̌iš both of Ahura Mazdā and the Aməṣ̌a Spəṇta, together with all the Frauuaṣ̌iš holding the order, those of the mental beings worthy of sacrifice.
            I bring in with the sacrifice the Frauuaṣ̌iš of Gaya Marətan, of Zaraϑuštra the Spitāma, of Kavi Vīštāspa, of Isat̰.Vāstra, son of Zaraϑuštra, together with all the Frauuaṣ̌iš holding the order, those of the first teachers of the doctrine.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY22.28" corresp="Y22.28">
            I bring with the sacrifice (the offerings) for each Frauuaṣ̌i holding the Order, that is everywhere in this earth, (already) departed (and) living (at the side of) the skilled, of the woman, of the infant, of the girl, of (the person) working in the fields. They ask for good sacrifices and praises from this house, those that remember (them) and have obtained (them).
        </ab>
    </div>
    <div n="37">
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY37.1" corresp="Y37.1">
            Thus, we worship indeed Ahura Mazdā,  who created the cow and the Order, 
            (who) created the (good) waters and the good plants, 
            (who) created the lights and the earth, as well as all the good things 
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY37.2" corresp="Y37.2">
            with his command, greatness and ability.
            We worship him indeed with the priority of the sacrifices,
            that are aside the cow.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY37.3" corresp="Y37.3">
            We worship him with his ahuric name, "beloved Mazdā", the most beneficial.
            We worship him with our bones and breathings.
            We worship him through the Frauuaṣ̌iš of the holders of the Order, the men and the women.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY37.4" corresp="Y37.4">
            We worship indeed Aṣ̌a Vahišta,
            that is the most beautiful, that is one Ameṣ̌a Spəṇta,
            that is holder of light, that is all the good things.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrY37.5" corresp="Y37.5">
            We worship Vohu Mana and the good Xšaϑra,
            the good Daēnā, the good Fsəratu and the good Ārmaiti.
        </ab>
    </div>
</div>