<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div n="Y">
    <div n="1">
        <ab xml:id="CABTrDrYt1.0" corresp="DrYt1.0">
        With the satisfaction to Ahura Mazdā.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrDrYt1.2" corresp="DrYt1.2">
        With the <em>barsom</em> I bring with the sacrifice the <em>miiazda</em> as nourishment of the creator Ahura Mazdā, holder of wealth and <em>xᵛarənah</em>, mental spirit; of the Aməṣ̌a Spəṇta, oh Hauruuatāt and Amərətatāt, oh generous cow, oh waters and plant, oh firewood and incense, for the satisfaction of Ahura Mazdā̊, of the Aməṣ̌a Spəṇta; for the satisfaction of Sraōša, of Aṣ̌i's kin; (for the satisfaction) of the fire; (for the satisfaction) of Ahura Mazdā as Ratu Bərəzaṇt, that is the Order.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrDrYt1.10" corresp="DrYt1.10">
        I bring with the sacrifice the (edible) offering as nourishment, oh Hauruuatāt and Amərətatāt, oh generous cow, oh waters and plant, oh firewood and incense, for the satisfaction of Ahura Mazdā̊, holder of wealth and <em>xᵛarənah</em>; of the Aməṣ̌a Spəṇta; of the Frauuaṣ̌iš of the suporters of the order, of the Frauuaṣ̌iš  of the first teachers of the doctrine, who were strong and very victorious; of the Frauuaṣ̌iš of the closest relatives, of the worthy of a sacrifice in which his name is mentioned.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrDrYt1.11" corresp="DrYt1.11">
        I bring with the sacrifice the (edible) offering as nourishment, oh Hauruuatāt and Amərətatāt, oh generous cow, oh waters and plant, oh firewood and incense, for the satisfaction of Ahura Mazdā̊, holder of wealth and <em>xᵛarənah</em>; of the Aməṣ̌a Spəṇta; of the Frauuaṣ̌iš of the suporters of the order, of the Frauuaṣ̌iš  of the first teachers of the doctrine, who were strong and very victorious; of the Frauuaṣ̌iš of the closest relatives, of the worthy of a sacrifice in which his name is mentioned.
        </ab>
    </div>
    <div n="2">
        <ab xml:id="CABTrDrYt2.1" corresp="DrYt2.1">
            These (thoughts) well thought, (these words) well said, (these actions) well performed.
            These <em>haōma</em>, (these) <em>miiazda</em>, (these) <em>zaōϑrā</em>, (this) generous cow,
            Hauruuatāta and Amərətāta, (this) water, (this) plant, these <em>aēsma</em>, (this) <em>baōiδi</em>,
            (all of them) we hand over (them) and we dedicate (them).</ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrDrYt2.1" corresp="DrYt2.3">
            We dedicate these: these (thoughts) well thought, (these words) well said, (these actions) well performed.
            These <em>haōma</em>, (these) <em>miiazda</em>, (these) <em>zaōϑrā</em>, (this) generous cow,
            Hauruuatāta and Amərətāta, (this) water, (this) plant, these <em>aēsma</em>, (this) <em>baōiδi</em>,
            (all of them) we hand over (them) and we dedicate (them).</ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrDrYt2.15" corresp="DrYt2.15">
            We dedicate these with satisfaction for the sacrifice, praise, satisfaction and glorification of Ahura Mazdā̊, 
            holder of wealth and <em>xᵛarənah</em>; of the Aməṣ̌a Spəṇta; of the Frauuaṣ̌iš of the suporters of the order, 
            of the Frauuaṣ̌iš  of the first teachers of the doctrine, who were strong and very victorious; 
            of the Frauuaṣ̌iš of the closest relatives, of the worthy of a sacrifice in which his name is mentioned.
        </ab>
    </div>
    <div n="4">
        <ab xml:id="CABTrDrYt4.9" corresp="DrYt4.9">
        We worship Hauruuatāt and Amərətatāt.
        We worship Ahura Mazdā, holder of wealth and <em>xᵛarənah</em>;
           we worship the Aməṣ̌a Spəṇta, of good command, generous.
           I praise, I call, I sing the good, mighty, beneficial Frauuaṣ̌iš of the supporters of the Order.
           We worship (these Frauuaṣ̌iš) of the house, of the clan, of the tribe, of the nation, of (the realm governed by) the highest Zaraϑuštra.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrDrYt4.10" corresp="DrYt4.10">
            And we worship now that Frauuaṣ̌i among all the first Frauuaṣ̌iš, that is (the Frauuaṣ̌i) of Ahura Mazdā,
            that is the greatest, the best, the most beautiful, 
            the most solid, the richest in reasoning, the best looking, who best reaches (the straight ways) in accordance with the Order.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrDrYt4.11" corresp="DrYt4.11">
            We worship now the good, mighty, beneficial Frauuaṣ̌iš of the supporters of the Order,
            those of the Aməṣ̌a Spəṇta, bright, of ntense gaze,
            great, overwhelming, brave, of Ahura (Mazdā),
            who are unthreatened supporters of the Order.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrDrYt4.12" corresp="DrYt4.12">
            We worship now the existence, the Daēna, the perception, the sould and the Frauuaṣ̌i
            of the first teachers, of the hearers of the teachings, of the men of women supporting the Order, that reach the victory for the Order.
            We worship the soul of the generous cow.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrDrYt4.13" corresp="DrYt4.13">
            (We worship the Frauuaṣ̌iš of) those who reach the victory for the Order (and among these), we worship the Frauuaṣ̌i of Gaya Marətan;
            we worship now the reward and the Frauuaṣ̌i of the Spitāma Zaraϑuštra, holder of the Order;
            we worship the Frauuaṣ̌i of the Kavi Vištāspa, holder of the Order;
            we worship the Frauuaṣ̌i of Isat̰.Vāstra, (son) of Zaraϑuštra, holder of the Order.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrDrYt4.14" corresp="DrYt4.14">
            We worship now the existence, the Daēnā, the perception, the sould and the Frauuaṣ̌i of the men and women supporters of the Order, who are the closest relatives, that reach the victory for the Order;
            together with all the Frauuaṣ̌iš supporting the Order: that of the supporters of the Order already departed, that of the supporters of the Order who are alive, that of the unborn men, who are the redesigner Saōš́iiaṇt.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrDrYt4.15" corresp="DrYt4.15">
            We worship now the souls of the dead, that are the Frauuaṣ̌iš of the supporters of the Order.
            We worship now the Frauuaṣ̌iš of all the closest relatives in this house already dead, of the priestly teachers and the priestly pupils, of the men and women supporting the Order.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrDrYt4.16" corresp="DrYt4.16">
            We worship the Frauuaṣ̌iš of all the priestly teachers supporting the Order.
            We worship the Frauuaṣ̌iš of all the priestly pupils supporting the Order.
            We worship the Frauuaṣ̌iš of all the men supporting the Order.
            We worship the Frauuaṣ̌iš of all the women supporting the Order.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrDrYt4.17" corresp="DrYt4.17">
            We worship the Frauuaṣ̌iš of all the infants already instructed supporting the Order.
            We worship the Frauuaṣ̌iš of those living inside the nation supporting the Order.
            We worship the Frauuaṣ̌iš of those living out of the nation supporing the Order.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrDrYt4.18" corresp="DrYt4.18">
            We worship the Frauuaṣ̌iš of all the men supporting the Order.
            We worship the Frauuaṣ̌iš of all the women supporting the ORder.
            We worship all the good, mighty, beneficial Frauuaṣ̌iš of the supporters of the Order, that (existed) since Gaya Maretan (and will exist) until Vərəϑraγna the Saōšiiaṇt.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrDrYt4.19" corresp="DrYt4.19">
            We worship all the Frauuaṣ̌iš of the supporters of the Order.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrDrYt4.21" corresp="DrYt4.21">
            We worship all the orderly (beings) worthy of sacrifice
            in the middle of the haōma-pressing juncture, in the middle of the juncture of the success and of the clan,.
        </ab>
    </div>
    <div n="5">
        <ab xml:id="CABTrDrYt5.2" corresp="DrYt5.2">
            I place properly the <em>miiazda</em> as nourishment of Hauruuatāt and Amərətatāt, oh generous cow, oh waters and plant, oh firewood and incense, for the satisfaction of Ahura Mazdā̊, of the Aməṣ̌a Spəṇta; for the satisfaction of Sraōša, of Aṣ̌i's kin; (for the satisfaction) of the fire, son of Ahura Mazdā.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrDrYt5.10" corresp="DrYt5.10">
            I place properly the <em>miiazda</em> as nourishment of Hauruuatāt and Amərətatāt, oh generous cow, oh waters and plant, oh firewood and incense, for the satisfaction of Ahura Mazdā̊, holder of wealth and <em>xᵛarənah</em>; of the Aməṣ̌a Spəṇta; of the Frauuaṣ̌iš of the suporters of the order, of the Frauuaṣ̌iš  of the first teachers of the doctrine, who were strong and very victorious; of the Frauuaṣ̌iš of the closest relatives, of the worthy of a sacrifice in which his name is mentioned.
        </ab>
        <ab xml:id="CABTrDrYt5.11" corresp="DrYt5.11">
            I place properly the <em>miiazda</em> as nourishment of Hauruuatāt and Amərətatāt, oh generous cow, oh waters and plant, oh firewood and incense, for the satisfaction of Ahura Mazdā̊, holder of wealth and <em>xᵛarənah</em>; of the Aməṣ̌a Spəṇta; of the Frauuaṣ̌iš of the suporters of the order, of the Frauuaṣ̌iš  of the first teachers of the doctrine, who were strong and very victorious; of the Frauuaṣ̌iš of the closest relatives, of the worthy of a sacrifice in which his name is mentioned.
        </ab>
    </div>
</div>