<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div type="ceremony" n="NerZurGereftan">
    <header>
        <creators>
            <creator>Cantera</creator>
        </creators>
        <created>09 February 2020</created>
        <updated/>
    </header>
    <div n="1" type="chapter">
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="NerZurGereftan1.1NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">pas nirang farāhim-*zur gereftan pas zud va raṯvi dar yazišngāh
                šodan va ātaš dar *ādešt bar aforuḫtan va ān kasi ke zud bāšad har do fanān bastan
                va raṯvi dar pas sang-e urvis šodan va āb rā pādyāvi kardan va pādyāvi ān ast ke dar
                barsom čidan gufte budim ke se bār az ān mašrabe-ye bozorg dar mašrabe-ye ḫord
                rizand va az mašrabe-ye ḫord dar mašrabe-ye bozorg rizand va āb rā nik eḥtyaṭ
                konand ke pāk bāšad va pas ruy-e sang-e urvis rā *sukure se tā va ǧāmdān va him va
                pyāle va māhruy va hāvan va daste ān āb pāk šostan va har yek se bār pas zur bar
                gereftan ān ast ke *sukure-ye farāhimdān va *sukure-ye zurdān har do be-dast-e čab
                bar-dārand va āb-e pāk be-šostan va har yek se bār pādyāb karde be-dast-e rāst
                bar-dārand va az ruy-e sang-e urvis bālā dārand</ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="NerZurGereftan1.1NerangEnglish.a"> Then,
                the instructions for the taking of the <em>zur</em> for the <em>farāhim</em> (=
                    <em>parāhum</em>). Then, the <em>zud</em> and the <em>raṯvi</em> have to go to
                the <em>yazišngāh</em> and kindle the fire in the fire-stand. The one who is going
                to be the <em>zud</em> has to tie the two <em>fanān</em> and the <em>raṯvi</em> has
                to go to the other side of the <em>urvisgāh</em> and to make the water pure. This
                making pure of the water is what we have already described in the section about the
                cutting of the <em>barsom</em> (NerBarsomCidan1.5). He should pour three times water from
                the big vessel to the small vessel and from the small vessel to the big one. He should
                treat the water carefully so that it becomes pure. Afterwards he should wash with this
                water the three <em>sukure</em>, the <em>ǧāmdān</em>, the <em>hum</em>, the cup, the
                    <em>māhruy</em>, the <em>hāvan</em> and the pestle on the
                <em>urvisgāh</em>, each one three times. Then, (it follws) the taking of the <em>zur</em> (<em>zurgereftan</em>). It consists of the follwing:  He has to take with the left hand both,
            the <em>sukure farāhimdān</em> and the <em>sukure zurdān</em>, and wash them with pure
            water. Once each one has been cleaned three times, he should take them with the right hand and
            raise them from the stone of the <em>urvis</em>.</ab1>
            </div>
    </div>
    <div n="2" type="chapter">
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="NerZurGereftan2.1NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">āb andar sukure-ye do tā porr kardan </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="NerZurGereftan2.1NerangEnglish.a">He
                should fill the two cups with water. </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="NerZurGereftan2.1NerangTransc.b" xml:lang="Pers">
                <em>us.mībarāma</em> se bār sukure andar bālā va šeib āvardan </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="NerZurGereftan2.1NerangEnglish.b"> At
                †us.bībarāma he should move up and down three times the cups.</ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="NerZurGereftan2.1NerangTransc.c" xml:lang="Pers">pas <em>raθβasca bərəzatō gāθā̊sca srāuuaiiōit̰ </em> sukure andar
                ruy-e sang-e urvis nahādan </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="NerZurGereftan2.1NerangEnglish.c">And then
                at <em>raθβasca bərəzatō gāθā̊sca srāuuaiiōit̰ </em> he should put them on the
                surface of the stone <em>urvis</em>
            </ab1>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <div n="2" type="stanza">
                <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="NerZurGereftan3.2NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">va yek sukure-ye zarr az dast-e čab-e māhruy benahišn </ab1>
                <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="3.2NerangEnglish.a">And he should put
                    a golden <em>sukure</em> on the left side of the <em>māhruy</em>.</ab1>
            </div>
        </div>
    </div>
</div>