<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div type="ceremony" n="ParagnaLL_Nerang">
    <header>
        <creators>
            <creator>Cantera</creator>
        </creators>
        <created>15 February 2020</created>
        <updated/>
    </header>

    <div n="2.1" type="chapter">
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL2.1.1NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">maḥalli ke avestā guyand aivanghan dar tag-e barsom bastan va avestā
                ḫvāndan</ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL2.1.1NerangEnglish.a" xml:lang="Pers">At the place where they recite the <em>avestā</em>, he has to tie
                the <em>aivanghan</em> at the bottom of the <em>barsom</em> and recite the following
                    <em>avestā</em></ab1>
        </div>
    </div>
    <div n="2.2" type="chapter">
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL2.2.1NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">aivanghan bar miyān-e barsom be dasturi ke kosti bar miyān
                mi-bandand pičidan va barsom šemordan va barsom ke kučektar bāšad</ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL2.2.1NerangEnglish.a" xml:lang="Pers">He has to twist the <em>aivanghan</em> in the middle of the
                    <em>barsom</em> in the same way as when they tie the <em>kosti</em>. He has to
                count the <em>barsom</em> and check which is the smaller (branch) of the
                    <em>barsom</em></ab1>
        </div>
    </div>
    <div n="2.2" type="chapter">
        <div n="2" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL2.2.2NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">be aṣ̌əm sar-aš boridan pe vōhū yeki digar yekǧou bolandtar ān
                boridan pe vahištəm bāqi ǧou bolandtar išān sar-aš boridan </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL2.2.1NerangEnglish.a" xml:lang="Pers">At <em>aṣ̌əm</em> he has to cut the end (of the smallest branch). At
                    <em>vohū</em> he has to cut another one one wheat corn longer. At
                    <em>vahištəm</em> he has to cut the other some wheat corn longer (than the
                previous one)<em>barsom</em>.</ab1>
        </div>
    </div>
    <div n="2.3" type="chapter">
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL2.3.1NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">pe <em>š́iiaoθənanąm</em> be-dasturi-ye kosti gereh afgandan </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL2.3.1NerangEnglish.a" xml:lang="Pers">At <em>š́iiaoθənanąm</em> he has to make a knot like in the
                    <em>kosti</em>.</ab1>
        </div>
    </div>
    <div n="3.1" type="chapter">
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K36" xml:id="ParagnaLL3.1.1NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">nirang-e hum čidan be dastur-e barsom čidan wāǧ gereftan va be-hamān
                dastur čidan va se gere-ye hum avval ke ašem vohi čand dar miyān-e angošt negāh
                dārid va har čand ke ḫᵛāhand čidan va fe humdān kardan va be hamān šāḫ be-dastur-e
                barsom čidan va vāǧ be-goftan ān se gere-ye hum ham be fe humdān kardan va sar
                humdān moḥkam kardan va dast az humdān ǧodā kardan va vāǧ tamām be goftan </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL3.1.1NerangEnglish.a" xml:lang="Pers">Instruction for cutting the <em>hum</em> in the same way as the
                    <em>barsom</em>. He should take the <em>wāz</em> and should cut in the same way
                as the <em>barsom</em> , first, three twigs of <em>hum</em> that he held between his
                fingers while (reciting) as meany Aṣ̌əm Vohūs. As many more as he he wants to cut
                and put in the <em>humdān</em>, he should cut them from the same branche and in the
                same manner as the <em>barsom</em> and also take the <em>wāz</em>. He should also
                bring these three twigs to the <em>humdān</em> and finx them on the <em>humdān</em>
                and remove the hand from the <humdān> and conclude the <em>wāz</em></humdān></ab1>
        </div>
    </div>

    <div n="4.1" type="chapter">
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL4.1.1NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">avval nirang urvarān čidan mašrabe-ye āb va fanām va kārd va
                barsom-čin piš-e deraḫt-e urvarān šodan wa fanām bastan xšnaoθra. ahurahe. mazdā̊.
                    <em>aṣ̌əm. vōhū.</em> yek guftan va biḫ-e deraḫt-e urwarān pāk kardan va dast va
                kārd va biḫ-e urwarān b-āb-e pādyāvi pāk šostan </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL4.1.1NerangEnglish.a" xml:lang="Pers">First, the instruction for cutting the <em>urvarān</em>. He should
                go to the tree of the <em>urvarān</em> (pomegranate) (bringing) a watter vessel, the
                    <em>padām</em>, knife and the <em>barsom-čin</em> and bind the <em>padām</em>.
                He should recite <em>xšnaoθra ahurahe mazdā̊ </em> and one Aṣ̌əm Vohū. He should
                purify a branch (?) of the urvarān-tree and wash the hand, the knife and the branch
                of the urvarān with <em>pādyāvi</em>-water. </ab1>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL4.1.3NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">dovvom bār-e digar <em>xšnaoθra. ahurahe. mazdā̊. ašəm. vohū.</em>
                yek ḫᵛāndan dast va biḫ-e urvarān b-āb-e bādyāvi šostan </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL4.1.3NerangEnglish.a" xml:lang="Pers">Second, he should recite another time <em>xšnaoθra ahurahe mazdā̊
                </em> and one Aṣ̌əm Vohū and wash the hand and the branch of the urvarān with
                    <em>pādyāvi</em>-water.</ab1>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL4.1.5NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">va seivom bār-e digar <em>xšnaoθra. ahurahe. mazdā̊. aṣ̌əm. vōhū
                </em> yek guftan va kārd va biḫ-e urwarān be-āb pādyāvi šostan </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL4.1.5NerangEnglish.a" xml:lang="Pers">Third, he should recite another time <em>xšnaoθra ahurahe mazdā̊
                </em> and one Aṣ̌əm Vohū and wash the knife and the branch of the urvarān with
                pādyāvi-water. </ab1>
        </div>
    </div>
    <div n="4.2" type="chapter">
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL4.2.1NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">va <em>aṣ̌əm</em> guftan sar-e ān biḫ-e urwarān boridan
                    <em>vohū</em> guftan wa kārd bar miyān-e ān nahādan <em>vahištəm</em> guftan ān
                biḫ-e urwarān boridan <em>astī. uštā. astī. uštā. ahmāi hiiat̰. aṣ̌āi. vahištāi
                    aṣ̌əm. </em> urvarān čidan hič vāǧ gīrešni-ye digar nadārad wa urvarān pāre pāre
                kardan dar urvarāndān nahādan va dar yazešgāh bordan moḥkam kardan </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL4.2.1NerangEnglish.a" xml:lang="Pers">He should say <em>aṣ̌əm</em> and cut the end of the
                <em>urvarān</em>-branch. He should say <em>vohū</em> and put the knife on the middle
                of it (the branch). He should say <em>vahištəm</em> and cut the
                <em>urvarān</em>-branch. During <em>astī uštā astī uštā ahmāi hiiat̰ aṣ̌āi vahištāi
                </em>, he should tear it off. There is no other <em>wāz</em> to take. He should cut
                in pieces the <em>urvarān</em>, put it on the <em>urwarāndān</em>, bring it to the
                    <em>yazešgāh</em> and deposite it. </ab1>
        </div>
    </div>
    <div n="4.3" type="chapter">
        <div n="3" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL4.3.3NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">va yek <em>aṣ̌əm vōhū</em> goftan <em>aɱāi. raēsca.</em> tā sar va
                yek <em>aṣ̌əm vōhū</em> goftan <em>hazaŋhrəm.</em> se bār tā sar va yek <em>ašem
                    vohu</em> goftan va <em>jasa.mē. auuaŋhe. mazda. </em> se bār tā sar va yek
                    <em>ašem vohu</em> goftan </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL4.3.3NerangEnglish.a" xml:lang="Pers">He should recite one Aṣ̌əm Vohū, (then) <em>aɱāi raēsca</em> until
                the end and one Aṣ̌əm Vohū, (followed by) three times <em>hazaŋhrəm</em> until the
                end. He should recite one Aṣ̌əm Vohū and three times <em>jasa.mē auuaŋhe mazda </em>
                until the end. He should recite one Aṣ̌əm Vohū. </ab1>
        </div>
    </div>
    <div n="5.1" type="chapter">
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL5.1.1NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">nirang ǧām doḫtan naḫost gāv yā gusfand āvordan yā be galle-ye
                išān šodan va ǧāmdān rā se bār b-āb pādyāvi šostan va dast be gāv nahādan <em>aṣ̌əm
                    vohū </em> se goftan </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL5.1.1NerangEnglish.a">The
                instruction for milking the ǧām is, first, to bring a cow or a sheep or to go to a
                herd of these animals, to wash three tims the <em>ǧāmdān</em> with with
                    <em>pādyāb</em>-water. He should put the hand on the cow, recite three Aṣ̌əm
                Vohūs </ab1>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL5.1.2NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers"> va dast be gāv nahādan <em>aṣ̌əm vohū </em> se goftan </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL5.1.2NerangEnglish.a">He should
                put the hand on the cow, recite three Aṣ̌əm Vohūs </ab1>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL5.1.3NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers"> frauuarāne gāh ānče bid gə̄uš tašne gə̄uš urune tauua gə̄uš
                huδā̊ŋhō urune xšnaoθra. y. v. x. f. yaϑā. ahū. vairiiō. zaotā. tā mraotū. agar do
                bid gə̄uš tašne gə̄uš urune yauuākəm gə̄uš huδā̊ŋhō urune xšnaoθra. y. v. x. f. agar
                se bid yaϑā. ahū. vairiiō. zaotā. OD mraotū. </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL5.1.3NerangEnglish.a">(He should
                recite three) the Frauuarāne with the corresponding <em>gāh</em> (with the
                    <em>šnūman</em>) <em>gə̄uš tašne gə̄uš urune tauua gə̄uš huδā̊ŋhō urune
                    xšnaoθra. y. v. x. f.</em> and the <em>wāz-gīrišnīh</em>) from <em>yaϑā ahū
                    vairiiō zaotā</em> until <em>mraotū</em>. If (the cows) are two, then <em>gə̄uš
                    tašne gə̄uš urune yauuākəm gə̄uš huδā̊ŋhō urune xšnaoθra. y. v. x. f. </em>. If
                (the cows) are three, then <em>gə̄uš tašne gə̄uš urune yūšmākəm gə̄uš huδā̊ŋhō urune
                    xšnaoθra. y. v. x. f.</em>. Then, (the <em>wāz-gīrišnīh</em>) <em>yaϑā ahū
                    vairiiō zaotā</em> until <em>mraotū</em>.</ab1>
        </div>
    </div>
    <div n="5.2" type="chapter">
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL5.2.1NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">avval se serešk u zamin duḫtan <em>aša.sara. manaŋha</em> miguyad
                šir u ǧāmdān midušad digar <em>aṣ̌a.sara. vacaŋha</em> miguyad šir u ǧāmdān midušad
                digar <em>aṣ̌a.sara. š́iiaoθəna.</em> miguyad ǧām andar ǧāmdān midušad </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL5.2.1NerangEnglish.a">First, he
                should milk three drops on the earth while he says <em>aša.sara manaŋha</em>. He
                says further <em>aṣ̌a.sara vacaŋha</em> and milks milk into the <em>ǧāmdān</em>. He
                further says <em>aṣ̌a.sara š́iiaoθəna </em> and milks the <em>ǰīwām</em> into the
                    <em>ǰīwāmdān</em>. </ab1>
        </div>
    </div>
    <div n="5.3" type="chapter">
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL5.3.1NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">digar dast-e avar gāv nahāde yā gusfand va <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō
                </em> goftan va <em>yasnəmca. </em> tā sar <em>āfrīnāmi gə̄uš tašne gə̄uš urune
                    tauua gə̄uš huδā̊ŋhō urune</em> se tā har kodām be-vāǧ gerefte bāšand ān vāǧ
                beguyad pas andar yazešgāh bordan moḥkam nahādan pas durtar āyad yek <em>aṣ̌əm vohū
                </em> goftan <em>ahmāi. raēsca.</em> tās sar <em>hazaŋhrəm.</em> se bār tā sar
                    <em>jasa.mē.</em> tā sar <em>ašem vohu</em> yek goftan </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL5.2.1NerangEnglish.a">Further, he
                has to recite two Yaθā ahū vairiiō with the hand on the cow or the sheep and then
                    <em>yasnəmca</em> until the end <em>āfrīnāmi</em> (with the <em>šnūman</em>)
                    <em>gə̄uš tašne gə̄uš urune tauua gə̄uš huδā̊ŋhō urune</em>, one of the three
                ones -- they should say the <em>vāǧ</em> that they have taken (at the beginning).
                Then, he should bring it to the <em>yazešngāh</em> and place it. Then, he should go
                further and say one Aṣ̌əm Vohū and <em>ahmāi raēsca </em> until the end and three
                times <em>hazaŋhrəm</em> until the end. He should recite one Aṣ̌əm Vohū. </ab1>
        </div>
    </div>

    <div n="6.1" type="chapter">
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL6.1.1NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers"> pas varas rā ke az gāv va varazā mičinand dast rā b-āb-e pādyāvi
                pāk bešuyad va ān varas rā be-dast girad se bār b-āb-e pādyāvi bešuyad <em>xšnaoθra
                    ahurahe mazdā aṣ̌əm. vohū.</em> se guftan <em>frauuarāne</em> gāh ānče bid
                    <em>ahurahe mazdā̊ raēuuatō xᵛarənaŋhato xšnaoθra</em> OD <em>frasastaiiaēca.
                    yaϑā. ahū. vairiiō. zaotā.</em> OD <em>mraotū</em></ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL6.1.1NerangEnglish.a">Afterwards,
                they cut the <em>varas</em> from a cow or beef. He washes the hand clean with
                    <em>pādyāb</em> and takes the <em>varas</em> with the hand and wash it three
                times with <em>pādyāvi</em> (and then recites) <em>xšnaoθra ahurahe mazdā</em>,
                three Aṣ̌əm Vohūs and the Frauuarāne with the corresponding <em>gāh</em> (and the
                    <em>šnūman</em>) <em>ahurahe mazdā̊ raēuuatō xᵛarənaŋhato xšnaoθra</em> until
                    <em>frasastaiiaēca</em> and <em>yaϑā ahū vairiiō zaotā</em> until <em>mraotū
                </em> . </ab1>
        </div>
    </div>
    <div n="6.2" type="chapter">
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL6.2.1NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers"><em>aṣ̌əm vōhū</em> čahār guftan ke se <em>ašem vohū</em> az bon ō
                sar šostan va pas se bār ḥalqe begardānand pas yek ḥalqe-ye zarrin b-āb pādyāvi
                bešuyand va ān varas ḥalqe-karde dar gardan-e ān andazand va ān ḥalqe-ye zarrin rā
                be-sar-e barsom-čin konand va yek sukure porr az āb-e pādyāb konand va yek-pāre-ye
                var-e ātaš vaharām dar ānǧā konand yaʾni xākestar-e ātaš šeib-e-ān nahānd (quiere
                decir que colocan las cenizas en su base) čenānke ḫorm-e ātaš bālā na-yāyad va ān āb
                be-ǧuš āyad va panǧāh-o yek bār ān varas b-āb ǧušān foru barand va bar āvarand zud
                āb-e sard b-ānǧā foru rizand </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL6.2.1NerangEnglish.a">He has to
                recite four Aṣ̌əm Vohū. During the third, he has to wash (the <em>varas</em>) from
                the begin to the end. They braid it three times and wash a golden ring with
                    <em>pādyāb</em>. Then they put the braided <em>varas</em> in the the ring neck
                and pit the golden ring next to the <em>barsom-čin</em>. They fill a <em>sukure</em>
                with <em>pādyāb</em> and put some hot ashes of the Ātaš Vaharām in it (viz. the
                    <em>sukure</em>), that is, they put ashes of the fire at its bottom so that the
                smoke of the fire does not go up and the water reaches the boiling point. The bring
                the <em>varas</em> fifty one times to the boiling water and take it out. Immediatly,
                the pour cold water on it. </ab1>
        </div>
    </div>
    <div n="7.1" type="chapter">
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL7.1.1NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers"> digar ān varas az ḥalqe bāz konand se bār b-āb-e pādyāvi bešuyand </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL7.1.1NerangEnglish.a">Then they
                lose again the <em>varas</em> from the ring and wash it three times with
                    <em>pādyāb</em>.</ab1>
        </div>
    </div>
    <div n="7.2" type="chapter">
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL7.2.1NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">čahār aṣ̌əm vōhū čon piš neveštam pas digar be-ḥalqe dar-ārand dar
                hamān ḥalqe-ye zarrin andazand va hezār-o-yek bār b-āb-e pādyāvi foru barand va
                bar-āvarand va varasdān nahand</ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL7.2.1NerangEnglish.a">four Aṣ̌əm
                Vohū as I have written before. Then they wind the <em>varas</em> in the ring and put
                it in the same golden ring. They bring it thousand and one times to the water and
                out of it and lay the <em>varas-dān</em>.</ab1>
        </div>
    </div>
    <div n="7.3" type="chapter">
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL7.3.1NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">va <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō </em> do <em>yasnəmca.</em> tā <em>ahurahe.
                    mazdā̊. raēuuatō. xvarənaŋhatō.</em> sar-aš mohkam be-nahand va dar yazišngāh
                mohkam be-nahand pas yek <em>aṣ̌əm vohū ahmāi raēsca</em> OD <em>hazaŋhrəm.</em> OD
                    <em>jasa.mē</em> tamām ḫᵛāndan </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL7.6.2NerangEnglish.a">Then they
                should recite two Yaθā ahū vairiiō and <em>yasnəmca</em> until (the <em>šnūman</em>
                <em>ahurahe. mazdā̊. raēuuatō. xvarənaŋhatō.</em> and they fix its end and they
                deposite it on the yazešngāh. Then he should recite one Aṣ̌əm Vohū, <em>ahmāi
                    raēšca</em> until <em>hazaŋhrəm</em> and <em>jasa.me. </em> complete.</ab1>
        </div>
    </div>
    <div n="8.1" type="chapter">
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL8.1.1NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers"> pas nirang farāhim-*zur gereftan pas zud va raṯvi dar yazišngāh
                šodan va ātaš dar *ādešt bar aforuḫtan va ān kasi ke zud bāšad har do fanān bastan
                va raṯvi dar pas sang-e urvis šodan va āb rā pādyāvi kardan va pādyāvi ān ast ke dar
                barsom čidan gufte budim ke se bār az ān mašrabe-ye bozorg dar mašrabe-ye ḫord
                rizand va az mašrabe-ye ḫord dar mašrabe-ye bozorg rizand va āb rā nik eḥtyaṭ
                konand ke pāk bāšad va pas ruy-e sang-e urvis rā *sukure se tā va ǧāmdān va him va
                pyāle va māhruy va hāvan va daste ān āb pāk šostan va har yek se bār pas zur bar
                gereftan ān ast ke *sukure-ye farāhimdān va *sukure-ye zurdān har do be-dast-e čab
                bar-dārand va āb-e pāk be-šostan va har yek se bār pādyāb karde be-dast-e rāst
                bar-dārand va az ruy-e sang-e urvis bālā dārand</ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL8.1.1NerangEnglish.a">Then, the
                instructions for the taking of the <em>zur</em> for the <em>farāhim</em> (=
                    <em>parāhum</em>). Then, the <em>zud</em> and the <em>raṯvi</em> have to go to
                the <em>yazišngāh</em> and kindle the fire in the fire-stand. The one who is going
                to be the <em>zud</em> has to tie the two <em>fanān</em> and the <em>raṯvi</em> has
                to go to the other side of the <em>urvisgāh</em> and to make the water pure. This
                making pure of the water is what we have already described in the section about the
                cutting of the <em>barsom</em> (NerBarsomCidan1.5). He should pour three times water
                from the big vessel to the small vessel and from the small vessel to the big one. He
                should treat the water carefully so that it becomes pure. Afterwards he should wash
                with this water the three <em>sukure</em>, the <em>ǧāmdān</em>, the <em>hum</em>,
                the cup, the <em>māhruy</em>, the <em>hāvan</em> and the pestle on the
                    <em>urvisgāh</em>, each one three times. Then, (it follws) the taking of the
                    <em>zur</em> (<em>zurgereftan</em>). It consists of the follwing: He has to take
                with the left hand both, the <em>sukure farāhimdān</em> and the <em>sukure
                    zurdān</em>, and wash them with pure water. Once each one has been cleaned three
                times, he should take them with the right hand and raise them from the stone of the
                    <em>urvis</em>. </ab1>
        </div>
    </div>
    <div n="8.2" type="chapter">
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL8.2.1NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">
                <em>frā.tē. staōmaiδe. ahurāne. ahurahe. vaŋhīš. yasnąsca. vahmąsca. hubərətīsca.
                    uštā.bərətīsca. vaṇta.bərətīsca. yazatanąm. ϑβā. aṣ̌aōnąm. kuxšnīša.</em> āb
                andar sokure-ye do tā porr kardan us.mībarāma se bār sokure andar bālā va šib
                āvardan pas raϑβasca bərəzatō gāϑā̊sca srāuuaiiōit̰ sokure andar ruy-e sang-e urwis
                nahādan </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL8.2.1NerangEnglish.a"><em>frā.tē
                    staōmaiδe ahurāne ahurahe +vaŋhūš yasnąsca vahmąsca hubərətīsca uštā.bərətīsca
                    vaṇta.bərətīsca yazatanąm ϑβā aṣ̌aōnąm †kuxšnīša.</em> He should fill the two
                cups with water. At <em>†us.bībarāma</em> he should move the cups up and down three
                times and then at <em>raϑβasca bərəzatō gāϑā̊sca srāuuaiiōit̰</em> he should put
                them on the surface of the stone <em>urwis</em>. </ab1>
        </div>
    </div>
    <div n="8.3" type="chapter">
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL8.3.1NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers"> pas <em>yaϑā ahū vairiiō</em> do goftan <em>yasnəmca</em> OD
                    <em>āfrīnāmi bərəzatō. ahurahe. nafəδrō. apąm. apasca. mazdaδātaiiā̊.</em> va
                yek sokure-ye zarr az dast-e čab-e māhruy be-nahešn </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL8.3.2NerangEnglish.a">Then, he
                should recite two Yaθā ahū vairiiō and <em>yasnəmca</em> until <em>āfrīnāmi bərəzatō
                    ahurahe nafəδrō apąm apasca mazdaδātaiiā</em> and he sould place a golden cup to
                the left side of the <em>māhruy</em> .</ab1>
        </div>
    </div>
    <div n="9.1" type="chapter">
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL9.1.1NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers"> pas digar haft šāḫ-e hum ke az gere tā gere yek-šāḫ ast pas
                    <em>xšnaoθra ahurahe mazdā̊ aṣ̌əm vōhū</em> se guftan <em>frauuarāne</em> gāh
                ānče bid <em>haomahe aṣ̌auua.zaŋhō xšnaoθra. y. v. x. f. yaϑā. ahū. vairiiō. zaotā.
                    frā. mē. mrūtē.</em> OD <em>mraotū</em>
            </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL9.1.1NerangEnglish.a">Then, again
                the seven hum-twigs. (One twig) is what (goes) from one knot to another knot. Then
                (he should recite) <em>xšnaoθra ahurahe mazdā̊</em> and three Aṣ̌əm Vohūs and the
                Frauuarāne with the corresponding <em>gāh</em> and (with the <em>šnūman</em>)
                    <em>haomahe aṣ̌auua.zaŋhō xšnaoθra. y. v. x. f.</em> (and with the
                    <em>wāz-gīrišnīh</em>) <em>yaϑā. ahū. vairiiō. zaotā. frā. mē. mrūtē.</em> until
                    <em>mraotū</em></ab1>
        </div>
    </div>
    <div n="9.2" type="chapter">
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL9.2.1NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">
                <em>ašem vohū</em> se az sar u bon bešuyad pas u hum-†pālā nahešn </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL9.2.1NerangEnglish.a"> During
                three Aṣ̌əm Vohūs he washes (the seven hum-twigs) from top to botton and he raises
                (them).</ab1>
        </div>
    </div>
    <div n="9.3" type="chapter">
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL9.3.1NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">
                <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō</em> do <em>yasnəmca</em> tā <em>afrināmi haomahe
                    aṣ̌auua.zaŋhō</em> pas se šāh ō dast-e čab-e māhruy nahādan kenār-e zur čahār
                šāh andar hum-pāle gozāštan va digar panǧ pārre-ye urvarām stadan b-āb pādyāvi
                šostan va čahār pārre andar hum-pāle gozāštan va yek pārre andar dast-e čab māhruy
                nahādan kenār-e hum</ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL9.3.1NerangEnglish.a"> (He should
                recite) two Yaθā ahū vairiiō, <em>yasnəmca</em> until <em>āfrināmi</em> (with the
                    <em>šnūman</em>) <em>haomahe aṣ̌auua.zaŋhō.</em> Then, he should put three twigs
                to the left side of the <em>mahruy</em>, next to the <em>zur </em> and leave four
                twigs in the <em>hum-pāle</em>. Then he should take five pieces of <em>urvarām</em>,
                wash them with <em>pādyāvi</em>-water and leave four of them in the
                    <em>hum-pāle</em> and one to the left side of the <em>māhruy</em>, next to the
                    <em>hum</em>.</ab1>
        </div>
    </div>
    <div n="10.1" type="chapter">
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL10.1.1NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">pas digar āb rā be-pādyāvi kardan be-dast šostan va barsom bist-o se
                tā be-aivyanghan gašte be-dast-e čab gereftan barsom-čin bā dast-e rāst gereftan pāk
                šostan va barsom-čin sar-e yek šāh-e barsom gereftan pas <em>xšnaoθra ahurahe mazdā̊
                    aṣ̌əm vohū</em> se <em>frauuarāne</em> gāh-e hāvan <em>frasastaiiaēca ahurahe.
                    mazdā̊. raēuuatō xvarənaŋvhatō xšnaoθra. y. v. x f. yaϑā. ahū. vairiiō.
                    zaotā.</em> OD <em>mraotū </em></ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL10.1.1NerangEnglish.a">Then, he
                should purify the water and wash his hands. He should take the <em>barsom</em> tied
                with the <em>aivyanghan</em> with the left hand and the <em>barsom-čin</em> with the
                right. He should purify them and hold the <em>barsom-čin</em> on the end of a branch
                of the <em>barsom</em>. Then, he shoud recite xšnaoθra ahurahe mazdā̊ and three
                Aṣ̌əm Vohū and the Frauuarāne with the <em>gāh hāvan</em> (and the <em>šnūman</em>)
                    <em>ahurahe mazdā̊ raēuuatō xvarənaŋvhatō xšnaoθra. y. v. x f.</em> (and the
                    <em>wāz-gīrišnīh</em>) <em>yaϑā ahū vairiiō zaotā</em> until <em>mraotū</em>.
            </ab1>
        </div>
    </div>
    <div n="10.1" type="chapter">
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL10.1.1NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">pas ān kasi ke barsom be-dast dārad do <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō </em>
                guftan </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL10.1.1NerangEnglish.a">Afterwards, the one who holds the <em>barsom</em> in the hand has to recite two
                Ahuna Vairiia. </ab1>
        </div>
    </div>
    <div n="10.2" type="chapter">
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL10.2.1NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">pas yek-yek barsom sar čidan va šemordan pas b-āb-e pādyāb šostan
                be-čahār ašem vohū se <em>aṣ̌əm vohū</em> az bon u sar šuyad va yek <em>aṣ̌əm
                    vōhū</em> az sar u bon šuyad va barsom be pāy-e māhruy nahādan </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL10.2.1NerangEnglish.a">AThen, he
                has to cut the end of the barsom, one to one, and count (the twigs) and wash them
                with <em>pādyāb</em>. (He has to recite) four Aṣ̌əm Vohūs. During the three first
                Aṣ̌əm Vohū, he washes them from the bottom to the top and during one Aṣ̌əm Vohū from
                the top to the bottom. He has to put the <em>barsom</em> at the bottom of the
                    <em>māhruy</em>. </ab1>
        </div>
    </div>
    <div n="11.1" type="chapter">
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL11.1.1NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">pas barsom andar miyān-e māhruy nahādan be-har do dast goftan
                    <em>xšnaoθra ahurahe mazdā̊</em> dahan barham nahādan be-wāǧ-e urmazd wa
                amešāsfandān beyāri ḫᵛāndan va setāyešn kardan dahan barham nahādan be-wāǧ-e urmazd
                wa amešāsfandān beyāri ḫᵛāndan va setāyešn kardan </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL11.1.1NerangEnglish.a">Then he
                should put the <em>barsom</em> with both hand on the middle of the <em>māhruy</em>
                and recite <em>xšnaoθra ahurahe mazdā</em>̊. He should close his mouth and recite in
                    <em>wāz</em> the plea for Urmazd and Amešasfandān and praise then. </ab1>
        </div>
    </div>
    <div n="11.2" type="chapter">
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL11.2.1NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">pas barsom andar miyān-e māhruy nahādan be-har do dast goftan
                    <em>xšnaoθra ahurahe mazdā̊</em> dahan barham nahādan be-wāǧ-e urmazd wa
                amešāsfandān beyāri ḫᵛāndan va setāyešn kardan dahan barham nahādan be-wāǧ-e urmazd
                wa amešāsfandān beyāri ḫᵛāndan va setāyešn kardan </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL11.2.1NerangEnglish.a">Then he
                should put the <em>barsom</em> with both hand on the middle of the <em>māhruy</em>
                and recite <em>xšnaoθra ahurahe mazdā</em>̊. He should close his mouth and recite in
                    <em>wāz</em> the plea for Urmazd and Amešasfandān and praise then. </ab1>
        </div>
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL11.2.2NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers"><em>yaθā ahū vairiiō</em> yek gere andar aivyanghan zadan va be
                    <em>š́iiaoθananąm</em> gere saḫt kardan va be dovvom <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō</em>
                dovvom gere zadan <em>š́iiaoθananąm</em> saḫt kardan pas sar-e aivanghan bar barsom
                pičidan har do dast be-barsom māhruy moḥkam nahādan </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL11.2.2NerangEnglish.a">At the
                (first) Ahuna Vairiia, he should tie a knot in the <em>aivanghan</em> and pull it
                tightly at <em>š́iiaoθananąm</em>. At the second Ahuna Vairiia, he has to tie a
                second knot and pull it tightly at <em>š́iiaoθananąm</em>. He should twist the end
                of the <em>aivanghan</em> in the <em>barsom</em> and fix it with both hands to the
                    <em>māhruy</em> of the <em>barsom</em>. </ab1>
        </div>
        <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL11.2.3NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">va ānke ātaš afruzad yek ašəm vohū ḫᵛāndan nik barsom rā benegarand </ab1>
        <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL11.2.3NerangEnglish.a">The one who
            (/when he) kindles the fire, should recite one Aṣ̌əm Vohū and the look attentively at
            the <em>barsom</em>. </ab1>
    </div>
    <div n="11.3" type="chapter">
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL11.3.1NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">pas ān kasi ke barsom be-dast dārad do <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō</em>
                goftan <em>yasnəmca</em> tā <em>āfrīnāmi. ahurahe. mazdā̊. raēuuatō
                    xvarənaŋvhatō</em> beguyad pas dast az barsom vāgirad </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL11.3.1NerangEnglish.a">Then, the
                one who touches the <em>barsom</em> with the hand should recite two Yaθā ahū vairiiō
                and <em>yasnəmca</em> until <em>āfrīnāmi</em> (with the <em>šnūman</em>)
                    <em>ahurahe. mazdā̊ raēuuatō xvarənaŋvhatō </em> and then he releases his hand
                from the <em>barsom</em>. </ab1>
        </div>
    </div>
    <div type="chapter" n="12.1">
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.1.1NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">pas hum pyāle va hum urvarān barad va ān yek sokure-ye ḫāli nahand
                ān kasi ke ātaš miforuzad yek šāḫ-e esm va buy nahand va varsdān piš āwarad sar-aš
                begirad vars rā andar hum pyāle andāzad ān kasi ke hum pyāle be-dast dārad va hāvan
                daste u čab dast-e māhruy ǧā-i ke hum urwarān nahāde ast naheš pas angušt-e čab-e
                ḫod moḥkam var ruy-e ān vars va ḫalqe nahad čenānke vars rā binad pas <em>xšnaoθra.
                    ahurahe. mazdā̊. ašəm vōhū</em> se <em>frauuarāne</em> gāh ānče bid
                    <em>zaraθuštrahe. spitamahe. aṣ̌aonō. frauuaṣ̌əē. xšnaoθra. y. v. x. f. yaϑā.
                    ahū. vairiiō. zaotā.</em> tā <em>mraotū.</em></ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.1.1NerangEnglish.a">Then, he
                brings the <em>hum-pyāle</em>, the <em>hum</em> and the <em>urvarān</em> and puts an
                empty cup. The one who kindles the fire, puts a piece of <em>esm</em> and
                    <em>buy</em>, brings the <em>varasdān</em> nearby, removes its lid and puts the
                vars in the <em>hum-pyāle</em>. The one who has the <em>hum-pyāle</em> has to place
                the <em>hāvan</em> and the pestle on the left side of māhruy where he has put the
                    <em>hum</em> and the <em>urvarān</em>. Therefore, he should put firmly his left
                (hand's) finger on the <em>varas</em> and the ring so that he sees the
                    <em>varas</em>. Then (he should recite) <em>xšnaoϑra ahurahe mazdā̊</em> and
                three Aṣ̌əm Vohūs and <em>frauuarāne</em> with the corresponding <em>gāh</em> (and
                the <em>šnūman</em>) <em>zaraϑuštarahe spitāmahe aṣ̌aonō frauuaṣ̌ə̄ xšnaoϑra ẏ• v•
                    x• f• and ẏaϑā ahū vairiiō zaotā </em> until <em>marotū.</em> . </ab1>
        </div>
    </div>
    <div type="chapter" n="12.2">
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.2.1NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers"><em>ahurāi. mazdāi. haomą. āuuaēδaiiamahi.</em> dast va hum pyāle va
                sokure az ruy-e sang-e urvis bālā dāštan hamān čašm andar him konešn <em>imą.
                    haomąsca. miiazdąsca barəsmaca. aṣ̌aiia. frastarətəm. gąmca. huδā̊ŋhəm.</em>
                čašm andar urvarān konešn <em>imąmca. uruuarąm. haδānaēpatąm. aṣ̌aiia.
                uzdātąm</em></ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.2.1NerangEnglish.a">At
                    <em>ahurāi mazdāi haōmą āuuaēδaiiamahi</em> he should raise the hand, the
                    <em>hum-pyāle</em> and the cup from the <em>urvis</em>-stone. He has as well to
                gaze at the <em>hum</em> at <em>imą haomąsca miiazdąsca barəsmaca aṣ̌aiia
                    frastarətəm gąmca huδā̊ŋhəm</em>. He has to gaze at <em>urvarān</em> at
                    <em>imąmca uruuarąm haδānaēpatąm aṣ̌aiia uzdātąm. </em>. </ab1>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.2.2NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers"><em>aiβiiō. vaŋᵛhibiiō.</em> čašm andar zur konešn <em>imā̊.
                    zaoϑrā̊. haomauuaitīš. gaomauuaitīš. haδānaēpatauuaitīš. aṣ̌aiia. uzdātā̊.
                    aiβiiō. vaŋhibiiō. apəmca. haomiiąm.</em> čašm andar hāvan konešn <em>asmanaca.
                    hāuuana. aiiaŋhaēnaca. hāuuana.</em></ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.2.2NerangEnglish.a">(He has to
                recite) <em>aiβiiō vaŋᵛhibiiō</em> and he has to gaze at the <em>zur</em> at
                    <em>imā̊ zaoϑrā̊ haomauuaitīš gaomauuaitīš haδānaēpatauuaitīš aṣ̌aiia uzdātā̊
                    aiβiiō vaŋhibiiō apəmca haomiiąm</em> and he has to gaze at the <em>hāvan</em>
                at <em>asmanaca hāuuana aiiaŋhaēnaca hāuuana.</em>
            </ab1>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.2.3NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers"> čašm andar vars konešn <em>imąmcā. uruuarąm. barəsmanīm.
                    jaγmūšīmca. aṣ̌aonō. aṣ̌ahe. raθβō. ratufritīm.</em> cašm andar esm va buy
                konešn <em>imąm aēsmąsca baoiδīmca</em> čašm andar ātaš konešn <em>tauua āθrō.
                    ahurahe. mazdā̊. puϑra. vīspaca. vōhū. mazdaδāta. aṣ̌aciϑra. pairica. dadəmahī.
                    āca. vaēδaiiamahī. āat̰. dīš. āuuaēδaiiamahī. </em>
            </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.2.3NerangEnglish.a">He has to
                gaze at the <em>varas</em> at <em>mąmcā uruuarąm barəsmanīm jaγmūšīmca aṣ̌aonō
                    aṣ̌ahe raθβō ratufritīm. </em>; he has to gaze at the <em>esm</em> and
                    <em>buy</em> at <em>imąm aēsmąsca baoiδīmca</em> and he has to gaze at the fire
                at <em>tauua āθrō ahurahe mazdā̊ puϑra vīspaca vōhū mazdaδāta aṣ̌aciϑra pairica
                    dadəmahī āca vaēδaiiamahī āat̰.dīš āuuaēδaiiamahī.</em>
            </ab1>
        </div>
        <div n="13" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.2.13NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">
                <em>āat̰. dīš. āuuaeδaiiamahi.</em> sukure va hum pyāle u ruy-e sang-e urvis nahādan
                    <em>asniiaēibiiō aṣ̌ahe. hāuuanə̄e. aṣ̌aone. aṣ̌ahe. raϑβe. y. v. x. f. āat̰
                </em> dast-e rāst bordan va daste-ye hāvan dar hāvan zadan hāvan †škāftan va bar
                dāštan āvardan-e u dast-e rāst-e zud bar ruy-e sang-e urvis sarnegān kardan daste
                durtar ruy-e sang-urvis nahādan pas <em>āat̰ dīš. āuuaeδaiiamahi. sāuuaŋhə̄e
                    vīsīāica. aṣ̌aone. aṣ̌ahe. raϑβe y. v. x. f. </em>
            </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.2.13NerangEnglish.a">(He must
                recite) <em>āat dīš āuuaeδaiiamahi</em> and place the cup and the <em>hum-pyāle</em>
                on the <em>urvis</em>-stone (while saying) <em>asniiaēibiiō aṣ̌ahe hāuuanə̄e aṣ̌aone
                    aṣ̌ahe raϑβe y. v. x. f. āat̰</em> and bring them to the right and hit the
                    <em>hāvany</em> with the pestle of the <em>hāvan</em>, strike the
                <em>hāvan</em>, take it and bring it to the right hand of the <em>zud</em> and put
                it on the <em>urvis</em>-stone upside-down and then (continue with) <em>āat̰ dīš
                    āuuaeδaiiamahi sāuuaŋhə̄e vīsīāica aṣ̌aone aṣ̌ahe raϑβe y. v. x. f.</em>
            </ab1>
        </div>
        <div n="14" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.2.14NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers"><em>āat̰. dīš. āuuaeδaiiamahi.</em> negah-e ruz va māh har ruz ke
                bāšad az urmazd tā anirān negah-e ruz va māh har dō ke bāšad az urmazd tā anirān
                negah-e ān ruz beguyand har māh ke bāšad negah-e ān māh beguyand tā sar </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.2.14NerangEnglish.a">
                <em>āat̰ dīš āuuaeδaiiamahi</em> and then the <em>negah</em> (patron?) of the
                corresponding day and the month, both, the correpsonding day and month. They say any
                    <em>negah</em> of the corresponding day --between the day Urmazd and the day
                Anirān -- and the <em>negah</em> of the corresponding month until the end. </ab1>
        </div>
    </div>
    <div type="chapter" n="12.3">
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.3.1NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">
                <em>aməṣ̌ā. spəṇtā. huxšaϑrā. huδā̊ŋhō yaz.</em> hāvan-e rāst be-naheš <em>iməm.
                    haōməm. aṣ̌aiia. uzadātąm. yaz.</em> hum va urvarān andar hāvan nahādan
                    <em>imąmca. uruuarąm. haδānaēpatąm. aṣ̌aiia. uzdātąm. yazamaide.</em>
            </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.3.1NerangEnglish.a">(He should
                recite) <em>aməṣ̌ā spəṇtā huxšaϑrā huδā̊ŋhō</em>, turn the <em>hāvan</em> upright,
                (continue with) <em>iməm haōməm aṣ̌aiia uzadātąm yaz.</em>, put the <em>hum </em>
                and <em>urvarān</em> in the <em>hāvan</em> (and continue again with) <em>imąmca
                    uruuarąmca haδānaēpatąm aṣ̌aiia uzdātąm yazamaide.</em>. </ab1>
        </div>

        <div n="6" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.3.6NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">
                <em>yeŋhe.hātąm</em> OD <em>tā̊scā yaz.</em> esm va buy yektā ke nahāde bar u ātaš
                nahešn </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.3.6NerangEnglish.a">(He should
                recite) <em>yeŋhē.hātąm</em> until <em>tā̊scā yaz</em>. He has to put onto the fire
                one piece of the esm and buy that has been prepared onto the fire. </ab1>
        </div>
    </div>
    <div type="chapter" n="12.4">
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.4.1NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">
                <em> aētaṯ. dim. vīspanąm</em> daste-ye hāvan az ruy-e sang-e urvis be-dast
                gereftan <em>mazištəm. dazdiiāi. ahūmca. ratūmca. yim. ahurəm. mazdąm.</em> čašm va
                ruy andar vāḫtar afšānidan <em>snaϑāi. aŋhrahe. mainiiə̄uš. druuatō.</em> yaʾni
                zanešn b-ahreman druvand <em>snaθāi aešmahe xruuī.draōš</em> čašm va ruy andar
                avāḫtar afšānidan yaʾni zaneš be-hišm ḫore-ye vepadraḫš div dādam <em>snaθāi
                    mazaniianąm daēuuanąm</em> čašm va ruy andar avāḫtar afšānidan yaʾni zaneš be
                māzanigān divān dādam <em>snaθāi vīspanąm daēuuanąm</em> čašm va ruy andar avāḫtar
                afšānidan yaʾni zanešn bā hamān divān dādam <em>varənīnąmca druuatąm</em> daste az
                ruy-e sang-urvis bar dāštan se bār bar se sān hāvan zadan yekbār az ānsu ke xoršid
                bar-āyad yeki az ānsuy-e nimruz yeki az ānsuy ke xoršid foru šavad pas daste bar
                dast negāh dāštan. </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.4.1NerangEnglish.a">(He should
                recite) <em>aētaṯ dim vīspanąm</em>, take in the hand the pestle of the
                    <em>hāvan</em> from the <em>urvis</em>-stone (and continue with) <em>mazištəm
                    dazdiiāi ahūmca ratūmca yim ahurəm mazdąm</em>. He should turn his glance and
                face towards the East (and recite) <em>snaϑāi aŋhrahe mainiiə̄uš druuatō</em> --that
                means, the striking of the druvand Ahreman--. At <em>snaθāi aešmahe xruuī.draōš</em>
                he should turn his glance and face to the North --that means, I stroke the div Hišm
                with bloody mace. At <em>snaθāi mazaniianąm daēuuanąm</em> he should (again) turn
                his glance and fce to the North -that means, I stroke the <em>div māzanigān</em>. At
                    <em>snaθāi vīspanąm daēuuanąm</em> he should turn his glance and face to the
                North --hat means, I stroke all divs. At <em>varənīnąmca druuatąm</em> he should
                take the pestle from the <em>urvis</em>-stone and hit the <em>hāvan</em> three times
                and at three sides: once at the side in which the sun goes up, once from the south
                side and once at the side in which the sun goes down. Then he should keep the pestle
                in his hand. </ab1>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.4.2NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">
                <em> fradaϑāi. ahurahe. mazdāi. raēuuatō. xvarənaŋhatō.</em> daste čahār angušt bālā
                bordan yaʾni bozorg dāram ormazd riyōmand ḫorremand rā <em>fradaϑāi. aməṣ̌anąm.
                    spəṇtanąm.</em> čahār angušt digar daste bālā bordan yaʾni bozorg dāram
                amešāsfandān rā <em>fradaϑāi. tištriiehe. stārō. raēuuatō. xᵛarənaŋhatō.</em> čahār
                angušt digar daste bālātar bar dãštan yaʾni bozorg dāram tištar setar-e ormazd-dād
                    <em>fradaϑāi. narš. aṣ̌aonō.</em> cahār angušt digar daste-ye hāvan bālā dāštan
                yaʾni bozorg dāram nar ašu rā <em>fradaϑāi. vīspanam. spəṇtahe. mainiiə̄uš. dāmanąm.
                    aṣ̌aonąm</em> daste-ye hāvan čahār angušt digar bālātar dāštan yaʾni bozorg
                dāram amešāsfandān hamā-ye minuvān va hamā-ye ašuvān pas daste forud āvardan se bār
                ruy-e hāvan gardānidan mes̱l ke xoršid mi-gardad </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.4.2NerangEnglish.a">At
                    <em>fradaϑāi ahurahe mazdāi raēuuatō xvarənaŋhatō</em> he should lift the pestle
                four fingers --that means, I hold big Urmazd, the rich and glorious--. At
                    <em>fradaϑāi aməṣ̌anąm spəṇtanąm</em> he should lift the pestle further four
                fingers --that means, I hold big the Amašasfandān--. At <em>fradaϑāi tištriiehe
                    stārō raēuuatō xᵛarənaŋhatō</em> he should raise the pestle further four fingers
                --that means, I hold big the Amšasfandān--. At <em>fradaϑāi tištriiehe stārō
                    raēuuatō xᵛarənaŋhatō</em> he should lift the pestle further four fingers --that
                means, I hold big Tištar, the star created by Urmazd--. At <em>fradaϑāi narš
                    aṣ̌aonō</em> he should lift the pestle further four fingers --that means, I hold
                big the righteous man--. At <em>fradaϑāi vīspanam spəṇtahe mainiiə̄uš dāmanąm
                    aṣ̌aonąm</em> he should lift the pestle of the <em>hāvan</em> further four
                finger --that means, I hold big the Amašasfandān, all the spiritual ones and all the
                righteous ones--. Then he should put down the pestle and rotate it over the rim of
                the <em>hāvan</em> in the same direction in which the sun rotates.</ab1>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.4.3NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers"> pas čahār <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō</em> ḫᵛāndan <em>yaθā ahū
                    vairiiō</em> avval ḫᵛāndan tā <em>š́iiaoθananąm</em> yekbār hum va urvarān
                kuftan <em>aŋhə̄uš</em> yekbār kuftan <em>mazdā̊</em> yekbār kuftan <em>xšaθrəmca
                    ahurāi ā. yim. darəɤubiiō vāstārəm</em> ḫᵛāndan čahār angušt daste az hāvan ǧodā
                kardan pas <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō</em> dovvom be <em>š́iiaoθananąm</em> do bār kuftan
                    <em>aŋhə̄uš</em> do bār kuftan <em>mazdā</em>̊ do bār kuftan <em>xšaθrəmcā</em>
                tā sar ḫāndan <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō</em> seivom be <em>š́iiaoθnanąm</em> se bār
                kuftan be <em>aŋhə̄uš</em> se bār kuftan va se bār kuftan <em>xšaθrəmcā</em> tā sar
                ḫᵛāndan <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō</em> čahārom tā <em>vāstārəm</em> kuftan va hāvan
                šekāftan </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.4.3NerangEnglish.a">Then he
                should recite four Yaθā ahū vairiiō. He should recite the first Yaθā ahū vairiiō
                until <em>š́iiaoθananąm</em>, when he should pound (the hum and <em>urvarān</em>)
                once; at <em>aŋhəūš</em> he should pound them once; at <em>mazdā</em>̊ he should
                pound them once; at<em>xšaθrəmca</em> he should pound them once. He should recite
                    <em>ahurāi ā yim darəγubiiō vāstārəm</em> and lift the pestle four fingers from
                the <em>hāvan</em>. During the second Yaθā ahū vairiiō, he should pound them at
                    <em>š́iiaoθananąm</em> twice; at <em>aŋhəūš</em> he should pound them twice; at
                    <em>mazdā̊</em> he should pound them twice; at <em>xšaθrəmca</em> he should
                pound them twice. He should recite it until the end. During the third Yaθā ahū
                vairiiō, he should pound them at <em>š́iiaoθananąm</em> thrice; at <em>aŋhəūš</em>
                he should pound them thrice; at <em>mazdā</em>̊ he should pound them thrice; at
                    <em>xšaθrəmca</em> he should pound them thrice. He should recite it until the
                end. During the fourth Yaθā ahū vairiiō until <em>vāstārəm</em> he should pound
                (them) and hit the <em>hāvan.</em></ab1>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.4.4NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">
                <em>mazdā. at̰. mōi. vahištā. srauuā̊scā. š́iiaoϑanācā. vaocā. tā.tū. vohū. manaŋhā.
                    aṣ̌ācā. iṣ̌udəm. stūtō. xšmākā. xšaϑrā. ahurā. fəraṣ̌ə̄m. vasnā. haiϑiiə̄m. dā̊.
                    ahūm</em> in vačast čahār bār ḫᵛāndan hum va urvarān andar hāvan kuftan </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.4.4NerangEnglish.a">
                <em>mazdā at̰ mōi vahištā srauuā̊scā š́iiaoϑanācā vaocā tā.tū vohū manaŋhā aṣ̌ācā
                    išudəm stūtō xšmākā xšaϑrā ahurā fəraṣ̌ə̄m vasnā haiϑiiə̄m dā̊ ahūm</em>. He
                should recite this stanza four times and pound the <em>hum</em> and <em>urvarām</em>
                in the <em>hāvan.</em>
            </ab1>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.4.5NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">
                <em>ā. airiiə̄mā. iš́iiō. rafəδrāi. jaṇtū. nərəbiiascā.6 nāiribiiascā. zaraϑuštrahē.
                    vaŋhə̄uš. rafəδrāi. manaŋhō: yā. daēnā. vairīm. hanāt̰. mīždəm. aṣ̌ahiiā. yāsā.
                    aṣ̌īm. yąm. iš́iiąm. ahurō. masatā. mazdā̊.</em> in vacašt čahār bār ḫᵛāndan har
                yek bār hum va urvarām kuftan hāvan škāftan</ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.4.5NerangEnglish.a">
                <em>ā airiiə̄mā iš́iiō rafəδrāi jaṇtū nərəbiiascā. nāiribiiascā zaraϑuštrahē
                    vaŋhə̄uš rafəδrāi manaŋhō.yā daēnā vairīm hanāt̰ mīždəm aṣ̌ahiiā yāsā aṣ̌īm yąm
                    iš́iiąm ahurō masatā mazdā</em>̊. He should recite this stanza four times and
                each time he should pound the <em>hum</em> and <em>urvarām</em> and hit the
                    <em>hāvan.</em>
            </ab1>
        </div>
        <div n="6" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.4.6NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">
                <em>aṣ̌əm. vōhū.</em> se bār ḫᵛāndan har yek ašəm yekbār zur andar hāvan
                riḫtan</ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.4.6NerangEnglish.a"> He should
                recite three times the Aṣ̌əm Vohū and each time, at <em>aṣ̌əm</em> he shoould pour
                    <em>zur</em> into the <em>hāvan.</em>
            </ab1>
        </div>
        <div n="8" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.4.8NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">
                <em>humaiia. upaŋhā̊. cīšmaide. ahunahe. vairiiehe. aṣ̌aiia. frasrūtahe.
                    hāuuanaiiā̊sca. aṣ̌aiia. fraṣ̌ūtaiiā̊. aršuḫδanąmcā. vacąm. aϑā. </em> daste va
                hāvan čonke ḫoršid gardad va se bār gardeš <em>zī.nə̄. humāiiōtarā. aŋhən</em> hum
                va urvarān kufte andar sar daste-ye hāvan nahādan bordan be-suy-e čab-e barsom
                nahādan </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.4.8NerangEnglish.a">
                <em>humaiia. upaŋhā̊. cīšmaide. ahunahe. vairiiehe. aṣ̌aiia. frasrūtahe.
                    hāuuanaiiā̊sca. aṣ̌aiia. fraṣ̌ūtaiiā̊. aršuḫδanąmcā. vacąm. aϑā.</em> He has to
                turn three times the pestle over around the <em>hāvan</em> in the direction in which
                the sun rotates. At <em>humāiiōtarā. aŋhən</em>, he should hold the pounded
                    <em>hum</em> and <em>urvarān</em> on the tip of the pestle of the
                <em>hāvan</em>, bring it to the left (of the <em>barsom</em>) and put it there.
            </ab1>
        </div>
        <div n="9" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.4.9NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">
                <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō</em> čahār bār ḫāndan va hum va urvarān kuftan b-āb-e zur andar
                kardan va hum pyāle kardan be <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō</em> har čahār <em>yaθā ahū
                    vairiiō</em> hamčenin bāyad kard </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.4.9NerangEnglish.a"> He should
                recite four times the Yaθā ahū vairiiō, pound the <em>hum</em> and <em>urvarān</em>
                and pour it into the <em>zur</em>-water and do it thorugh the <em>hum-pyāle</em>. He
                much do it in the same way dring the recitation of the four Yaθā Ahū Vairiiō. </ab1>
        </div>
        <div n="10" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.4.10NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers"> pas <em>yə̄. səuuištō. ahurō. mazdā̊scā. ārmaitišcā. aṣ̌əmcā.
                    frādat̰.gaēϑəm. manascā. vohū. ḫšaϑrəmcā. sraotā.mōi. mərəždātā.mōi.</em> hum va
                urvarān †ašvārdan <em>ādāi. kahiiāicīt̰. paitī.</em> har se bār ḫᵛāndan pas dast
                andar hāvan nahādan ān sokure-e farāhum-ḫᵛor bar-ruy-e hāvan daste nahādan va ān
                sokure ke šib-e hum-pyāle nahāde ast ke-š farāhum andar-ast be-dast-e rāst bar
                dāštan yek qaṯre be-sokure-ruy-e hāvan kardan bāqi andar farāhum-dān kardan digar
                yekqaṯre be sokure-ye farāhum-dān kardan </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.4.10NerangEnglish.a"> Then,
                (he should recite) <em>yə̄ səuuištō ahurō mazdā̊scā ārmaitišcā aṣ̌əmcā
                    frādat̰.gaēϑəm manascā vohū ḫšaϑrəmcā sraotā.mōi mərəždātā.mōi</em>, squeeze the
                    <em>hum</em> and <em>urvarān</em> (and continue with) <em>ādāi kahiiāicīt̰
                    paitī</em>. He should recite (this stanza) three times. Then he should touch the
                    <em>hāwan</em> with his hand and place the cup for drinking the <em>farāhum</em>
                on the <em>hāvan</em> and pestle. He has then to take with the right hand the cup
                that was placed under the <em>hum-pyāle</em> and in which is contained the
                    <em>farāhum</em> and pour a drop into the cup placed on the <em>hāvan</em>. He
                should pour the rest into the <em>farāhum-dān</em> and pour again a drop into the
                    <em>farāhum-dān</em>. </ab1>
        </div>
        <div n="13" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.4.13NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers">
                <em>at̰. rātąm. zaraϑuštrō. tanuuascīt̰. xvax́iiā̊. uštanəm. dadāitī. pauruuatātəm.
                    manaŋhascā. vaŋhə̄uš. mazdāi. š́iiaoϑanahiiā. aṣ̌āi. yācā. uxδax́iiācā.
                    səraošəm. xšaϑrəmcā.</em> pas ān hum va urvarān kufte andar guše-ye sang-e urvis
                nahādan vars andar hum pyāle gozāštan pas dast be-pādyāb bordan ān hum va ān urvarān
                ke be-dast-e čab nahāde ast āvardan hum-pyāle nahādan ān zur ke be-dast-e čab nahāde
                ast āvardan piš-e hum-pyāle nahādan pas qatre-ye šir andar ǧām-dān riḫtan az ān
                riḫtan az ān naguftim ānǧā <em>imąmcā. gąm. jīuuiiąm.</em> čon šir nabud be-kār ne
                pas be-dast-e čab barsom ke andar māhruy nahāde gereftan ān kasi ke ḫᵛāhad kardan
                    <em>yaθā ahū vairiiō</em> ḫᵛāndan dast be-pādyāvi bar-ā-bar †ādošt be-istādan
                    <em>nəmastə. ātarš. mazdā̊. ahurahe. huδā̊. mazišta. yazata. xšnaōϑra. ahurahe.
                    mazdā̊. aṣ̌əm. vohū. frauuarāne.</em> gāh-e hāvan <em>tauua. ātarš. puθra.
                    ahurahe. mazdā̊. x. y. v. x. f. yaθā. ahū. vairiiō. yō. zaōtā. frā. mē.
                    mrūtē.</em> ānkas ke dast andar barsom dārad <em>aθā. ratuš.</em> kardan dast-e
                čab ādošt šodan ādošt šostan <em>aṣ̌əm vohū</em> se ḫᵛāndan ādošt šostan az čab tā
                rāst va miyān-e ādošt šostan </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.4.13NerangEnglish.a">
                <em>at̰ rātąm zaraϑuštrō tanuuascīt̰ xvax́iiā̊ uštanəm dadāitī pauruuatātəm
                    manaŋhascā vaŋhə̄uš mazdāi š́iiaoϑanahiiā aṣ̌āi yācā uxδax́iiācā səraošəm
                    xšaϑrəmcā</em>. Thereafter, he should put the pounded <em>hum</em> and
                    <em>urvarām</em> at the corner of the <em>urvis</em>-stone and put the
                    <em>varas</em> inside the <em>hum</em>-cup. Then he should wash his hand with
                    <em>pādyāb</em> and bring the <em>hum</em> and <em>urvarān</em> that were put to
                the left and put them in the <em>hum</em>-cup. Afterwards, he should bring and place
                next to the <em>hum</em>- cup. Then he should pour a drop of milk into the
                    <em>ǧāmdān</em>. I have not described how to pour. Here it does not apply (the
                recitation of) <em>imą̇mcā. gą̇m. jīuuīą̇m,</em> since there is no milk. Then, he
                should take the <em>barsom</em> that has been placed on the <em>māhruy</em> with the
                left hand. The one who wishes to perform (the liturgy) should recite a Yaθā ahū
                variiō, wash his hands and stand in front of <em>ādošt</em> (and recite)
                    <em>nəmastə. ātarš. mazdā̊. ahurahe. huδā̊. mazišta. yazata. xšnaōϑra. ahurahe.
                    mazdā̊,</em> one Aṣ̌əm Vohū and the <em>frauuarāne</em> with the <em>gāh-e
                    hāvan</em> (and the <em> šnūman</em>) <em>tauua. ātarš. puθra. ahurahe. mazdā̊.
                    x. y. v. x. f.</em> (and with the <em>wāz-gīrišnīh</em>) <em>yaθā. ahū. vairiiō.
                    yō. zaōtā. frā. mē. mrūtē.</em>
            </ab1>
        </div>
    </div>
    <div type="chapter" n="12.5">
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.5.1NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers"> pas ānke dast avar barsom dārad <em>yaθā. ahū. vairiiō.</em> dō
                ḫᵛāndan <em>yasnəmca</em> tā <em>āfrīnāmi. zaraθuštrahe. spitamahe. aṣ̌aōnō.
                    frauuaṣ̌əe</em> pas dast az barsom bar dāštan az pas sang-e urvis bedar āmadan </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.5.1NerangEnglish.a">Thereafter, the one who holds his hand on the barsom should recite two Yaθā ahū
                vairiiō and <em>yasnəmca</em> until <em>āfrīnāmi. zaraθuštrahe. spitamahe. aṣ̌aōnō.
                    frauuaṣ̌əe.</em> Then, he has to remove his hand from the <em>barsom</em> and go
                outside passing the <em>urvis</em>-stone. </ab1>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="stanza">
            <ab1 n="NerangTransc.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.5.3NerangTransc.a" xml:lang="Pers"> yek ašem vohu yek <em>aɱāi. raēšca.</em> OD <em>hazaŋrəm</em> OD
                    <em>jasa.mē</em> tā sar goftan pas is̱ā ahu vairyu ḫᵛāndan ān kasi ke yašt
                mikonad pas urvisgāh šodan yašt tā sar tamām ḫᵛāndan har ḫšnīman ke ḫᵛāhad šāyad
                ellā nu-nāvar visperad-e ruz-e avval dovvom čon yašt tamām šod †zud ān farāhim
                nahāde in avestā ḫāndan <em>rātōiš. darəgō.bāzāuš. nāšū. paitī.viiādā̊.
                    paitī.sə̄ṇdā̊. mātarō. jītaiiō. yeŋ́hē.hātąm</em> tā sar ḫᵛāndan
                    <em>yeŋ́hē.hātąm</em> tā sar ḫᵛāndan ānkas ke yašt karde bāšad urvarān az no
                čidan va ǧām az no duḫtan barsom bist o se az no čidan vars rā be-hamān dastur-e
                ruz-e avval šostan be-ḫalqe kardan va nahādan va digar ruz sāǧešn tamām kardan
                be-hamān dastur ruz-e avval farāhim gereftan moḥkam nahādan čon yašt tamām šod digar
                ruz farāhim be-hamān dastur be-āb ravān riḫtan digar ānkas ke yašt karde bāšad
                digar urvarān no čidan va barsom si o panǧ tā čidan ǧām duḫtan vars rā be-hamān
                dastur šostan ḫalqe kardan hazār va yekbār be-āb forubordan va āvardan digar ruz
                be-hamām dastur-e ruz-e avval hamān sāǧešn ḫub nahādan farāhim va stāyeš ḫᵛāndan
                farāhim moḥkam nahādan agar gahanbār bāšad bāšad visperad be-ḫšnumaine gahanbār
                kardan agar gahanbār na-bāšad visperad be-ḫšnumane-e ruz kardan va yā ašuvān čon
                yašt tamām kardan zur dar āb riḫtan ān farāhim rā moḥkam nahādan har bār ke yašti
                konand ān farāhim gerd kardan qatre-ye dar farāhim-dān bar sar-e hāvan nahādan
                čenānke rasm ast farāhim barāy-e ān-ast yazešn bā-in farāhim va rastat (?) va
                ǧāme-ye pāk va sāǧešn-e pāk va maqām-e pāk va del-e pāk va ḫᵛāndan-e avestā-ye
                dorost farmude-ye dastur ānče az yazdān va amāšasfandān va ānče az yazdān be-ḫᵛāhad
                be-resad in-ast neyrang farāhim gereftan </ab1>
            <ab1 n="NerangEnglish.a" source="K7c" xml:id="ParagnaLL12.5.3NerangEnglish.a">Then he
                should recite one Aṣ̌əm Vohū, one <em>aɱāi raēšca</em> until <em>jasa.mē</em> until the end. Then
                    he shoud recite one Yaθā Ahū vairiiō. The one who will perform the <em>yašt</em> should
                    go to the <em>urvisgāh</em> and recite the <em>yašt</em> until the end. He might use whatever
                    <em>šnūman</em> he likes except the one for <em>nu-nāvar</em> or the <em>visperad</em> of the first day.
                    Secondly, when he has completed the yašt, the <em>zut</em> should recite following <em>avestā</em>
                    after having put the (remaining) <em>farāhim</em>: <em>rātōiš darəgō.bāzāuš nāšū
                    paitī.viiādā̊ paitī.sə̄ṇdā̊ mātarō jītaiiō.</em> He should then recite a Yeŋ́hē.hātąm
                    until the end. The one who will have performed the <em>yašt</em>, he should cut
                    anew the <em>varas</em>, milk anew the <em>ǧām</em>, cut again the twenty-three twigs of the
                    <em>barsom</em>. He should wash the <em>varas</em> according to the instructions for the first day,
                    twist it in the ring, put it in its place. Next day he should complete the
                    preparatives according to the instruction for the first day. He should take the
                    <em>farāhim</em>, deposite it and when the <em>yašt</em> has been completed, he should pour the
                   <em> farāhim</em> next day into a waterstream following the same instructions as for the
                    first day. The one who will have performed the <em>yašt</em>, he shoud cut again anew the
                    <em>urvarān</em>, cut the thirty-five twigs of the <em>barsom</em>, milk the <em>ǧām</em>, wash the <em>varas</em>
                    according to the same instructions and twist it in the ring. He should immerse
                    and take it out the water thousand and one times. Next day, he should dispose
                    correctly all <em>sāǧešn</em> according to the same instructions of the first day. He
                    should recite the <em>farāhim</em> and the <em>setāyeš</em>, put the <em>farāhim</em> at its place. Each
                    time that they perform a <em>yašt</em>, they should get (new) <em>farāhim</em>, (pour) a drop into
                    the <em>farāhim-dān</em> and put it on the <em>hāvan</em> as it is the custom. The <em>farāhim</em> is to
                    that purpose. The <em>yazešn</em> (should be performed) with this <em>farāhim </em>... (?), with
                    pure clothes, pure <em>sāǧešn</em>, at a pure place, with a pure heart and with a correct
                    recitation of the <em>avestā</em> according to the instructions. Might he obtain whatever
                    he requires from the gods and the Amašāsfandān, whatever he requires from the
                    gods. This is the instruction for getting the <em>farāhim</em>.
            </ab1>
        </div>
    </div>
</div>